<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ovid's Tristia, containing five books of mournful elegies which he sweetly composed in the midst of his adversity, while he liv'd in Tomos, a city of Pontus, where he died after seven years banishment from Rome / translated into English by W.S.</title>
            <title>Tristia. English</title>
            <author>Ovid, 43 B.C.-17 or 18 A.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9375</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12329559</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12329559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59618</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59618)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 644:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ovid's Tristia, containing five books of mournful elegies which he sweetly composed in the midst of his adversity, while he liv'd in Tomos, a city of Pontus, where he died after seven years banishment from Rome / translated into English by W.S.</title>
                  <title>Tristia. English</title>
                  <author>Ovid, 43 B.C.-17 or 18 A.D.</author>
                  <author>W. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The fourth edition, corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[119] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Clark, and are to be sold by Thomas Williams  ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added t.p., engraved.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>OVIDS TRISTIA</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Containinge fiue Bookes of mournfull Elegies which hee ſweetly compoſed in the midst of his aduerſitie, while hee liu'd in Tomos a Cittie of Pontus where hee dyed after ſeauen yeares Banishment from Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Translated into English by W. S.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Veniam pro laude peto—</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by Andrew Clark.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <byline>T. Cecill. sculp.</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:2"/>
               <head>The Explantion of the Frontiſpiece.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>AUguſtus Caeſar</hi> in the front doth ſtand,</l>
               <l>Who baniſh'd <hi>Ovid</hi> to the <hi>Pontick</hi> land.</l>
               <l>One ſide ſhews <hi>Rome,</hi> the other doth preſent,</l>
               <l>The Ship which carried him to baniſhment.</l>
               <l>A happy Pyramid 'its ſelf doth raiſe,</l>
               <l>Built on thoſe Books from whence he got his praiſe.</l>
               <l>The ſable Pyramid doth likewiſe ſhow,</l>
               <l>That his ruine from the <hi>Art of Love</hi> did grow.</l>
               <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neath poor
<hi>Ovid</hi> reſts his weary head</l>
               <l>Upon his Coffin, when all hope was fled.</l>
               <l>And thereupon his wreath of Bayes doth lye,</l>
               <l>To ſhew he did in <hi>Pontus</hi> baniſh'd dye.</l>
               <l>But yet his Muſe new life to him doth give,</l>
               <l>And by his lines ſweet <hi>Ovid</hi> ſtill doth live,</l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Vade Liber mundo, Dominus fuit exu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; inde</l>
                  <l>Diſce pati á Domino, fer mala, vade Liber.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:2"/>
            <p>OVID's TRISTIA, CONTAINING Five Books of mournful
<hi>ELEGIES.</hi> Which he ſweetly compoſed in the midſt of his Adverſity, while he liv'd in <hi>Tomos</hi> a City of <hi>PONT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> Where he died after Seven Years Baniſhment from <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>W. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Veniam pro laude peto.—</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The fourth Edition, Corrected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Andrew Clark,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Williams</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in
<hi>Hoſier-Lane,</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:3"/>
            <head>TO THE Honourable, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Honour by Deſert, S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               <hi>Kenelme Digby</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur generous mind fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by nature to vertue and vertuous actions, is ſo well known to Souldiers and Scholars, that as <hi>Mars</hi> gives you Bayes, ſo the <hi>Muſes</hi> do give you Books.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quis ergo generoſus? Ad virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem bene à natura co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitus.</hi> Sen. l. 5. p. 44.</note> The conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath emboldned me (though a ſtranger) to offer to your protection this tranſlation of <hi>Ovids</hi> Elegys, who I think was even rocked in his cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle by the Muſes and fed with ſugar and
<hi>Heliconian</hi> water, which made him have ſo ſweet a vein of Poetry. So that the name of <hi>Ovid</hi> is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient commendation for any work of his; if my <hi>Engliſh</hi> can but like the<pb facs="tcp:59618:4"/>Eccho ſend back the ſoft Muſick of his lines. And indeed if he write beſt of love that hath been in love; and that there is a certain
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or efficacy in his words that feels the affection; I doubt not but my own ſorrow hath learn'd me how to tranſlate <hi>Ovids</hi> ſorrow. For I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I was never in Fortunes books, and therefore am not much indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her, neither do I care for her frowns; but I am grieved for one who is my brother, in miſ-fortune, who is
<hi>exul in Patria,</hi> being enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to let that skill and experience which he hath gotten abroad in Marine affairs, and which hath been approved of both by the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Nations in ſeveral long voyages, lie dead in him for want of employment, which is the life of practical knowledge: And though he muſt be compelled by his preſent fates to accept of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of foraign Nations, yet if a way might be opened unto him he is more willing (as he is bound by duty) to ſerve his native King and Country, which deſire of his I<pb facs="tcp:59618:4"/>know your generous diſpoſition cannot but cheriſh, and approve of my love towards him. This book
<hi>Ovid</hi> ſent to the City of <hi>Rome</hi> a ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by die firſt verſe, <hi>Parve nec in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>video &amp;c.</hi> and I am now to ſend it forth into a City abounding with <hi>Criticks,</hi> and therefore it deſires your worthy patronage and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; for which (if <hi>Ovid</hi> lived) he would make his fluent Muſe expreſs his thankfulneſs: But I for any favour which you ſhall ſhew unto this tranſlation, muſt acknowledge my ſelf bound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your vertue, which I wiſh may ſhine forth in proſperous actions, until your fame be equal to <hi>Caeſars,</hi> who baniſhed
<hi>Ovid.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The ſervant of your Vertues, W. SALTONSTAL,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT is now grown a common cuſtome to ſeek thy good will by an Epiſtle, and therein to move thy affection to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to the preſent work, wherein I need not beſtow any great pains, for this is a tranſlation of <hi>Ovids</hi> laſt book which he writ in baniſhment, and therefore if you would ſet before your eyes the preſent eſtate wherein he then lived, it would exceedingly move your pitty towards him. Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that you ſaw
<hi>Ovid</hi> in the Land of <hi>Pontus,</hi> where he whoſe company was ſo much deſired, was now baniſh'd from all company; he that was once the Darling of the Muſes, now made the ſubject of miſery; he that drank choiſe wines, now drinks ſpring water; he that wore a wreath of Bayes, now wears a wreath of Cypreſs: and to conclude, he that was once ſo famous, was now as much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, and all this was moſt unworthily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on him for ſome offence committed againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and alſo for writing that unhappy Book which he called the Art of Love; for theſe two he accuſes as the cauſers of his baniſhment; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time he writ this laſt Book, entituling it his <hi>Triſtium,</hi> becauſe it contained his ſorrow:<pb facs="tcp:59618:5"/>And laſtly conſider, that after he had written this book, having divers times ſought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed from baniſhment; and deſpairing of any mercy from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> he at laſt dyed, in the ſeventh year of his Baniſhment, from <hi>Rome:</hi> the Muſes, together with <hi>Venus</hi> and a hundred little <hi>Cupids</hi> being mourners at his Funeral, If therefore you ever loved the ſweetneſs of <hi>Ovids</hi> veine, or if the conſideration of his ſufferance in baniſhment, his want, his griefs, his afflictions, and laſty his death in a barbarous Land, can move your pitty and compaſſion, I doubt not but you will ſhew much love and affection to theſe Elegies, even for <hi>Ovids</hi> ſake, whoſe compoſitions were ſo ſweet and fluent, that his verſes did run like a ſmooth ſtream fed by the ſpring of the Muſes, ſo that he could hardly ſpeak but in the manner of a verſe, for ſo he teſtifies of himſelf:
<hi>Quicquid conabor dicere verſus erit.</hi> Now for my ſelf, I have put theſe Elegies of <hi>Ovids</hi> into an Engliſh mourning habit, with a frontiſpiece to give thee a clear view of <hi>Ovids</hi> miſery, and to make thy heart more apt to receive a deeper impreſſion of his ſorrow, that ſeeing how unworthily he was dealt withal, thou mayeſt both pitty
<hi>Ovid,</hi> and love this work of his, which is all I deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomia">
            <div type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Angelus Politianus</hi> his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram on the baniſhment and death of <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>THe <hi>Roman</hi> Poet lies in the <hi>Euxine</hi> ſhore,</l>
               <l>And barbarous earth the Poet covers o're</l>
               <l>Him that did write of love, that land doth hide,</l>
               <l>Through which the <hi>Iſters</hi> colder ſtreams do glide.</l>
               <l>And were it not a ſhame to be (O <hi>Rome</hi>)</l>
               <l>More cruel then the <hi>Geles</hi> to ſuch a ſon?</l>
               <l>Oh Muſes while he ſick in <hi>Scyſhia</hi> lay,</l>
               <l>Who was there that his ſickneſs could allay?</l>
               <l>Or keep his cold limbs in the bed by force,</l>
               <l>Or paſs away the day with ſome diſcourſe?</l>
               <l>Or that could feel his pulſe when it did bear,</l>
               <l>Or apply to him warm things to cheriſh heat?</l>
               <l>Or cloſe his eyes, even ſwimming round with death;</l>
               <l>And at his mouth receive his lateſt breath?</l>
               <l>There were none, for his ancient friend then were</l>
               <l>In thee O <hi>Rome,</hi> from <hi>Pontus</hi> diſtant far.</l>
               <l>His wife and Nephews were far off together,</l>
               <l>His Daughter went not with her baniſh'd Father.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Beſſi</hi> and <hi>Coralli</hi> were in theſe parts,</l>
               <l>And the skin-wearing <hi>Getes</hi> with ſtony hearts.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sarmate</hi> riding on his horſe was there,</l>
               <l>To comfort him with looks that dreadful were.</l>
               <l>Yet when he was dead, the <hi>Beſſi</hi>-wept, the
<hi>Gete,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſtout <hi>Sarmatians</hi> did their faces bear.</l>
               <l>Woods, mountains, beaſt, a mourning day did keep,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iſters</hi> pearly ſtreams they ſay did weep.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:6"/>
               <l>Some ſay that frozen <hi>Pontus</hi> did begin</l>
               <l>To melt, with tears that Sea-Nimphs ſhed for him.</l>
               <l>Light <hi>Cupids</hi> with their mother <hi>Venus</hi> ran,</l>
               <l>And with torches ſet the funeral pile on flame:</l>
               <l>And while his body did conſume and burn,</l>
               <l>They put his aſhes in a cloſed Urn:</l>
               <l>And on his Tombe-ſtone theſe words graven were</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He that did teach the Art of Love lies here.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then <hi>Venus</hi> with her white hand did bedew</l>
               <l>His grave, whilſt ſhe ſweet Nectar on him threw.</l>
               <l>The Muſes brought their Poet many a verſe,</l>
               <l>Which I am far unworthy to rehearſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Julius Scaliger</hi>'s Verſes on <hi>Ovid,</hi> wherein he maketh <hi>Ovid</hi> ſpeak to <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>I Would thy cruelty had in me begun,</l>
               <l>Nor by murders ſteps to ruine me hadſt come.</l>
               <l>It my wanton youth did move thy diſcontent,</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt condemn thy ſelf to baniſhment.</l>
               <l>For ſuch foul deeds thy private rooms do ſtain,</l>
               <l>That men condemned ne're did act the ſame.</l>
               <l>Could not my wit, nor gentleneſs thee reſtrain,</l>
               <l>Nor ſweet tongue, ſecond to <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Veine?</l>
               <l>My ſtrain hath made the ancient Poets ſoft,</l>
               <l>And to the new the weight of things hath taught.</l>
               <l>I then did lye when as I praiſed thee,</l>
               <l>For this my baniſhment mas deſerv'd by me.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Umbra Ovidii,</hi> OR Ovids Ghoſt.</head>
               <l>WHen I did live I got the wreath of Bayes,</l>
               <l>From other Poets in my younger daies:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:7"/>
               <l>And ſoon my fame throug all the world was known,</l>
               <l>While <hi>Ovid</hi> only was eſteem'd at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But then at laſt as I did raiſe my fame</l>
               <l>By verſe, ſo from my verſe my ruine came.</l>
               <l>By an errour I great <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s wrath did move.</l>
               <l>And then by writing of the Art of Love:</l>
               <l>For which two faults by <hi>Caeſar</hi> I was ſent,</l>
               <l>To the <hi>Pontick</hi> land to live in baniſhment.</l>
               <l>I endeavour'd ſtill to be repeal'd from hence.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Caeſar</hi> would not pardon my offence.</l>
               <l>Thus ſeven years I in baniſhment did ſpend,</l>
               <l>Until by death my ſorrows had an end.</l>
               <l>And then my ſoul to <hi>Charon</hi>'s boat did go,</l>
               <l>Who unto <hi>Ovid</hi> did much kindneſs ſhow:</l>
               <l>And row'd me ſtraight to the <hi>Eliſian</hi> fields,</l>
               <l>Which unto happy ſouls ſuch pleaſure yields.</l>
               <l>Where now I live, and every day converſe.</l>
               <l>With ghoſts of Lovers who my lines rehearſe.</l>
               <l>And for my ſake ſweet Garlands they compoſe,</l>
               <l>Of Lillies mingled with the crimſon Roſe:</l>
               <l>Which they do give me, thereby to explain,</l>
               <l>How lovers once did love ſweet <hi>Ovids</hi> vein,</l>
               <l>And now at laſt it joyes my ghoſt to ſee,</l>
               <l>The world doth ſtill preſerve my memory.</l>
               <l>And that my ſorrows they tranſlated have,</l>
               <l>And have not buryed them within my grave,</l>
               <l>For which my ghoſt unto the world gives thanks,</l>
               <l>In theſe words writ on the <hi>Elyſian</hi> banks.</l>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Elegies themſelves as much indebted know</l>
                  <l>To us, as <hi>Heroicks</hi> did to <hi>Virgil</hi> owe.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:7"/>
            <div n="1" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>In this Elegie at large</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi> gives his book a charge,</l>
                  <l>To ſee <hi>Rome,</hi> and gives direction</l>
                  <l>How with time to varie action.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y little Book the City thou ſhalt ſee,</l>
               <l>Woe's me, thy Maſter may not go with thee:</l>
               <l>Go, but undreſt, and ſeeing thou art mine,</l>
               <l>Put on a habit like unto the time.</l>
               <l>Be not clothed with the <hi>Hyacinths</hi> purple juyce,</l>
               <l>Such colours are in mourning out of uſe.</l>
               <l>Paint not thy Title with Vermillion dye,</l>
               <l>To draw unto thee every gazing eye:</l>
               <l>No oyle of Cedar to thy leave allow;</l>
               <l>Nor weare white corners on thy ſable blow,</l>
               <l>Such Ornaments may happy books inveſt,</l>
               <l>But be thou like unto my fortune dreſt,</l>
               <l>Thy forehead with no pumice ſtone make fair,</l>
               <l>But come thou forth with looſe and ragged hair.</l>
               <l>Nor ſhame thoſe blots which on thy face appears;</l>
               <l>For ſome many think they were made with my tears.</l>
               <l>Go book, ſalute the City in my name,</l>
               <l>For on thy feet I will go back again;</l>
               <l>And if by chance among the common crew,</l>
               <l>Some mindful of me aske thee how I do?</l>
               <l>Return this anſwer, tell them that I live,</l>
               <l>And that my God this life doth freely give.</l>
               <l>But if they more do ſeek, then ſilent be,</l>
               <l>And ſpeak not that ſhould not be read in thee,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:8"/>
               <l>Then the angry Reader will repeat my fault,</l>
               <l>While by the people I am guilty thought,</l>
               <l>Defend me not, though they my fault repeat,</l>
               <l>An ill cauſe by defence is made more great.</l>
               <l>Some thou ſhalt find will ſigh cauſe I am gone,</l>
               <l>And read theſe verſe with wet cheeks alone,</l>
               <l>Who often wiſhes <hi>Caeſar</hi> would but pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Some lighter puniſhment might his wrath appeaſe.</l>
               <l>And I do pray he may ne're wreched be,</l>
               <l>That wiſhes <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould thus pity me.</l>
               <l>But may his wiſhes come to paſs, that I</l>
               <l>At laſt may in my native Country dye.</l>
               <l>But book, I know, thou ſhalt receive much blame,</l>
               <l>And be thought inferiour unto <hi>Ovid's</hi> veine:</l>
               <l>Yet every Judge the time and matter weighs;</l>
               <l>The time conſidered, thou deſerveſt praiſe.</l>
               <l>Smooth verſes from a quiet mind do flow,</l>
               <l>My ryhmes are over-caſt with ſuddain woe,</l>
               <l>Verſes require much leiſure and ſweet eaſe,</l>
               <l>But I am toſt by windes and angry Seas.</l>
               <l>Verſes were never made in fear while I</l>
               <l>Do look each minute by the ſword to dye.</l>
               <l>So that an equal judge may well approve</l>
               <l>Theſe lines of mine, and read them with much love.</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Homer</hi> been diſtreſs'd ſo many wayes,</l>
               <l>It would his ſharp diſcerning wit amaze.</l>
               <l>Then book be careleſs of all idle fame,</l>
               <l>For to diſpleaſe thy Reader, is no ſhame,</l>
               <l>Since fortune hath not ſo kind to me been,</l>
               <l>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou their idle praiſe ſhould ſo eſteem.</l>
               <l>When I was happy, I did covet fame,</l>
               <l>And had a great deſire to get a name.</l>
               <l>But now both verſe and ſtudy I do hate,</l>
               <l>Since they have brought me to this baniſht ſtate.</l>
               <l>Yet go my book, thee in my place I aſſigne,</l>
               <l>And would to God I could not call thee mine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:8"/>
               <l>Though as a ſtranger thou doſt come to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou canſt not to the people come unknown:</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou no title, yet thy ſable hew,</l>
               <l>If thou deny me, will thy authour ſhew:</l>
               <l>Yet enter ſecretly, leaſt ſome diſdain</l>
               <l>My verſe, which is not now eſteem'd by fame.</l>
               <l>And if by chance ſome when they hear me nam'd,</l>
               <l>Do caſt thee by out of their ſcornful hand.</l>
               <l>Tell them that I do teach no Rules of Love,</l>
               <l>That work was long ſince puniſh'd from above,</l>
               <l>Perhaps thou doſt imagine thou art ſent,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Caeſar's</hi> Court, which is not my intent:</l>
               <l>Aſpire not thou unto thoſe ſeats Divine,</l>
               <l>From whence the thunder did on me decline.</l>
               <l>Though once the Gods more favourable were.</l>
               <l>Yet now their juſt deſerved wrath I feare.</l>
               <l>The fearful Dove once ſtruck, ſtill after ſprings,</l>
               <l>When ſhe doth hear the Hawks large ſpreading wings:</l>
               <l>And from the fold the Lamb dare never ſtray,</l>
               <l>That from the Wolf hath gotten once away.</l>
               <l>Nor would young <hi>Phaeton</hi> deſire to drive</l>
               <l>His Fathers ſteeds, if be were now alive.</l>
               <l>So having felt great <hi>Joves</hi> devouring flame,</l>
               <l>I am afraip I ſhould be ſtruck again.</l>
               <l>He that was in the Grecian fleet before,</l>
               <l>Will bend his ſails from the <hi>Euboean</hi> ſhore.</l>
               <l>And ſo my weather-beaten bark doth ſhun,</l>
               <l>That place from whence the furious ſtorm begun.</l>
               <l>Therefore be wiſely circumſpect, take heed,</l>
               <l>It is enough if thee the people read.</l>
               <l>While <hi>Icarus</hi> flew too high with waxen plumes,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Icarian</hi> Seas from him their name aſſumes.</l>
               <l>Yet it is hard to councel in this action,</l>
               <l>Since time and place will give thee beſt direction.</l>
               <l>For if thou ſee that <hi>Caeſars</hi> wrath be ſpent,</l>
               <l>And that his anger is to mildneſs bent:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:9"/>
               <l>Or if ſome Courtier thee to <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhow,</l>
               <l>And ſpeake to him in thy behalf, then go</l>
               <l>With lucky ſtars, and bring me ſome relief,</l>
               <l>To lighten this my heavy weight of grief.</l>
               <l>For he by whom I did theſe wounds obtain</l>
               <l>Can like <hi>Achilles</hi> ſpear cure them again.</l>
               <l>But take heed leaſt thou do diſ-favour find,</l>
               <l>My hopes are ſmall and fears perplex my mind,</l>
               <l>Leſt I another puniſhment obtain,</l>
               <l>If thou do move his new-calm'd wrath again.</l>
               <l>But when into my ſtudy thou doſt get,</l>
               <l>And there upon the little ſhelves art ſet.</l>
               <l>There thou ſhalt ſee thy other brothers ſtand,</l>
               <l>Brought all to life by one life-giving hand.</l>
               <l>The reſt are by their paper titles known,</l>
               <l>Whoſe written names are on their fore-head ſhown.</l>
               <l>Three other books thou ſhalt likewiſe diſcern,</l>
               <l>Teaching loves Art which every one can learn.</l>
               <l>But ſhun them, and if thou baſt ſo much breath,</l>
               <l>Tell them that <hi>Oedipus</hi> was his fathers death.</l>
               <l>And if thy parents words have power to move,</l>
               <l>Love none of thoſe although they teach to love.</l>
               <l>Fifteen volumes of changed ſhapes there lies,</l>
               <l>Which were of late ſnatch't from my obſequies:</l>
               <l>Bid them among their changed ſhapes relate,</l>
               <l>The ſad change of my Fortune and eſtate;</l>
               <l>For ſhe's unlike to what ſhe was before,</l>
               <l>Once happy, now my fate I muſt deplore.</l>
               <l>I have more precepts to give thee in charge,</l>
               <l>But that my words thy ſtaying would enlarge?</l>
               <l>And ſhould'ſt thou carry all my thoughts with thee,</l>
               <l>A burthen to thy bearer thou would'ſt be.</l>
               <l>'Tis far, make haſt, while here I live alone,</l>
               <l>Within a Land far diſtant from my home.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="elegy">
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:9"/>
               <head>ELEGIE II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>While fear of Shipwrack all amaze</l>
                  <l>He to the Gods devoutly prayes.</l>
                  <l>Deſcribes the tempeſt and his fear,</l>
                  <l>At laſt the Gods his prayers hear.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>YE Gods of Seas (for what remains but prayer)</l>
               <l>Be pleas'd at laſt our beaten bark to ſpare,</l>
               <l>Be not offended all for <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſake.</l>
               <l>One God enrag'd, ſome other pitty take.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> hated <hi>Troy, Apollo</hi> did defend</l>
               <l>The <hi>Trojans,</hi> and farr <hi>Venus</hi> was their is friend:</l>
               <l>And though that <hi>Juno Turnus</hi> did reſpect,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Venus</hi> did <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſtill protect.</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Neptune</hi> ſtill <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> ruine ſought,</l>
               <l>Yet him <hi>Minerva</hi> unto barbour brought.</l>
               <l>And though to them we far inferiour be,</l>
               <l>One God diſpleas'd, ſome power may pleaſed be.</l>
               <l>But yet alas it is in vain to ſpake,</l>
               <l>Since on my face the angry waves do break,</l>
               <l>And now the ſouthern winds ſo cruel are,</l>
               <l>The will not let the Gods even hear my prayer:</l>
               <l>But coupling miſchiefs, with their ruffling gales,</l>
               <l>They take away my prayers, and drive our ſails.</l>
               <l>The waves like mountains now are rowled on,</l>
               <l>Which even ſeem to touch the ſtarry Throne,</l>
               <l>And by and by deep vallies do appear,</l>
               <l>As if that hell it ſelf diſſolved were.</l>
               <l>Nothing but air and water can I ſee,</l>
               <l>And both of them do ſeem to threaten me.</l>
               <l>Whiles divers winds their forces do diſplay,</l>
               <l>The ſea is doubtful which he ſhould obey.</l>
               <l>For now the winds comes from the purple caſt,</l>
               <l>And ſo again it bloweth from the weſt.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Boreas</hi> flies out from the Northern Wain,</l>
               <l>While Southern winds do beat him back again;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:10"/>
               <l>Our Pilot knew not whither he ſhould ſteer,</l>
               <l>Are fails him, loſt in his amazed fear.</l>
               <l>Periſh we muſt, all hope of life is paſt,</l>
               <l>And while I ſpake the angry billows flaſh'd</l>
               <l>Into my face, and with their waves did fill</l>
               <l>My mouth, while I continued praying ſtill.</l>
               <l>I know my wife at home doth now lament,</l>
               <l>And grieve to thimk upon my baniſhment,</l>
               <l>Yet knows ſhe not how I am toſſed here,</l>
               <l>And little thinks ſhe that I am ſo near</l>
               <l>Unto my death, and were ſhe here with me,</l>
               <l>My grief for her a ſecond death would be.</l>
               <l>Now though I dye, yet while that ſhe is ſafe,</l>
               <l>I ſhall ſurvive in her my other half.</l>
               <l>But now quick lightning breaketh through the Cloud,</l>
               <l>And following Thunder roareth out aloud.</l>
               <l>And now the waves upon the ſhip do beat,</l>
               <l>Like bullets, and as one wave doth retreat,</l>
               <l>Another comes that doth exceed the reſt,</l>
               <l>And thus their fury is by turns expreſt.</l>
               <l>I fear not death, yet I do grieve that I</l>
               <l>Should here by Shipwrack in this manner dye.</l>
               <l>Happy is he whom ſickneſs doth invade,</l>
               <l>Whoſe body in the ſolid earth is lade.</l>
               <l>And having made his will, in his grave may reſt,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall the fiſhes on his body feaſt.</l>
               <l>And yet ſuppoſe my death deſerved be,</l>
               <l>Shall all the reſt be puniſht here for me?</l>
               <l>O ye green Gods who do the Sea command,</l>
               <l>Take off from us your heavy threatning hand.</l>
               <l>And let me bear this wretched life of mine,</l>
               <l>Unto that place which <hi>Caeſar</hi> did aſſign.</l>
               <l>If you deſire with death to puniſh me,</l>
               <l>My fault was Judg'd not worthy death to be,</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Caeſar</hi> meant to take my life away,</l>
               <l>He need not uſe your help who all do ſway.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:10"/>
               <l>For if that he do pleaſe my bloud to ſpill,</l>
               <l>My life is but a tenure at his will.</l>
               <l>But you whom I did never yet offend,</l>
               <l>Have pity on me, and to mercy bend.</l>
               <l>For though you ſave me in this great diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>Yet you ſhall ſee my ruine ne're the leſs.</l>
               <l>And if the windes and ſeas did favour me,</l>
               <l>I ſhould no leſt a baniſh'd man ſtill be.</l>
               <l>I am not greedy, riches to obtain,</l>
               <l>Nor do I plough the ſea in hope of gain,</l>
               <l>I go not to <hi>Athens,</hi> where I once have been,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Aſian</hi> towns which I have never ſeen,</l>
               <l>Nor unto <hi>Alexandria</hi> do I go,</l>
               <l>To ſee how <hi>Nilus</hi> ſeven ſtreams do flow.</l>
               <l>I wiſh a gentle wind which may ſo ſtand,</l>
               <l>To bring me ſafe to the <hi>Sarmatian</hi> Land.</l>
               <l>And though to the ſhoares of <hi>Pontus</hi> I am ſent,</l>
               <l>I now complain of tardie baniſhment.</l>
               <l>And though to <hi>Tomos</hi> I am ſent away,</l>
               <l>Yet for a ſpeedy paſſage I do pray.</l>
               <l>Then if you love me, calme the angry ſeas,</l>
               <l>And gently guide our ſhip if ſo you pleaſe:</l>
               <l>Or if you hate me, bring me to that Land,</l>
               <l>Where death even for my puniſhment may ſtand.</l>
               <l>Then bear me hence you windes, what do I here?</l>
               <l>Or why doth <hi>Italy</hi> in ſight appear,</l>
               <l>Why ſtay you me who am by <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſent,</l>
               <l>Unto the <hi>Pontick</hi> land to baniſhment,</l>
               <l>Which I deſerv'd, nor dare I to defend,</l>
               <l>That fault which he ſo lately hath comdemn'd.</l>
               <l>Yet if the Gods did know our ſecret thought,</l>
               <l>There was no wicked meaning in my fault.</l>
               <l>You know, blind errour carried me away,</l>
               <l>While folly did my harmleſs mind betray.</l>
               <l>If to his houſe I ever bore good will,</l>
               <l>And have obeyed <hi>Auguſtus</hi> pleaſure ſtill:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:11"/>
               <l>If I have prayed even in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> name,</l>
               <l>If have prayed even for his happy reign;</l>
               <l>And offer'd incenſe in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> name:</l>
               <l>If ſuch my mind, then Gods from you I crave</l>
               <l>Some pitty, or elſe make the ſea my grave.</l>
               <l>But ſtay, me thinks the Clouds away are blown,</l>
               <l>And the ſeas vanquiſh't rage is orecome:</l>
               <l>For theſe ſame Gods which I before implor'd,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Gods which I conditionally implor'd,</l>
               <l>Being ne're deceived, do now their help afford.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>When that unhappy hour was come,</l>
                  <l>That he muſt now depart from <hi>Rome;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He ſhews how his Wife and friends lament,</l>
                  <l>His then approaching baniſhment.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>WHen I remember that ſame fatal night,</l>
               <l>The laſt that I injoy'd the Gities ſight;</l>
               <l>Wherein I left each thing to me moſt dear;</l>
               <l>Then from mine eyes there ſlideth down a tear;</l>
               <l>For when the morning once drew near that I,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſentence muſt leave
<hi>Italy;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I had no mind to think upon the way,</l>
               <l>My heavy heart did ſeek out all delay.</l>
               <l>Servants, nor yet companions did I chuſe,</l>
               <l>Nor coin, nor cloathes, which baniſht men might uſe.</l>
               <l>I ſtood amaz'd like one by thunder ſtruck,</l>
               <l>Who lives, yet thinks that life hath him forſook.</l>
               <l>But when this cloud of ſorrow was ote blown,</l>
               <l>And all my ſenſes were more able grown;</l>
               <l>I bad forewel to each ſad friend by name,</l>
               <l>For now of many there did few remain.</l>
               <l>My Wife wept, and me weeping did imbrace,</l>
               <l>A ſhower of tears ſtill raining on her face;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:11"/>
               <l>My daughter now was in the <hi>Affrick</hi> land,</l>
               <l>Nor of my ſad fate could ſhe underſtand.</l>
               <l>Through all my houſe deep groans and ſighs I hear;</l>
               <l>As if ſome funeral ſolemnized were.</l>
               <l>My wife, my children, and my ſelf were mourners,</l>
               <l>And private grief did vent it ſelf in corners.</l>
               <l>If humble ſorrows great examples brook,</l>
               <l>Such was the face of things when <hi>Troy</hi> was took.</l>
               <l>It was the deepeſt ſilence of the night,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Luna</hi> in her chariot ſhined bright:</l>
               <l>When looking on the Capitols high frame,</l>
               <l>Which joyned was unto our houſe in vain:</l>
               <l>You Gods (quoth I) whom theſe fair ſeats enfold,</l>
               <l>And temples which I ne're ſhall more behold:</l>
               <l>And all yee Gods of <hi>Rome</hi> whom I muſt leave,</l>
               <l>I theſe my laſt tendred prayers do you receive;</l>
               <l>Though wounded I the buckler uſe top late,</l>
               <l>Let exile caſe me of the peoples hate.</l>
               <l>Tell <hi>Caeſar</hi> though I ſin'd by ignorance,</l>
               <l>There was no wickedneſs in my offence.</l>
               <l>And as you know ſo let him know the ſame,</l>
               <l>That ſo his wrath may be appeas'd again.</l>
               <l>With larger prayers my wife did then beſeech</l>
               <l>The Gods until that ſobs cut off her ſpeech,</l>
               <l>Then falling down with flowing hair long ſpred;</l>
               <l>She kiſt the hearth whereon the fire lay dead;</l>
               <l>And to our penates pourd forth many a word,</l>
               <l>Which for her husband now no help afford,</l>
               <l>Now growing night did haſte delay again,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Arctos</hi> now had turn'd about her Wain,</l>
               <l>And loath was I to leave my countries ſight,</l>
               <l>Yet this for exile was my ſentenc'd night.</l>
               <l>If any urged my haſte, I would reply,</l>
               <l>Alaſs, conſider, whither, whence I flye.</l>
               <l>And then my ſelf with flattery would beguile,</l>
               <l>And think no hour did limit my exile.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:12"/>
               <l>Thrice went I forth, and thrice returning find,</l>
               <l>Slow paces were indulgent to my mind.</l>
               <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t having bid farwel, I ſpake again,</l>
               <l>And many parting kiſſes gave in vain.</l>
               <l>Then looking back upon my children dear,</l>
               <l>The ſame repeated charge I gave them there.</l>
               <l>Why make we haſt? 'tis juſt to ſeek delay,</l>
               <l>Since I am ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Scythia.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For I muſt leave my children, houſe, and wife,</l>
               <l>Who while I live muſt lead a widdows life,</l>
               <l>And you my loving friends that preſent be,</l>
               <l>And were like <hi>Theſeus</hi> faithful unto me:</l>
               <l>Let us imbrace, and uſe times little ſtore,</l>
               <l>Perhaps I never ſhall imbrace you more.</l>
               <l>And then my words to action did give place,</l>
               <l>While I each friend did lovingly imbrace,</l>
               <l>But while I ſpake and tears bedew'd my eyes,</l>
               <l>The fatal morning ſtar began to riſe.</l>
               <l>My heart was ſo divided therewithal,</l>
               <l>As if my limbs would from my body fall.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Priam</hi> griev'd when he too late did find,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Grecian</hi> Horſe with armed men was lin'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Then ſorrow was in one loud cry expreſt,</l>
               <l>And every one began to knock his breaſt;</l>
               <l>And now my wife her arms about me caſt,</l>
               <l>And while I wept, ſhe ſpake theſe words at laſt;</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not go alone, for I will be</l>
               <l>Thy wife in baniſhment and follow thee.</l>
               <l>In the ſame ſhip with thee I'le go aboard,</l>
               <l>And one land ſhall to us one life afford.</l>
               <l>Thee unto exile <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s wrath commands,</l>
               <l>Me love, which love to me for <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſtands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>This ſhe repeats, which ſhe had ſpoke before,</l>
               <l>And could not be perſwaded to give o're.</l>
               <l>Till at the laſt when I my hair had rent,</l>
               <l>Forth like ſome living Funeral I went.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:12"/>
               <l>And after (as I heard) when night grew on,</l>
               <l>Being mad with grief, ſhe threw her ſelf along</l>
               <l>Upon the ground, while as her hair now lies,</l>
               <l>Soild in the duſt, and when that ſhe did riſe,</l>
               <l>She did bewail her gods, her ſelf and all,</l>
               <l>And on her husbands name did often call.</l>
               <l>Grieving as much for this my late exile,</l>
               <l>As if ſhe ſaw me on the Funeral pile;</l>
               <l>She wiſhes death her ſorrows would relieve,</l>
               <l>Yet then again for my ſake ſhe would live.</l>
               <l>And may ſhe live while I obey my fate:</l>
               <l>And live to help me in this wretched ſtate,</l>
               <l>But now the keeper of the Beare was waſht</l>
               <l>With waves which even to the Heavens fl ſht;</l>
               <l>While we the <hi>Ionian</hi> ſeas now ploughing were,</l>
               <l>Fear made us bold even in the midſt of fear.</l>
               <l>Alaſs, the winds the ſeas in black adorn,</l>
               <l>And with the beating waves the ſand grew warm,</l>
               <l>When ſtreight a Sea o're Poope and ſtern too came,</l>
               <l>Waſhing thoſe Gods were painted on the ſame,</l>
               <l>And now the planks did groan, the ropes did crack,</l>
               <l>As if the ſhip lamented her own wrack.</l>
               <l>Our maſters paleneſs did confeſs his fear,</l>
               <l>And knowing not what to do; gives o're to ſtear.</l>
               <l>And as a man unable to reſtrain</l>
               <l>A head-ſtrong Horſe, doth ſlack the bridle rein,</l>
               <l>So he let looſe the ſails unto the Seas,</l>
               <l>Leaving the ſhip to drive on where it pleaſe.</l>
               <l>And had not <hi>Aeolus</hi> other winds ſtraight ſent,</l>
               <l>We had been driven back from whence we went,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illyria</hi> being on our ſtarboard hand,</l>
               <l>We came in ſight of the <hi>Italian</hi> Land.</l>
               <l>Ceaſe then you winds to drive us on that ſhore,</l>
               <l>'Tis <hi>Caeſars</hi> will we ſhould go back no more.</l>
               <l>Thus fearing that which I did much deſire,</l>
               <l>The leaping waves did to the decks aſpire.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:13"/>
               <l>Spare me ye Gods of ſeas ſome mercy ſhow,</l>
               <l>Let it ſuffice that <hi>Caeſar</hi> is my foe.</l>
               <l>And let not death my weary ſoul invade,</l>
               <l>If one already ruin'd may be ſav'd.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Unto his friend whoſe love be found,</l>
                  <l>Conſtant when his fortune frown'd</l>
                  <l>And like a chimney hot to be,</l>
                  <l>In the winter of adverſity.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>O Friend, thy love deſerves the foremoſt place,</l>
               <l>Who pittiedſt me as if 'twere thy own caſe:</l>
               <l>For when I was amazed with my grief,</l>
               <l>Thy gentle words did yield me great relief.</l>
               <l>And didſt perſwade me ſtill to live, while I,</l>
               <l>Wearied with ſorrow did deſire to dye.</l>
               <l>And though by ſignes thy name I do conceal,</l>
               <l>Yet whom I mean thy conſcience will reveal.</l>
               <l>And of thy true love I will mindful be,</l>
               <l>For I do owe my very life to thee.</l>
               <l>My ſoul ſhall vaniſh into empty ayre,</l>
               <l>My body to the funeral pile repair.</l>
               <l>E're I forget thy love which I did find,</l>
               <l>Or time do make it ſlip out of my mind.</l>
               <l>But may the eaſie Gods to thee incline,</l>
               <l>And give a fortune far unlike to mine.</l>
               <l>Yet had my ſhip with gentle winds ſail'd on,</l>
               <l>Thy faithful love to me had been unknown.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pirithous Theſeus</hi> love could never know,</l>
               <l>Till to the infernal waters they did go:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pylades</hi> love had never been expreſt,</l>
               <l>Till madde <hi>Oreſtes</hi> furies him diſtreſt.</l>
               <l>And had <hi>Eurialus</hi> ſcap'd the daring foe,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Niſus</hi> love who ſhould the ſtory know?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:13"/>
               <l>For as the fire the yellow gold doth try,</l>
               <l>So love is proved by adverſity.</l>
               <l>While fortune helps us, and on us doth ſmile,</l>
               <l>They will attend upon our wealth that while,</l>
               <l>But if ſhe frown, they flye, and ſcarce of any</l>
               <l>Shall he be known, that had of friends ſo many.</l>
               <l>This which before, I from examples drew,</l>
               <l>In my own fortune now is proved true.</l>
               <l>Since of my friends ſo few remaining be,</l>
               <l>The reſt did love my fortune and not me.</l>
               <l>Then let thoſe few aid me diſtreſs'd the more,</l>
               <l>And bring my ſhip with ſafety to the ſhore:</l>
               <l>And let not any fear to be my friend,</l>
               <l>Leaſt that his love great <hi>Caeſar</hi> might offend.</l>
               <l>For faithfulneſſe in friendſhip he doth love,</l>
               <l>And in his enemies doth it approve.</l>
               <l>My caſe is better, ſince that no attempt,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt him, but folly wrought my baniſhment.</l>
               <l>Be watchful then in my behalf and fee,</l>
               <l>If that his anger may appeaſed be.</l>
               <l>If any wiſh I ſhould my griefs rehearſe,</l>
               <l>They are too many to be ſhew'd in verſe.</l>
               <l>My griefs are more than ſtars within the skies,</l>
               <l>Or little motes which from the duſt ariſe.</l>
               <l>For to my ſorrows none can credit give,</l>
               <l>Poſterity will ſcarce the ſame believe.</l>
               <l>Beſides thoſe other griefs which ought to have,</l>
               <l>Within my ſecret thoughts a ſilent grave.</l>
               <l>Had I a voice and breaſt could ne're be tyr'd,</l>
               <l>More mouths and tongues than ever grief deſir'd;</l>
               <l>Yet could not I expreſſe the ſame in words,</l>
               <l>My grief ſo large a theam to me affords.</l>
               <l>You learned Poets leave off now to write,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Uliſſes</hi> troubles, and my woes recite.</l>
               <l>I ſuffered more; he wandred many years</l>
               <l>In comming home front <hi>Troy,</hi> as it appears<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:14"/>
               <l>We ſaild ſo far to the <hi>Sarmatian</hi> ſhore,</l>
               <l>Till we diſcover'd ſtars unknown before.</l>
               <l>With him a faithful troop of <hi>Grecians</hi> went,</l>
               <l>My friends forſook me in my baniſhment.</l>
               <l>To bring him home his happy ſails were ſpread,</l>
               <l>While I even from my native country fled.</l>
               <l>Nor do I ſaile from <hi>Ithaca,</hi> from whence,</l>
               <l>It would not grieve me co be baniſht thence:</l>
               <l>But even from <hi>Rome,</hi> which doth the Gods enfold,</l>
               <l>And from ſeven hills doth all the world behold.</l>
               <l>He had a body hardned to endure,</l>
               <l>To labour I my ſelf did ne're inure,</l>
               <l>In the ſtern wars great pains he daily took,</l>
               <l>But I was ſtill devoted to my book.</l>
               <l>One God oppoſing me, no God brought aide,</l>
               <l>But him <hi>Bellona</hi> helpt the warlike Maid.</l>
               <l>And ſince that <hi>Neptune</hi> is than <hi>Jove</hi> far leſs,</l>
               <l>Him <hi>Neptune,</hi> but great <hi>Jove</hi> doth me oppreſs.</l>
               <l>Beſides ſome fictions do his labours grace,</l>
               <l>Which in our griefs ſad ſtory have no place.</l>
               <l>And laſtly though at laſt, his home he found,</l>
               <l>And landed on the welcome long ſought ground.</l>
               <l>But ne're ſhall I my native country ſee,</l>
               <l>Until the angry Gods appeaſed be.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Unto his Wife whoſe faithful love,</l>
                  <l>And conſtancy he doth approve.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>APollo Lyde</hi> never lov'd ſo well,</l>
               <l>Nor did <hi>Philetas</hi> love ſo much excell</l>
               <l>To <hi>Battis,</hi> as my conſtant love to thee,</l>
               <l>Worthy a husband that might happier be:</l>
               <l>Thou helpedſt me when fortune did decline,</l>
               <l>So if that I am any thing, 'tis thine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:14"/>
               <l>And none through thee, to ſpoil me more were able,</l>
               <l>Who wiſht to ſee me bear a ſhipwrack table.</l>
               <l>For as Wolf whom hunger doth make bold,</l>
               <l>Doth dare to ſet upon the unwatcht fold:</l>
               <l>Or as the Vulture round about doth flye,</l>
               <l>To ſee what Carkaſs doth unburied lye:</l>
               <l>In the like manner ſome unfaithful hand,</l>
               <l>Had ſeiz'd my goods, but that thou didſt withſtand;</l>
               <l>And by friends help didſt fruſtrate his intent,</l>
               <l>To whom I can no worthy thanks preſent.</l>
               <l>This was a certain trial of thy love,</l>
               <l>If any trial need the ſame approve.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Andromaches</hi> love to <hi>Hector</hi> when he fell</l>
               <l>By ſtout <hi>Achilles,</hi> cannot parallel</l>
               <l>Thine, more expreſt to me in my ſad fate,</l>
               <l>Then was <hi>Laodamia's</hi> to her mate.</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou been <hi>Homers</hi> wife as thou art mine,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhouldſt in fame <hi>Penelope</hi> out-ſhine.</l>
               <l>Whether thou ow'ſt thy vertues to thy ſelf,</l>
               <l>And liberal nature did impart this wealth;</l>
               <l>Or elſe the example of ſome Matrons life,</l>
               <l>Doth teach thee how to be a loyal wife;</l>
               <l>And ſo by cuſtome made thee like to either;</l>
               <l>If things unequal may compare together.</l>
               <l>Alas my verſe hath now no ſtrength to praiſe thee,</l>
               <l>Nor to the height of thy deſerts can raiſe thee:</l>
               <l>And if we any lively vigour had,</l>
               <l>Through length of miſery it is now decay'd,</l>
               <l>Elſe thy conſpicuous vertues ſhould appear,</l>
               <l>'Mongſt women that for vertue famous were:</l>
               <l>Yet if my verſes any praiſe can give,</l>
               <l>Within my verſe thou ſhalt for ever live.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Unto his friends who did engrave,</l>
                  <l>And on their Rings his Image have,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59618:15"/>
                  <l>Thoſe he wiſhes him to view,</l>
                  <l>In thoſe verſes which he drew.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THou that my Image wear'ſt in Rings expreſt,</l>
               <l>Let not my brow with Ivie wreathes be dreſt.</l>
               <l>Such enſignes happy Poets may adorne,</l>
               <l>No Garland on my temples muſt be worne.</l>
               <l>Though you conceal it, yet you know 'tis true,</l>
               <l>Who on your finger do me often view.</l>
               <l>And having made my counterfeit in gold,</l>
               <l>Me in my baniſhment do ſo behold.</l>
               <l>The ſight whereof doth make thee to let fall</l>
               <l>Theſe words, How far is <hi>Ovid</hi> from us all?</l>
               <l>I thank your love, but 'tis my verſe which ſhews</l>
               <l>My lively picture, therefore it peruſe.</l>
               <l>My verſe which ſings the changed ſhapes of men,</l>
               <l>Which by my flight was left unperfect then.</l>
               <l>Departing, theſe I with my hand at laſt</l>
               <l>Into the fire with other riches caſt.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Theſtias</hi> the brand her ſon did ſmother,</l>
               <l>Being a better ſiſter then a mother.</l>
               <l>So I did caſt thoſe books into the flame,</l>
               <l>Which by my fault had merited no blame.</l>
               <l>Hating my Muſe, which did my fault include,</l>
               <l>Or elſe becauſe my verſe ſeem'd lame and rude.</l>
               <l>But ſince I could not ſo deſtroy them quite,</l>
               <l>But that ſome copies yet are come to light:</l>
               <l>Now may they live, and ſtill delightful be,</l>
               <l>Unto the Reader put in mind of me.</l>
               <l>Yet they with patience can be read of none,</l>
               <l>That to the world are uncorrected ſhown.</l>
               <l>Snatch'd from the forge before they could be fram'd,</l>
               <l>Deprived of my laſt life-giving hand.</l>
               <l>For praiſe I pardon crave, it ſhall ſuffice,</l>
               <l>If Reader thou do not my Verſe deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>Yet in the front theſe verſes placed be,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:15"/>
               <l>If with thy liking it at leaſt agree.</l>
               <l>Who meets this Orphan Volume poor in worth,</l>
               <l>Within your City harborage afford.</l>
               <l>To win more favour, not by him ſet forth,</l>
               <l>But raviſh'h from the funeral of his Lord.</l>
               <l>This therefore which preſents its own defect,</l>
               <l>At pleaſure with a friendly hand correct.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>To his unconſtant friend, whoſe love</l>
                  <l>He findes doth now unconſtant prove,</l>
                  <l>And like a Glow-worm ſeems to ſhine,</l>
                  <l>But yields no heat in hardeſt time.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>LEt Rivers now flow back unto their Spring,</l>
               <l>And let the Sun from Weſt his courſe begin:</l>
               <l>The earth ſhall now with ſhining ſtars be fill'd,</l>
               <l>The skies unto the furrowing plough ſhall yield.</l>
               <l>The water ſhall ſend forth a ſmoaking flame,</l>
               <l>The fire ſhall yield forth water back again.</l>
               <l>All things ſhall go againſt old natures force,</l>
               <l>And no part of the world ſhall keep his courſe.</l>
               <l>This I preſage becauſe I am deceiv'd</l>
               <l>Of him, whoſe love moſt faithful I believ'd.</l>
               <l>What made thy hollow thoughts ſo ſoon reject me,</l>
               <l>What did'ſt thou fear when fortune did afflict me.</l>
               <l>That thou would'ſt never comfort me at all,</l>
               <l>Or mourn at my living Funeral.</l>
               <l>That name of friendſhip which ſhould holy be,</l>
               <l>Is not eſteem'd or reckon'd of by thee.</l>
               <l>What had it been to have ſeen a maim'd friend,</l>
               <l>And with the reſt ſome words of comfort lend?</l>
               <l>And if no tears for me thou couldſt have ſhed,</l>
               <l>With fained pitty might'ſt have ſomething ſed.</l>
               <l>Thou might'ſt have done as ſome who I ne're knew,</l>
               <l>And in the common voice have bid adiew:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:16"/>
               <l>And laſtly, while thou mighteſt take the pain</l>
               <l>To ſee my face ne're to be ſeen again,</l>
               <l>And might'ſt have then (which ne're ſhall more befall)</l>
               <l>Give and receive a farewel laſt of all.</l>
               <l>Which others did, whom no ſtrict league did binde,</l>
               <l>And made their tears the witneſs of their minde.</l>
               <l>For were not we in love joyn'd each to other,</l>
               <l>By length of time and living both together?</l>
               <l>My buſineſs and my ſports were known to thee,</l>
               <l>And ſo were thy affairs well known to me.</l>
               <l>Did not I know thee well at <hi>Rome</hi> of late,</l>
               <l>Whom I for mirth-ſake did aſſociate?</l>
               <l>Are theſe things vaniſht into empty wind,</l>
               <l>Drown'd in the <hi>Lethe</hi> of a faithleſs mind;</l>
               <l>I do not think that thou wert born at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Whither alas I never more ſhall come)</l>
               <l>But on ſome Rock here in the <hi>Pontick</hi> land,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Scythian</hi> Mountains that ſo wildly ſtand.</l>
               <l>And veins of flint are every where diſperſt,</l>
               <l>In ſlender branches through thy Iron breſt.</l>
               <l>And ſure thy Nurſe ſome cruel Tiger was,</l>
               <l>Who gave thee ſuck as ſhe along did paſs:</l>
               <l>Elſe thou hadſt made my grief by application</l>
               <l>Thy own, nor wouldſt thou need this accuſation.</l>
               <l>But ſince to encreaſe the burthen of my grief,</l>
               <l>My firſt of miſeries found ſuch poor relief,</l>
               <l>Repair this breach of love, that in the end</l>
               <l>Thy now complain'd of love I may commend.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>He ſhews his friend that vulgar love,</l>
                  <l>Is fortunes ſhadow, and doth move</l>
                  <l>With it; then does congratulate</l>
                  <l>His worth deſerving better fate.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>MAiſt thou live happy even till thou dye,</l>
               <l>Who readſt this work here with a friendly eye,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:16"/>
               <l>And may my prayers unto the Gods nor fail</l>
               <l>For thee, which for my ſelf did ne're prevail.</l>
               <l>While thou art fortunate thou ſhalt have friends,</l>
               <l>But in adverſity their friendſhip ends.</l>
               <l>Thou ſee'ſt how Doves to new built houſes come,</l>
               <l>While as the ruin'd Tower all birds do ſhun.</l>
               <l>The empty Barns no vermine ever haunt,</l>
               <l>And no friend comes to him that is in want.</l>
               <l>While the Sun ſhines, our ſhadows then will ſtay,</l>
               <l>But when o're-caſt, it vaniſhes away.</l>
               <l>So do the people follow fortunes light,</l>
               <l>Which clouded once, they vaniſh out of ſight.</l>
               <l>But may theſe truths to thee moſt falſe ſtill ſeem,</l>
               <l>Which by my ill chance have confirmed been.</l>
               <l>A great reſort of friends unto me came,</l>
               <l>While I kept up my well-known houſe and name,</l>
               <l>But when it fell, my ruine they did ſhun,</l>
               <l>And all at once to fly from me begun.</l>
               <l>Nor do I wonder if they thunder fear,</l>
               <l>That blaſteth every thing it cometh near:</l>
               <l>Yet a friend conſtant in adverſity,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> approves even in his enemy.</l>
               <l>Nor is he wont to be diſpleas'd to ſee,</l>
               <l>Thoſe that have loved once, ſtill friends ſhould be.</l>
               <l>Even <hi>Troas</hi> when that he <hi>Oreſtes</hi> knew,</l>
               <l>Did praiſe that love which <hi>Pylades</hi> did ſhew.</l>
               <l>And that <hi>Patroclus</hi> was <hi>Achilles</hi> friend,</l>
               <l>Though in his foe brave <hi>Hector</hi> doth commend.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Theſeus</hi> went down with his friend to
<hi>Hell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pluto</hi> was griev'd to ſee them love ſo well.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Turnus</hi> did with tears commiſerate,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euryalus</hi> and <hi>Niſus</hi> diſmal fate.</l>
               <l>Friendſhip is in an enemy approv'd;</l>
               <l>Yet how few with theſe words of mine are mov'd?</l>
               <l>For ſuch my ſtate of fortune now appears,</l>
               <l>I ought to keep no meaſure in my tears.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:17"/>
               <l>Yet though my own times are unfotunate,</l>
               <l>They are made more clear even by thy better fate,</l>
               <l>I ſaw dear friend, that this to thee would come,</l>
               <l>When a leſs wind did drive thy ſhip along.</l>
               <l>If ſpotleſſe life deſerve to be eſteem'd.</l>
               <l>No man deſerveth more to be eſteem'd;</l>
               <l>If liberal Arts can any man advance,</l>
               <l>Thou mak'ſt each cauſe good by thy eloquence,</l>
               <l>And mov'd herewith I do to thee preſage,</l>
               <l>A glorious Scene upon the worldly ſtage.</l>
               <l>Not thunder told me this, nor yet the ſight</l>
               <l>Of ſheeps entrails, nor birds voyce or flight.</l>
               <l>Reaſon did me this augury afford,</l>
               <l>When as I ſaw thy mind with vertue ſtor'd.</l>
               <l>And now do gratulate this my divination,</l>
               <l>In that thy venues have ſuch publication.</l>
               <l>Would I had kept in darkneſſe out of ſight</l>
               <l>My ſtudies, which I wiſh had ne're known light:</l>
               <l>For as thy fame from eloquence doth grow,</l>
               <l>So from my verſe, my ruine firſt did flow.</l>
               <l>Thou know'ſt my life, and how I did abſtain</l>
               <l>From thoſe ſame Arts of Love which I did frame.</l>
               <l>Thou know'ſt I writ it in my younger daies,</l>
               <l>In jeſting manner, not to merit praiſe.</l>
               <l>Though I dare nothing urge in my defence,</l>
               <l>I think I may excuſe my late offence.</l>
               <l>Excuſe me then, nor e're forſake thy friend,</l>
               <l>But as thou haſt begun, ſo alſo end.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi> here his ſhip doth praiſe,</l>
                  <l>That carried him through many Seas.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>YEllow <hi>Minerva</hi> doth my ſhip maintan,</l>
               <l>Which of her painted Helmet bears the name.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:17"/>
               <l>For with the leaſt wind ſhe will nimbly ſail,</l>
               <l>And go with Oars when as the wind doth fail.</l>
               <l>She will out-ſail her company out-right,</l>
               <l>And fetch up any ſhip that is in ſight.</l>
               <l>She can endure the waves which on her bear,</l>
               <l>Yet will ſhe never open any leake.</l>
               <l>I boarded her in the <hi>Corinthian</hi> bay,</l>
               <l>From whence ſhe ſtoutly brought me on my way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>By <hi>Pallas</hi> help, by whom ſhe was protected,</l>
               <l>Through many dangerous ſeas ſhe was directed.</l>
               <l>And may ſhe now cut through the <hi>Pontick</hi> ſtrand,</l>
               <l>And bring me ſafely to the <hi>Getick</hi> Land.</l>
               <l>Who when that ſhe had carryed me at laſt,</l>
               <l>Through the <hi>Ionian</hi> Seas, when we had paſt</l>
               <l>Along thoſe coaſts, we ſtood to the left hand,</l>
               <l>And ſo we came unto the <hi>Imbrian</hi> Land.</l>
               <l>Then with a gentle wind ſhe ſailed on,</l>
               <l>And touch'd at <hi>Samos</hi> as ſhe went along.</l>
               <l>Upon the other ſide there ſtands a Wood,</l>
               <l>Thus farre my ſhip did bring me through the flood.</l>
               <l>Through the <hi>Biſtonians</hi> fields on foot I went,</l>
               <l>And then from <hi>Helleſpont</hi> her courſe ſhe bent.</l>
               <l>For to <hi>Dardania</hi> ſhe her courſe intended,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Lampſace</hi> which <hi>Priapus</hi> defended.</l>
               <l>So to the walls of <hi>Cyzicon</hi> ſhe came,</l>
               <l>Which the <hi>Maeonian</hi> people firſt did frame.</l>
               <l>Thence to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was her way,</l>
               <l>Whereas two Seas do meet within one bay.</l>
               <l>Now may my other ſhip with a ſtrong gale,</l>
               <l>Paſs by the moving Iſles; while ſhe doth ſail,</l>
               <l>By the <hi>Thinnian</hi> bay, while her courſe doth fall,</l>
               <l>To come hard by <hi>Anchialus</hi> high wall.</l>
               <l>Then to <hi>Meſſembria, Odeſſon,</hi> and the Tower,</l>
               <l>Which is defended by God <hi>Bacchus</hi> power:</l>
               <l>And to <hi>Megara</hi> which did firſt receive</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcathous,</hi> who did his Country leave.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:18"/>
               <l>So to <hi>Miletus</hi> which is the place aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>To which by <hi>Caeſars</hi> wrath I am confin'd.</l>
               <l>Where for an offering of a greater price,</l>
               <l>A Lambe to <hi>Pallas</hi> I will ſacrifice,</l>
               <l>And you two Brothers that are ſtellifi'd,</l>
               <l>I pray that you my ſhip may gently guide,</l>
               <l>One ſhip to the <hi>Cyanean</hi> Iſles is bound;</l>
               <l>The other goes to the <hi>Biſtonian</hi> ground.</l>
               <l>And therefore grant the winde may fitly ſtand,</l>
               <l>To bring them ſafely to a diverſe land.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Unto the Reader here he ſhowes,</l>
                  <l>That he this firſt Book did compoſe</l>
                  <l>In his journey, and ſo doth crave</l>
                  <l>His pardon, if ſome faults it have.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>EAch letter that thou readeſt in this Book,</l>
               <l>I did indite, while I my journey took.</l>
               <l>And while I writ the Sea did me enfold,</l>
               <l>While I did tremble with <hi>December's</hi> cold.</l>
               <l>Or when having paſt the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> through the main,</l>
               <l>We were enforced to take ſhip again;</l>
               <l>I think it did amaze the <hi>Cyclades,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſee me writing verſes on the Seas.</l>
               <l>I wonder too, that I with ſtormes of mind,</l>
               <l>And waves oppreſt, could ſuch invention find.</l>
               <l>For if that Poetry be nam'd a madneſs,</l>
               <l>Yet it did eaſe my minde in mid'ſt of ſadneſs.</l>
               <l>Now by the ſtormy winds our ſhip was beaten,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Sterope</hi> did make the ſeas to threaten.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arctophylax</hi> did cloud the day again,</l>
               <l>And Southern windes did bring down ſhowers of rain.</l>
               <l>The Sea leak'd in a pace, yet then I drew,</l>
               <l>With trembling hand theſe verſes here in view.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:18"/>
               <l>And now the winds did whiſtle in the ſhrowds,</l>
               <l>The waves did ſeem to riſe up to the clouds.</l>
               <l>The Pilot lifting up his hands and heart</l>
               <l>Beſought the Gods for help, and left his Art:</l>
               <l>Where e're I look, deaths ſhape behold I may,</l>
               <l>Which maketh me at once, to fear, and pray.</l>
               <l>The Heavens ſight would but encreaſe my fears,</l>
               <l>The Land more fearful then the Sea appears.</l>
               <l>The fear of cruel men my thoughts doth trouble,</l>
               <l>The ſword, and ſeas, do make my fears ſeem double.</l>
               <l>For that would fain deprive me of my breath,</l>
               <l>And this would have the glory of my death.</l>
               <l>On the left hand a barbarous Nation ſtood,</l>
               <l>Who do delight in ſlaughter, warre, and blood:</l>
               <l>And while the waves do give the ſea no reſt.</l>
               <l>The ſea is not more troubled than my breaſt.</l>
               <l>So that the Reader ought to pardon theſe</l>
               <l>Few lines of mine, if that they do not pleaſe.</l>
               <l>I writ them not within my garden Arbour,</l>
               <l>Or while my bed my weary limbs did harbour.</l>
               <l>But on our ſhip the angry waves did beat,</l>
               <l>And the blew water did my paper wet.</l>
               <l>Winter grew angry for to ſee me write,</l>
               <l>While he in threatning ſtormes did ſhew his might.</l>
               <l>I yield to him, and may his ſtormy weather,</l>
               <l>Here with my verſe be ended both together.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:19"/>
            <head>LIB. 2.</head>
            <argument>
               <l>Unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> he excuſes</l>
               <l>Himſelf, and condemns his Muſes.</l>
               <l>And many Poets doth recite,</l>
               <l>Who in their times did looſely write;</l>
               <l>Yet in that age were never ſent,</l>
               <l>Though like in fault, to baniſhment.</l>
            </argument>
            <l>WHat have I to do with you my unhappy book?</l>
            <l>On whom as on my ruine I muſt look.</l>
            <l>Why do I returne unto my Muſe again,</l>
            <l>Is't not enough one puniſhment to obtain.</l>
            <l>It was my verſe that firſt did overthrow me,</l>
            <l>And made both men, and women wiſh to know me.</l>
            <l>It was my verſe did make great <hi>Caeſar</hi> deem,</l>
            <l>My life to be ſuch, as my verſe did ſeem.</l>
            <l>Amongſt my chiefeſt faults I muſt rehearſe,</l>
            <l>My love of ſtudy, and my looſer verſe.</l>
            <l>In which while I my fruitleſs labour ſpent,</l>
            <l>I gained nothing but ſad baniſhment.</l>
            <l>Thoſe learned Siſters I ſhould therefore hate,</l>
            <l>Who their adorers ſtill do ruinate.</l>
            <l>Yet ſuch my madneſſe is, that folly armes me,</l>
            <l>To ſtrike my foot againſt that ſtone that harmes me;</l>
            <l>Even as ſome beaten Fencer after tries</l>
            <l>To re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gain honour, by a ſecond Prize.</l>
            <l>Or as ſome torne ſhip that newly came</l>
            <l>To ſhore, yet after ſtands to ſea again.</l>
            <l>Perhaps as <hi>Telephus</hi> was healed by a ſword,</l>
            <l>So that which hurt me ſhall like help afford.</l>
            <l>And that my verſe his mov'd wrath may appeaſe,</l>
            <l>Since verſes have great power the Gods to pleaſe.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> hath bidden each <hi>Italian</hi> Dame.</l>
            <l>To ſing ſome verſes to great <hi>Opis</hi> name:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:19"/>
            <l>And unto <hi>Phoebus</hi> when he ſet forth plaies,</l>
            <l>To him once ſeen within an age of daies.</l>
            <l>So may my verſe great <hi>Caeſars</hi> now obtain,</l>
            <l>By examples to appeaſe thy wrath again.</l>
            <l>Juſt is thy wrath, which I will ne're deny,</l>
            <l>Such ſhameful words, from my mouth do not flie:</l>
            <l>And this offence makes me for pardon crie,</l>
            <l>Since faults are objects of thy clemencie.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Jove</hi> would be ſoon diſarm'd, if he ſhould ſend,</l>
            <l>His thunder-bolts as oft as men offend.</l>
            <l>Now though his thunders make the world to fear,</l>
            <l>It breaks the clouds, and makes the aire more clear:</l>
            <l>Whom therefore father of the Gods we name,</l>
            <l>Than <hi>Jove</hi> none greater doth the world contain.</l>
            <l>Thou <hi>Pater Patriae</hi> too art call'd, then be,</l>
            <l>Like to thoſe Gods in name and clemencie.</l>
            <l>And ſo thou art, for no more moderate hand,</l>
            <l>Could hold the reines of Empire and command,</l>
            <l>Thy enemie once overcome in field</l>
            <l>Thou pardon'ſt, which he victor would not yield.</l>
            <l>And ſome thou did'ſt with honours dignifie,</l>
            <l>That have attempted 'gainſt thy majeſtie.</l>
            <l>Thy warres on one day did begin and ceaſe,</l>
            <l>While both ſides brought their offerings unto peace:</l>
            <l>That as the Victor in the vanquiſht Foe,</l>
            <l>The vanquiſht in the victor gloried ſo.</l>
            <l>My caſe is better ſince I ne're did joyne,</l>
            <l>With thoſe who did in arms 'gainſt thee combine.</l>
            <l>By Sea, by Earth, and <hi>Stygian</hi> Gods I ſwear,</l>
            <l>And by thy ſelf whoſe God-like power I fear.</l>
            <l>My thoughts, though wanting means to be expreſt,</l>
            <l>As faithful were, as thoſe who moſt profeſt.</l>
            <l>For I did joyne my frequent prayers with them,</l>
            <l>That thou might'ſt here long wear thy Diadem.</l>
            <l>And for thy ſafety made a poor expence,</l>
            <l>To pleaſe the Gods with offered Frankincenſe,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:20"/>
            <l>Beſides, thoſe faulty books of mine contain,</l>
            <l>In many places, thy moſt ſacred name.</l>
            <l>And if thou would'ſt that worke of mine peruſe.</l>
            <l>Of changed ſhapes, ſnatcht from my baniſht Muſe;</l>
            <l>In it thy name ſtill mention'd thou ſhalt finde,</l>
            <l>And many things which ſhew my humble minde.</l>
            <l>For though my hapleſs Muſe cannot aſpire,</l>
            <l>To raiſe thy fame and glory any higher;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Jove's</hi> pleas'd when we his glorious acts rehearſe,</l>
            <l>And make him be the ſubject of our verſe.</l>
            <l>And when we do the Giants warres recite,</l>
            <l>In his own praiſes be doth ſure delight.</l>
            <l>Others may celebrate thy ſacred name,</l>
            <l>And ſing thy praiſes in a fluent veine.</l>
            <l>Though we an hundred Bulls do ſacrifice,</l>
            <l>The Gods the ſmalleſt gifts do not deſpiſe.</l>
            <l>But oh! more cruel then a foe was he,</l>
            <l>Who firſt did ſhew my wanton lines to thee.</l>
            <l>Leſt that my verſes which thy fame do ſpread,</l>
            <l>Might ſo with equal favour now be read.</l>
            <l>Y t thou being angry, who durſt love profeſs?</l>
            <l>For I did hate my ſelf in my diſtreſs,</l>
            <l>As in ſome falling houſe the heavy weight,</l>
            <l>The firſt declining poſts oppreſſes ſtreight.</l>
            <l>So when that fortune an eſtate doth rend,</l>
            <l>All things by their own weight to ruine tend.</l>
            <l>The people likewiſe hate me for my books,</l>
            <l>And ſo compoſe themſelves unto thy looks.</l>
            <l>Yet I remember in my younger daies,</l>
            <l>My life and manners thou didſt often praiſe.</l>
            <l>For though unthriving honeſty obtain</l>
            <l>No honour, yet no crime did ſoile my fame.</l>
            <l>The Defendants cauſe ſometimes in hand I took,</l>
            <l>On which the hundred Senators ſhould look.</l>
            <l>And when I private matters did compound,</l>
            <l>Each ſide the juſtice of my ſentence found.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:20"/>
            <l>And if at laſt I had not thus offended,</l>
            <l>I know thou haſt me formerly commended.</l>
            <l>This laſt deſtroyes me, ſinks my ſhip below</l>
            <l>The waves, which often did in ſafety go.</l>
            <l>Nor did ſome ſmall and little wave diſtreſs me,</l>
            <l>But a whole Ocean did at once oppreſſe me.</l>
            <l>Alas, why have my eyes thus hapleſs been,</l>
            <l>To give me knowledge of a private ſin.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Acteon</hi> did <hi>Diana</hi> naked ſpie,</l>
            <l>And yet for this he by his hounds did die.</l>
            <l>Though fortune did offend in this, nor he,</l>
            <l>Yet errours 'gainſt the Gods muſt puniſht be.</l>
            <l>Even ſo that day that errour me betray'd,</l>
            <l>A ſmall, but not ignoble houſe decay'd.</l>
            <l>Yet ſuch as from antiquity hath ſhown,</l>
            <l>Armes that have been inferiour unto none.</l>
            <l>Not Wealthy, nor yet e're with want diſgrac'd,</l>
            <l>But with the houſes of the Gentry plac'd.</l>
            <l>And if my houſe had borne an humble name,</l>
            <l>It had been famous by my fluent veine.</l>
            <l>Which though I us'd more lightly then became,</l>
            <l>Yet all the world beareth up my name.</l>
            <l>The learned too have <hi>Naſo</hi> known, nor fear</l>
            <l>To place him with thoſe that renowned were.</l>
            <l>Yet now this houſe which by my Muſe was rais'd</l>
            <l>Is by one fault of mine again diſgrac'd.</l>
            <l>Yet fallen ſo as it it ſelf may rear,</l>
            <l>If <hi>Caſar's</hi> wrath would once more milde appear.</l>
            <l>Whoſe mercie in my ſentence was expreſt,</l>
            <l>Farre ſhort of that my fear did firſt ſuggeſt,</l>
            <l>Whoſe anger reacht not to this life of ours,</l>
            <l>But with great mildneſs us'd thy Princely powers,</l>
            <l>And thou my forfeit goods to me did'ſt give,</l>
            <l>And with my life did'ſt grant me means to live.</l>
            <l>Nor by the <hi>Senates</hi> ſentence was I ſent,</l>
            <l>Or private judgement into baniſhment,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:21"/>
            <l>But didſt thy ſelf pronounce thoſe heavie words,</l>
            <l>Whoſe execution full revenge affords.</l>
            <l>Beſides, thy Edict forcing my exile,</l>
            <l>Did with great favour my late fault enſtile.</l>
            <l>Whereby I am not baniſht but Confin'd,</l>
            <l>And miſery is in gentle words aſſign'd.</l>
            <l>For there's no puniſhment though ne're ſo ſtrict,</l>
            <l>Can more then thy diſpleaſure me afflict.</l>
            <l>Yet ſometimes angry Gods appeaſed are,</l>
            <l>And when the Clouds are gone, the day is fair.</l>
            <l>I have ſeen the Elm loaden with Vines again,</l>
            <l>That had before been ſtrucken by <hi>Joves</hi> flame:</l>
            <l>Therefore Ile hope, ſince thou canſt not deny</l>
            <l>To grant me this even in my miſery.</l>
            <l>Thy mercy makes me hope, till I reflect</l>
            <l>Upon my fault, which doth all hope reject:</l>
            <l>And as the rage of Seas by winds incens'd,</l>
            <l>Is not with equal fury ſtill commenc'd:</l>
            <l>But that ſometimes a quiet calm it hath,</l>
            <l>And ſeems to have laid by his former wrath:</l>
            <l>Even ſo my various thoughts do make me fare,</l>
            <l>Now calm'd by hope, then troubled with deſpair,</l>
            <l>By thoſe ſame Gods that grant thee long to reign,</l>
            <l>That thou maiſt ſtill maintain the <hi>Roman</hi> name.</l>
            <l>And by thy Countrie happie in thy fate,</l>
            <l>Where I a ſubject were of thine of late.</l>
            <l>May ſo the City render thee due love,</l>
            <l>For thy great acts which do thy mind approve.</l>
            <l>So may thy <hi>Livia</hi> live here many years,</l>
            <l>Who only worthie of thy love appears.</l>
            <l>Whom nature kept for thee, elſe there had been,</l>
            <l>None worthie to have been thy Royal Queen.</l>
            <l>So may thy Son grow up, and with his father,</l>
            <l>Rule this ſame Empire happily together.</l>
            <l>And by his acts and thine, which time can't bide,</l>
            <l>May both your off-ſprings ſo be ſtellifi'd.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:21"/>
            <l>May victory ſo accuſtom'd to thy Tent,</l>
            <l>Come to his coulours, and her ſelf preſent;</l>
            <l>And fly about him with diſplayed wings,</l>
            <l>While ſhe a Laurel wreath to crown him brings.</l>
            <l>To whom thou doſt thy wars command reſign,</l>
            <l>And giveſt him that fortune that was thine.</l>
            <l>While thou thy ſelf at home in peace doſt reign,</l>
            <l>Thy other ſelf doth foraign Wars maintain.</l>
            <l>May he return a victor o're his ſoe,</l>
            <l>And on his plumed horſe in triumph go.</l>
            <l>Oh ſpare me therfore! and do now lay by</l>
            <l>Thy Thunder, which hath bred my miſery.</l>
            <l>Spare me thou <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> let that name,</l>
            <l>Give me ſome hope, to pleaſe thee once again.</l>
            <l>I ſue not to repeal my baniſhment,</l>
            <l>Though unto greater ſutes the Gods aſſent.</l>
            <l>For if thou wouldſt ſome milder place aſign</l>
            <l>Of exile, it would eaſe this grief of mine.</l>
            <l>For here I ſuffer even the worſt of woes,</l>
            <l>While I do live amongſt the barbarous foes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Being ſent unto <hi>Danubius</hi> ſeven-fold ſtream,</l>
            <l>Whereas <hi>Caliſtho</hi> drives her frozen Team.</l>
            <l>And while the ſilver waves do gently ſlide,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Colchians</hi> from the <hi>Getes</hi> can ſcarce divide:</l>
            <l>And though for greater faults ſome are profcrib'd,</l>
            <l>Yet none in farther baniſhment abide.</l>
            <l>Beyond this, nought but cold and foes remain,</l>
            <l>And ſeas that are bound with an Icye Chain.</l>
            <l>Part of the <hi>Euxine</hi> ſea which <hi>Rome</hi> commands</l>
            <l>Runs here, and then below <hi>Sarmatia</hi> ſtands.</l>
            <l>Here doth the ſpreading <hi>Roman</hi> Empire end,</l>
            <l>Whoſe utmoſt bounds do hither ſcarce extend,</l>
            <l>This makes me pray to be removed hence,</l>
            <l>A peaceful exile granting my offence.</l>
            <l>Nor with thoſe people may a captive bide,</l>
            <l>Who once enrag'd the <hi>Iſter</hi> can't divide.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:22"/>
            <l>Beſides, a free-born <hi>Roman</hi> cannot be,</l>
            <l>By foreign hands held in captivity.</l>
            <l>Though two faults, verſe, and errour me oppreſt,</l>
            <l>The latter ſhall in, ſilence be ſuppreſt.</l>
            <l>I am unworthy to renew the wound,</l>
            <l>O <hi>Caeſar,</hi> by which I the ſmart have found.</l>
            <l>But of my fault they urge a ſecond part,</l>
            <l>In that I taught Loves wanton idle Art.</l>
            <l>I ſee that human acts the Gods deceive,</l>
            <l>My fault is not ſuch as thou doſt believe.</l>
            <l>For as great <hi>Jove</hi> that heaven beholding ſits,</l>
            <l>No leiſure unto ſmall affairs admits:</l>
            <l>So when this under Orbe thou doſt o're-look ,</l>
            <l>Thy royal thoughts no meaner cares do brook.</l>
            <l>As that thou ſhouldſt (my Leige) have ſo muſh leiſure,</l>
            <l>To read my verſe, fram'd with unequal meaſure.</l>
            <l>It ſeems the weight of the <hi>Roman</hi> name does lye,</l>
            <l>Not on thy ſhoulders very heavily.</l>
            <l>That thou wouldſt deign to mark thoſe idle lines;</l>
            <l>And view what I had writ at idle times.</l>
            <l>Now thou rebelling <hi>Hungary</hi> doſt tame,</l>
            <l>While as the <hi>Thracians</hi> menace arms again.</l>
            <l>The <hi>Armenians</hi> ſeeking peace, the <hi>Parthian</hi> ſhows</l>
            <l>His ſpreading colours, and do bend their bows.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Germany</hi> feels thy valour in thy Son,</l>
            <l>While <hi>Caeſars</hi> foes, young <hi>Caeſar</hi> doth o're-come.</l>
            <l>And laſtly through thy Empires large extention.</l>
            <l>No part doth fall away through thy prevention.</l>
            <l>The City and the Laws thou doſt defend,</l>
            <l>And by example doſt thy ſubjects mend.</l>
            <l>Nor with thy people doſt thou live at eaſe,</l>
            <l>When by thy wars thou ſetteſt them in peace.</l>
            <l>'Mongſt ſuch affairs I wounder thou hadſt time</l>
            <l>For to peruſe thoſe Idle jeſts of mine.</l>
            <l>Or if thou readſt them with a quiet thought,</l>
            <l>I wiſh that in my art thou hadſt read no fault.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:22"/>
            <l>It was not for ſeverer judgements writ,</l>
            <l>And for thy princely view it was unfit.</l>
            <l>Yet ſuch as doth not 'gainſt thy laws offend,</l>
            <l>Or wanton rules to marryed Wives commend.</l>
            <l>And leaſt thou doubt to whom they written were,</l>
            <l>In one book of the three, theſe verſes are.</l>
            <l>Away all you whoſe fillets bind your hair:</l>
            <l>And you that ankle-touching garments wear:</l>
            <l>The lawfull ſcapes of love we here rehearſe,</l>
            <l>That ſo their may be no fault in my verſe.</l>
            <l>What though we baniſh from this Art all ſuch</l>
            <l>As the robe and fillet bids us not to touch.</l>
            <l>Yet may the Matron uſe another art,</l>
            <l>And draw from thence what I did ne'r impart.</l>
            <l>Let the Matron then not read, for ſhe may find,</l>
            <l>Matter in all verſe to corrupt her mind.</l>
            <l>What e're ſhe touches, ſhe that delights in ill,</l>
            <l>Of vices knowledge ſhe may learn the skill.</l>
            <l>Let her the <hi>Annales</hi> take (though moſt ſevere)</l>
            <l>The fault of <hi>Ilia</hi> will thereby appear.</l>
            <l>And in the <hi>Aeneads</hi> read as in the other,</l>
            <l>How wanton <hi>Venus</hi> was <hi>Aeneas</hi> mother.</l>
            <l>And I will ſhew beneath in every kind,</l>
            <l>That there's no verſe but may corrupt the mind,</l>
            <l>Yet every book is not for this to blame,</l>
            <l>Since nothing profits but may hurt again.</l>
            <l>Than ſire what better, yet he that doth deſire</l>
            <l>To burne a houſe, doth arm himſelf with ſire.</l>
            <l>Health-giving phyſick, health doth oft empair,</l>
            <l>Some hearbs are wholeſome and ſome poyſon are.</l>
            <l>The chief and traveller ſwords wear, to th' end,</l>
            <l>Th' one may aſſault, the other may defend.</l>
            <l>Though eloquence ſhould plead the honeſt cauſe,</l>
            <l>It may defend the guilty by the laws.</l>
            <l>So if my verſe be read with a good mind,</l>
            <l>Thou ſhalt be ſure in it no hurt to find.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:23"/>
            <l>He therefore erres who led by ſelf-conceit,</l>
            <l>Doth miſ-interpret whatſoe're I write.</l>
            <l>Why are there Cloiſters, wherein Maids do walk,</l>
            <l>That with their Lovers they may meet and talk?</l>
            <l>The Temple though moſt ſacred let her ſhun,</l>
            <l>That with an evil mind doth thither come,</l>
            <l>For in <hi>Joves</hi> temple her thoughts will ſuggeſt,</l>
            <l>How many Maids by <hi>Jove,</hi> have been oppreſt:</l>
            <l>And think in <hi>Junoe's</hi> temples when ſhes praying,</l>
            <l>How <hi>Juno</hi> injur'd was by <hi>Joves</hi> oft ſtraying;</l>
            <l>And <hi>Pallas</hi> ſeen, ſhe thinks ſome faulty birth,</l>
            <l>Made her to hide <hi>Ericthon</hi> born of earth:</l>
            <l>If ſhe come to <hi>Mars's</hi> temple, o're the gate,</l>
            <l>There ſtandeth <hi>Venus</hi> with her cuning mate.</l>
            <l>In <hi>Iſis</hi> temple, ſhe revolveth how,</l>
            <l>Poor <hi>Io</hi> was tranſform'd into a Cow.</l>
            <l>And ſomething then her wandring fancy moves,</l>
            <l>To think of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Anchiſes</hi> loves.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Jaſus</hi> and <hi>Ceres</hi> next her thoughts encite,</l>
            <l>And pale <hi>Endimion</hi> the Moons favourite,</l>
            <l>For though thoſe ſtatues were for prayer aſſign'd,</l>
            <l>Yet every thing corrupts an evil mind,</l>
            <l>And my firſt leaf bids them not read that Art,</l>
            <l>Which I to Harlots only did impart.</l>
            <l>And ſince in maidens it is thought a crime,</l>
            <l>For to preſs farther than the Prieſts aſſign:</l>
            <l>Is ſhe not faulty then, who not forbears</l>
            <l>To read my verſes, prohibited chaſte cares?</l>
            <l>Matrons to view thoſe pictures are content,</l>
            <l>Which various ſhapes of venery preſent?</l>
            <l>And Veſtal Virgins do peruſe the ſame,</l>
            <l>For which the Author doth receive no blame.</l>
            <l>Yet why did I that wanton vein approve?</l>
            <l>Why doth my Book perſwade them unto love?</l>
            <l>It was my fault which I do hear confeſs,</l>
            <l>My wit and judgement did therein tranſgreſs.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:23"/>
            <l>Why did not I of <hi>Troy's</hi> ſad ruin tell,</l>
            <l>(That vexed theme) which by the <hi>Graecians</hi> fell.</l>
            <l>Or <hi>Thebes</hi> ſeven gates which ſeverally kept,</l>
            <l>Where by mutual wounds thoſe brothers dy'd and ſlept.</l>
            <l>An ample ſubject warlike <hi>Rome</hi> afforded,</l>
            <l>Whoſe acts I might have piouſly recorded.</l>
            <l>And though great <hi>Caeſars</hi> deeds abroad are known,</l>
            <l>Yet by my verſe ſome part I might have ſhown:</l>
            <l>For as the Suns bright rayes do draw the ſight,</l>
            <l>So might thy acts my willing Muſe incite.</l>
            <l>Yet 'twas no fault to plough a little field,</l>
            <l>Knowing that theme doth fertile matter yield.</l>
            <l>For though the Cock-boat through the Lake do row,</l>
            <l>She dare not venture unto ſea to go.</l>
            <l>This I did fear, for though my lighter vein,</l>
            <l>To frame ſome ſlender meaſures can attain;</l>
            <l>Yet had I took to write the Gyants war,</l>
            <l>That work for me had been to heavy far.</l>
            <l>That happy wits of <hi>Caeſars</hi> acts may tell,</l>
            <l>Whoſe high ſtrain'd lines his acts can parallel.</l>
            <l>And though I once attempted ſuch an act,</l>
            <l>Me thought my verſe did from thy worth detract.</l>
            <l>Then to my Youthful Layes I went again,</l>
            <l>And writ of love, under a fained name.</l>
            <l>The fates did draw me 'gainſt my own intent,</l>
            <l>By writing to obtain a baniſhment.</l>
            <l>Why learnt I by my parents care, or why</l>
            <l>Did tempting books detain my buſie eye?</l>
            <l>For this thou hat'ſt me, ſince thou doſt diſtruſt,</l>
            <l>I taught by art how to ſolicite luſt.</l>
            <l>When I to wives no theft of love did ſhow,</l>
            <l>How could I teach what I did never know?</l>
            <l>For though ſome ſmooth ſoft verſes I did frame,</l>
            <l>No ill report could ever wound my fame.</l>
            <l>Nor can ſome husband of the vulgar rank,</l>
            <l>For being made a doubtful father, thank</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:24"/>
            <l>My verſe, by which my thoughts are not expreſt,</l>
            <l>My life is modeſt, though my muſe love jeſt.</l>
            <l>Beſides, my works are Fictions, and do crave</l>
            <l>Some liberty, which their Authour may not have.</l>
            <l>Nor do books ſhew the mind, whoſe chief intention,</l>
            <l>Is to delight the ear with new invention.</l>
            <l>Should <hi>Accius</hi> cruel be, <hi>Terence</hi> delight</l>
            <l>In bankets, and all warriours who do write</l>
            <l>Of wars, and laſtly ſome have love-layes fram'd,</l>
            <l>Who though like faulty, yet are not like blam'd.</l>
            <l>What did the harping old man teach in rhyme,</l>
            <l>But to ſteep <hi>Venus</hi> in the heat of Wine?</l>
            <l>And <hi>Sappho</hi> doth inſtruct maids how to love,</l>
            <l>Yet he nor <hi>Sappho</hi> no man doth reprove.</l>
            <l>Who blames <hi>Battiades</hi> that abus'd his leaſure,</l>
            <l>In wanton verſe to ſet forth his own pleaſure?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Menanders</hi> pleaſant merry tales of love,</l>
            <l>The harmleſs thoughts of virgins do approve.</l>
            <l>What do the <hi>Iliads</hi> ſhew, but wars ſad ſhape,</l>
            <l>In the regaining an adulterous rape.</l>
            <l>And how <hi>Achilles Chryſes</hi> love enflam'd,</l>
            <l>And how the <hi>Grecians Helen</hi> back regain'd.</l>
            <l>The <hi>Odyſſes</hi> ſhew how in a wooing ſtrife,</l>
            <l>Thoſe ſutors vainly ſought <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> wife.</l>
            <l>And <hi>Homer</hi> tells how <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> ty'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>In cloſe embraces, by the Gods were ſpy'd.</l>
            <l>Whom but from <hi>Homer</hi> could we ever know,</l>
            <l>How two fair Ladies lov'd a ſtranger ſo?</l>
            <l>The tragedies in ſtatelineſs excel,</l>
            <l>Yet thoſe of loves affairs do often tell.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hyppolitus</hi> was loved of his mother,</l>
            <l>And fait <hi>Canace</hi> did affect her brother.</l>
            <l>When <hi>Menelaus Helen</hi> bore away,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Cupid</hi> did drive the chariot on that day.</l>
            <l>When in the Childrens bloud the mother dyes</l>
            <l>The ſword, this act from frantick love did riſe,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:24"/>
            <l>Love to a <hi>Lapwing</hi> chang'd the <hi>Thracian</hi> King,</l>
            <l>And fitted <hi>Progne</hi> with a Swallows wing.</l>
            <l>And 'twas a brothers love that did affright,</l>
            <l>The Sun, and made him for to hide his light.</l>
            <l>Never ſhould <hi>Scylla</hi> on the ſtage appear.</l>
            <l>But that love made her clip her fathers hair.</l>
            <l>And whoſo reads <hi>Oreſtes</hi> frantick fears,</l>
            <l>Of murthered <hi>Pyrrhas</hi> and <hi>Aegiſthus</hi> heares.</l>
            <l>What name I him did the <hi>Chimaera</hi> tame?</l>
            <l>Whoſe treacheous hoſteſs ſought his life in vain.</l>
            <l>What of <hi>Hermione</hi> or the <hi>Arcadian</hi> Maid?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Phoebe</hi> whoſe courſe the <hi>Latmian</hi> lover ſtaid.</l>
            <l>Or what of <hi>Danae,</hi> by <hi>Jove</hi> a mother grown,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Hercules</hi> got, in two nights joyn'd in one.</l>
            <l>To theſe adde <hi>Yole, Pyrrhus</hi> and that Boy,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sweet Hylas,</hi> with <hi>Paris,</hi> fire-brand unto
<hi>Troy.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And ſhould I here recite loves tragick flames,</l>
            <l>My book would ſcarce contain their very names.</l>
            <l>Thus tragedies to wanton laughter bend,</l>
            <l>And many ſhameful words in them they blend.</l>
            <l>Some blameleſs have <hi>Achilles</hi> acts defac'd,</l>
            <l>And by ſoft meaſures have his deeds diſgrac'd.</l>
            <l>Though <hi>Ariſtides</hi> his own faults compil'd,</l>
            <l>Yet <hi>Ariſtides</hi> was not ſtraight exil'd.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Eubius</hi> did write an impure hiſtory,</l>
            <l>And does deſcribe unwholſom venery.</l>
            <l>Nor he that <hi>Sybarin</hi> luxuries compoſed,</l>
            <l>Nor he that his own ſinful acts diſcloſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Theſe in the libraries by ſome bounteous hand,</l>
            <l>To publick uſe do there devoted ſtand.</l>
            <l>By ſtrangers pens I need not ſeek defence,</l>
            <l>Our own books with ſuch liberty diſpence.</l>
            <l>For though grave <hi>Ennius</hi> of wars tumults writ,</l>
            <l>Whoſe artleſs works do ſhew an able wit.</l>
            <l>The cauſe of fire <hi>Lucretius</hi> doth explain,</l>
            <l>And ſhews how three cauſes did this world frame.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:25"/>
            <l>Wanton <hi>Catullus</hi> yet his Muſe did task,</l>
            <l>To praiſe his Miſtreſs, whom he then did mask</l>
            <l>Under the name of <hi>Lesbia,</hi> and ſo ſtrove;</l>
            <l>In verſe to publiſh his own wanton love.</l>
            <l>And with like licence <hi>Calvus</hi> too aſſaies,</l>
            <l>For to ſet forth his pleaſure divers waies.</l>
            <l>Why ſhould I mention <hi>Memnons</hi> wanton vein?</l>
            <l>Who to each filthy act doth give a name.</l>
            <l>And <hi>Cinna</hi> ſtriving by his verſe to pleaſe</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Cornificus,</hi> may well be rank'd with theſe:</l>
            <l>And he that did commend to after fame,</l>
            <l>His love diſguiſed by <hi>Metellus</hi> name.</l>
            <l>And he that ſailed for the fleece of gold,</l>
            <l>His ſecret thefts of love doth oft unfold.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hortenſius</hi> too, and <hi>Servius</hi> writ as bad,</l>
            <l>Who'd think my fault ſo great examples had?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Siſenna Ariſtides</hi> works tranſlates,</l>
            <l>And oft in wanton jeſts expatiates.</l>
            <l>For praiſing <hi>Lycoris,</hi> none doth <hi>Gallus</hi> blame,</l>
            <l>If that his tounge in wine he could contain.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Tibullus</hi> writes that womens oathes are wind,</l>
            <l>Who can with outward ſhews their husbands blind,</l>
            <l>Teaching them how their keepers to beguile,</l>
            <l>While he himſelf is conſen'd by that wiſe,</l>
            <l>That he would take occaſion for to try</l>
            <l>Her ring, that he might touch her hand thereby.</l>
            <l>By private tokens he would talk ſometime,</l>
            <l>And on the table draw a wanton ſign:</l>
            <l>Teaching what oyles that blewneſs ſhall expel,</l>
            <l>Which by much kiſſing on their lips doth dwell.</l>
            <l>And unto husbands do ſtrict rules commend,</l>
            <l>If they be honeſt, wives will not offend.</l>
            <l>And when the dog doth barke, to know before,</l>
            <l>That 'tis their Lover that ſtands at the door.</l>
            <l>And many notes of Love-thefts he doth leave.</l>
            <l>And teacheth wives their husbands to deceive.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:25"/>
            <l>Yet is <hi>Tibullus</hi> read and famous grown,</l>
            <l>And unto thee great <hi>Caeſar</hi> he was known.</l>
            <l>And though <hi>Propertiue</hi> did like precepts give,</l>
            <l>Yet his clear fame doth ſtill unſtained live.</l>
            <l>To theſe did I ſucceed, for I'le ſuppreſs</l>
            <l>Their names who live, and faulty are no leſs.</l>
            <l>I fear'd not where ſo many ſhips had paſt,</l>
            <l>That my poor bark ſhould ſhipwrackt be at laſt.</l>
            <l>For ſome do ſhew the Art to play at dice,</l>
            <l>Which was in former times eſteem'd a vice.</l>
            <l>And how to make the dice ſtill higher run,</l>
            <l>And ſo the little looſing Ace to ſhun.</l>
            <l>Or how to caſt and ſtrike a Dye again.</l>
            <l>To run that chance which any one ſhall name.</l>
            <l>And how at Drafts a crowned King to make,</l>
            <l>And play your man where none the ſame can take.</l>
            <l>To know to chaſe, and to retire, and then</l>
            <l>In flying how to back your man again.</l>
            <l>And ſome the game of three-ſtones likewiſe ſhow,</l>
            <l>Where he does win that brings them on a row.</l>
            <l>Others in ſundry games like pains do take,</l>
            <l>Wherein we loſe our time to win a ſtake.</l>
            <l>And ſome of Tennis-play do alſo ſing,</l>
            <l>And do inſtruct us how by art to ſwim.</l>
            <l>Here one the ſecrets of face-drugs diſcloſes,</l>
            <l>Another laws of crowned feaſts compoſes.</l>
            <l>And the beſt day he likewiſe doth aſſign.</l>
            <l>And what Cups do become the ſparkling wine.</l>
            <l>And in <hi>December</hi> merry ryhmes ate ſung,</l>
            <l>By which the Winter doth ſuſtain no wrong.</l>
            <l>So I to write ſome merry verſes meant,</l>
            <l>Which ſtraight were puniſht with ſad baniſhment.</l>
            <l>Of all theſe former writers there was none,</l>
            <l>Whoſe Muſe did ruine him, but I alone.</l>
            <l>If I had jeſted in ſome Mimick vein,</l>
            <l>Which wanton Sceanes of love doth ſtill contain.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:26"/>
            <l>In which the Lover does come forth to wooe,</l>
            <l>And wanton wives do cheat their husbands too:</l>
            <l>Yet theſe, Maids, Matrons, and old men delight,</l>
            <l>And 'fore the Senate acted are by night.</l>
            <l>Whoſe wanton language doth the ear prophane.</l>
            <l>Making looſe offers at thoſe acts of ſhame.</l>
            <l>When husbands are beguil'd by pretty waies,</l>
            <l>They applaud the Poet, and do give him bayes.</l>
            <l>He gains by being puniſh'd for his crimes,</l>
            <l>And makes the <hi>Praetor</hi> pay more for his lines.</l>
            <l>And when (great <hi>Caeſar</hi>) thou doſt ſet forth playes,</l>
            <l>The Poet's pay'd, that did the plot firſt raiſe.</l>
            <l>Which thou beholdeſt, and haſt ſet out to view,</l>
            <l>Whereby thou doſt thy gracious mildneſs ſhew.</l>
            <l>And with thoſe eyes which make the world to fear,</l>
            <l>Thou ſaw'ſt the Scenes of love that acted were.</l>
            <l>If Mimicks may write in a wanton ſtrain,</l>
            <l>Why ſhould my verſe ſuch puniſhment obtain?</l>
            <l>Are they by licence of the ſtage protected?</l>
            <l>Which makes the Mimicks bawdy jeſts affected.</l>
            <l>My poems too have made the people riſe,</l>
            <l>To help attention with their greedy eyes.</l>
            <l>Though in your houſe the lively pictures ſtand,</l>
            <l>Of Noblemen drawn by the painters hand:</l>
            <l>Yet have you wanton tables hanging by,</l>
            <l>Which ſhew the divers ſhapes of venery.</l>
            <l>Though you have <hi>Ajax</hi> picture full of ire,</l>
            <l>And fierce <hi>Medea</hi> with her eyes like fire.</l>
            <l>Yet <hi>Venus</hi> ſeems to dry her moyſtned hairs</l>
            <l>As if from ſea ſhe newly did repair.</l>
            <l>Let others of wars bloudy tumults write,</l>
            <l>And of thy acts which learned pens invite.</l>
            <l>Nature hath ſcanted me and doth reſtrain,</l>
            <l>To meaner ſubjects this my humble vein.</l>
            <l>Yet <hi>Virgil</hi> who is read with much delight,</l>
            <l>Doth of the acts of brave <hi>Aeneas</hi> write.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:26"/>
            <l>And no part is with greater favour read,</l>
            <l>Then where he brings him to Queen <hi>Dido's</hi> bed.</l>
            <l>Yet in his youth he did commend fair <hi>Phillis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And ſports himſelf in praiſing <hi>Amarillis.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And though I formerly in that ſame vein</l>
            <l>Offended, yet I now do bear the blame.</l>
            <l>I had writ verſes, when before thee I,</l>
            <l>Amongſt the other horſe-men paſſed by.</l>
            <l>And now my age doth even bear the blame</l>
            <l>Of thoſe things which my younger years did frame,</l>
            <l>My faulty books are now reveng'd at laſt,</l>
            <l>And I am puniſh'd for a fault that's paſt.</l>
            <l>Yet all my works are not ſo light and vain,</l>
            <l>Sometimes I lanch'd into the deeper main.</l>
            <l>And in ſix books <hi>Romes</hi> holidaies have ſhew'd,</l>
            <l>Where with the Month each Volume doth conclude.</l>
            <l>And to thy ſacred name did dedicate</l>
            <l>That work, though left unperfect by my fate.</l>
            <l>Beſides, I ſtately Tragedies have writ,</l>
            <l>And with high words the Tragick ſtile did fit:</l>
            <l>Beſides, of changed ſhapes my muſe did chant,</l>
            <l>Though they my laſt life-giving hand did want.</l>
            <l>And would thy anger were but ſo appeas'd,</l>
            <l>As that to read my verſe thou wouldſt be pleas'd.</l>
            <l>My verſe, where from the infant birth of things,</l>
            <l>My Muſe her work unto thy own time brings.</l>
            <l>Thou ſhouldſt behold the ſtrength of every line,</l>
            <l>Wherein I ſtrive to praiſe both thee and thine.</l>
            <l>Nor are my verſes mingled ſo with gall,</l>
            <l>As that my lines ſhould be Satyrical.</l>
            <l>Amongſt the vulger people none yet found,</l>
            <l>Themſelves once touch'd, my Muſe my ſelf doth wound.</l>
            <l>Therefore each generous mind I do believe.</l>
            <l>Will not rejoyce, but at my ill fare grieve.</l>
            <l>Nor yet will triumph o're my wretched ſtate.</l>
            <l>Who ne're was proud even in my better fate.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:27"/>
            <l>O therefore let theſe reaſons change thy mind</l>
            <l>That in diſtreſs I may thy favour find,</l>
            <l>Not to return, though that perhaps may be,</l>
            <l>When thou in time at laſt maiſt pardon me.</l>
            <l>But I intreat thee to remove me hence,</l>
            <l>To ſafer exile fitting my offence.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <head>LIB. 3.</head>
            <div n="1" type="elegy">
               <argument>
                  <l>The Book doth to the Reader ſhew,</l>
                  <l>That he it loath to come to view;</l>
                  <l>And tels how he was entertain'd</l>
                  <l>By ſome, while others him diſdain'd.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>I Am that Book who fearfully do come,</l>
               <l>Even from a baniſht man to viſit <hi>Rome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And coming weary from a foraign land,</l>
               <l>Good Reader let me reſt within thy hand.</l>
               <l>Do not thou fear or be aſham'd of me,</l>
               <l>Since no love verſes in this paper be.</l>
               <l>My Maſter now by fortune is oppreſt,</l>
               <l>It is no time for him to write in jeſt;</l>
               <l>Though in his youth he had a wanton vein,</l>
               <l>Yet now he doth condemn that work again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Behold! here's nothing but ſad mourning lines,</l>
               <l>So that my verſe agreeth with his times.</l>
               <l>And that my ſecond verſe is lame in ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Short feet do cauſe it, or the journies length.</l>
               <l>Nor are my rough leaves cover'd o're with yellow,</l>
               <l>For I my authors fortune mean to follow.</l>
               <l>And though ſome blots my clearer letters ſtain,</l>
               <l>Know that my authors toars did make the ſame.</l>
               <l>If thou my language ſcarcely underſtand,</l>
               <l>Know that he writ me in a barbarous land.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:27"/>
               <l>Therefore good Reader teach me where to go,</l>
               <l>Some place of reſt unto a ſtrange book ſhow.</l>
               <l>This having ſaid, with words which grief made ſlow,</l>
               <l>One ready was the way to me to ſhow.</l>
               <l>I thankt him, and did pray the Gods that he,</l>
               <l>Might like my Maſter never baniſht be.</l>
               <l>Lead on, and I will follow by thy hand,</l>
               <l>Though I am tir'd with paſſing ſea and land.</l>
               <l>He did conſent, and as we went, quoth he,</l>
               <l>This is the holy ſtreet which thou doſt ſee.</l>
               <l>Here's <hi>Veſtaes</hi> Temple that keeps holy fire,</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Numa's</hi> lofty pallace doth aſpire,</l>
               <l>Here is <hi>Evanders</hi> gate, and now you come,</l>
               <l>Unto that place where they firſt builded <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And then quoth I, this is the houſe of <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This oaken crown doth my conjecture prove.</l>
               <l>He told me it was <hi>Caeſars,</hi> nay then, quoth I,</l>
               <l>I ſee great <hi>Jove</hi> dwels here in Majeſty.</l>
               <l>Yet why doth Bayes upon the gates appear?</l>
               <l>And thus incircle <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſtatue here?</l>
               <l>In it becauſe his houſe doth merit praiſe?</l>
               <l>And is beloved of the God of Bayes.</l>
               <l>Or doth it now denote a Feſtival?</l>
               <l>In token of that peace he gives to all.</l>
               <l>Or as the Lawrel evermore is green,</l>
               <l>So ſtill his houſe moſt flouriſhing hath been.</l>
               <l>Or do thoſe letters on the wreath engrav'd,</l>
               <l>Shew that that City by his power was ſav'd.</l>
               <l>Oh <hi>Caeſar!</hi> ſave one Citizen at laſt,</l>
               <l>Who now into the utmoſt world is caſt.</l>
               <l>Where he ſad puniſhment doth ſtill ſuſtain,</l>
               <l>Which he by errour only did obtain.</l>
               <l>Alaſs while I view <hi>Caeſars</hi> pallace here,</l>
               <l>My letters ſeem to quake with trembling fear.</l>
               <l>Doſt thou not ſee my paper does look pale,</l>
               <l>And how my trembling feet begin to fail?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:28"/>
               <l>I pray that this ſame houſe which now I ſee,</l>
               <l>May to my maſter reconciled be.</l>
               <l>From thence we to <hi>Apollo's</hi> Temple went,</l>
               <l>To which by ſteps there is a fair aſcent.</l>
               <l>Where ſtand the ſignes in fair outlandiſh ſtone,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Belus</hi> and of <hi>Palamed</hi> the ſonne.</l>
               <l>There ancient books, and thoſe that are more new,</l>
               <l>Do all lye open to the readers view.</l>
               <l>I ſought my brethren there, excepting them,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hapleſs birth my father doth condemn.</l>
               <l>And as I ſought, the chief man of that place,</l>
               <l>Bid me be gone out of that holy ſpace.</l>
               <l>I went to Temples to the Theater-joyn'd,</l>
               <l>But here no entertainment could I finde,</l>
               <l>Nor could I come unto the outward yard,</l>
               <l>Which unto learned books is not debar'd,</l>
               <l>We are heirs unto miſ-fortune by deſcent,</l>
               <l>And we his children ſuffer baniſhment.</l>
               <l>Perhaps when time doth <hi>Caeſar's</hi> wrath ſubdue,</l>
               <l>He will to him and us ſome favour ſhew.</l>
               <l>Since for the peoples help I do not care,</l>
               <l>O <hi>Caeſar</hi> hearken to my earneſt prayer.</l>
               <l>Since publick ſtalls are unto me deny'd,</l>
               <l>In private corners I my ſelf may hide:</l>
               <l>And you <hi>Plebeians</hi> take in hand again,</l>
               <l>My verſes which you once repuls'd with ſhame.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>In Swan-like tunes he doth deplore</l>
                  <l>His exile, and knocks at the door</l>
                  <l>Of death, deſiring haſty fare,</l>
                  <l>His wretched life would terminate.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>WAs it my fate that I ſhould <hi>Scythia</hi> ſee,</l>
               <l>And the land whoſe Zenith is the Axle-tree?</l>
               <l>And would not you ſweet Muſes nor <hi>Apollo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Help me, who did your holy rites ſtill follow?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:28"/>
               <l>Could not my hamleſs verſes me excuſe,</l>
               <l>And life more ſerious then jeſting Muſe?</l>
               <l>But that I muſt when I the ſeas had paſt,</l>
               <l>Unto the <hi>Pontick</hi> land be brought at laſt.</l>
               <l>And I that ſtill my ſelf from care with-drew,</l>
               <l>Loving ſoft eaſe, and no rough labour knew.</l>
               <l>Having paſt great dangers both by ſea and land,</l>
               <l>Here worſt of miſeries is by me ſuſtain'd.</l>
               <l>Yet I endure theſe evils, for I find,</l>
               <l>My body doth receive ſtrength from my mind.</l>
               <l>And in my paſſage to my ſad exile,</l>
               <l>I with my ſtudie did my cares beguile.</l>
               <l>But when I did my journies end attain,</l>
               <l>And that unto the hated ſhore I came:</l>
               <l>Then from mine eyes a ſhower of tears did flow,</l>
               <l>Like water runing from the melted ſnow.</l>
               <l>And then my houſe and <hi>Rome</hi> comes in my mind,</l>
               <l>And every thing that I had left behind.</l>
               <l>Alaſs that I ſhould knock ſtill at the grave,</l>
               <l>To be let in, yet can no entrance have.</l>
               <l>Why have I ſtill eſcaped from the ſword?</l>
               <l>Could not the ſea to me a death afford?</l>
               <l>You Gods who conſtant are in your juſt ire,</l>
               <l>And do with <hi>Caeſar</hi> in revenge conſpire.</l>
               <l>I do beſeech you haſten on my fate,</l>
               <l>And bid death open unto me the gate.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>He lets his wiſe here underſtand.</l>
                  <l>Of his ſickneſs in a forraign land.</l>
                  <l>Then writes his Epitaph, with intent</l>
                  <l>To make his Books his monument.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THat this my Letter by a ſtrangers hand</l>
               <l>Is writ, the cauſe, my ſickneſs underſtand.</l>
               <l>For in the worlds remoteſt part I lye</l>
               <l>Sick, and uncertain of recovery.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:29"/>
               <l>What comfort can within that climate ſhine.</l>
               <l>On which the <hi>Getes</hi> and <hi>Sauramates</hi> confine?</l>
               <l>My nature does not with the ſoile agree,</l>
               <l>The air and water does ſeem ſtrange to me.</l>
               <l>My ſhelter poor, my diet here is bad,</l>
               <l>No health-eſtoring phyſick can be had.</l>
               <l>No friend to comfort me, who will aſſay,</l>
               <l>With ſome diſcourſe to paſs the time away.</l>
               <l>But here upon my bed of ſickneſs caſt,</l>
               <l>I think of many things which now are paſt.</l>
               <l>And thou my deareſt wife above the reſt,</l>
               <l>Doſt hold the chiefeſt place within my breaſt.</l>
               <l>Thy abſent name is mentiond ſtill by me,</l>
               <l>And every day and night I think on thee.</l>
               <l>Sometimes I ſpeak things without ſenſe or wit,</l>
               <l>That I may name thee in my frantick fit.</l>
               <l>If I ſhould ſwound, and that no heating wine,</l>
               <l>Could give life to this faultring tongue of mine,</l>
               <l>To hear of thy approach would make me live,</l>
               <l>Thy very preſence would new vigor give.</l>
               <l>Thus I moſt doubtful of life an grown,</l>
               <l>But thou perhaps liv'ſt merrily at home.</l>
               <l>No, I dare ſay, that thou my deareſt wife.</l>
               <l>Doſt in my abſence lead a mourning life.</l>
               <l>Yet if the number of my years de done,</l>
               <l>And that my haſty thread of life is ſpun.</l>
               <l>You Gods you might with eaſe have let me have,</l>
               <l>Within my native land a happy grave.</l>
               <l>If that you would have let my death prevent,</l>
               <l>My fatal journey unto baniſhment;</l>
               <l>Then had I dy'd in my integrity,</l>
               <l>But now I here a baniſh'd man muſt dye.</l>
               <l>And ſhall I here reſigne my weary breath,</l>
               <l>The place makes me unhappy in my death.</l>
               <l>Upon my bed I ſhall not fall aſleep,</l>
               <l>And none upon my Coffin here ſhall weep.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:29"/>
               <l>Nor ſhall my wives tears, while that they do fall</l>
               <l>Upon my face, me unto life recal.</l>
               <l>I ſhall not make my will, nor with ſad cries</l>
               <l>No friendly hand ſhall cloſe my dying eies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Without a Tomb or Funeral I ſhall be,</l>
               <l>While as the barbarous earth doth cover me.</l>
               <l>Which when thou heareſt, be not with grief oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Nor do not thou for ſorrow beat thy breaſt.</l>
               <l>Why ſhoudſt thou wring thy tender hands in vain?</l>
               <l>Or call upon thy wretched husbands name?</l>
               <l>Tear not thy cheeks, nor cut thy hair for me,</l>
               <l>For I am not (good wife) now took from thee.</l>
               <l>When I was baniſht then I dy'd, alaſs!</l>
               <l>For baniſhment then death more heavy was.</l>
               <l>Now I would have thee to rejoyce (good wife)</l>
               <l>Since all my grief is ended with my life.</l>
               <l>And bear thy ſorrows with a valiant heart:</l>
               <l>Miſ-haps have taught thee how to play thy part.</l>
               <l>And with my body may my ſoul expire,</l>
               <l>That ſo no part may ſcape the greedy fire.</l>
               <l>For if to <hi>Pythagoras</hi> we may credit give,</l>
               <l>Who ſaith the ſoul eternally doth live:</l>
               <l>My ſoul 'mongſt the <hi>Sarmatick</hi> ſhades ſhall ſtray,</l>
               <l>And to the cruel ghoſts ne'r find the way.</l>
               <l>Yet let my aſhes be put in an Urn,</l>
               <l>So being dead I ſhall again return.</l>
               <l>This lawful is, the <hi>Theban</hi> being dead,</l>
               <l>His loving ſiſter ſaw him buried.</l>
               <l>And let ſweet powders round my bones be laid,</l>
               <l>And ſo into ſome ſecret place convey'd;</l>
               <l>Graving theſe Verſes on a Marble ſtone,</l>
               <l>In Letters to be read by every one.</l>
               <l>I Ovid, <hi>that did write of wanton Love,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lye here, my Verſe my 'overthrow did prove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou that haſt been in Love, and paſſeſt by,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pray ſtill that</hi> Ovids <hi>bones may ſoftly lye.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:30"/>
               <l>This Epitaph ſhall ſuffice, ſince my books be</l>
               <l>A far more laſting Monument to me.</l>
               <l>Which though they hurt me, yet ſhall raiſe my name,</l>
               <l>And give their Authour everlaſting fame.</l>
               <l>Yet let thy love in Funoral gifts be ſhew'd,</l>
               <l>And bring ſweet Garland with thy tears be-dew'd.</l>
               <l>Thoſe aſhes which the funeral fire ſhall leave,</l>
               <l>Will in their Urn thy pious love perceive.</l>
               <l>More would I write, but that my voyce is ſpent,</l>
               <l>Nor can my dry tongue ſpeak what I invent.</l>
               <l>Then take my laſt words to thee; live in health,</l>
               <l>Which though I ſend to thee, I want my ſelf.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Ovid doth his friend adviſe,</l>
                  <l>A life of greatneſs to deſpiſe.</l>
                  <l>Since Thunder doth the hill aſſail.</l>
                  <l>While quiet peace lives in the vale.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>MY always deareſt friend, but then moſt known,</l>
               <l>When I by adverſe Fortune was o're-thrown.</l>
               <l>If thou wilt take the Counſel of a friend,</l>
               <l>Live to thy ſelf, do not too high aſcend.</l>
               <l>Since Thunder from the higheſt Tower doth come,</l>
               <l>Live to thy ſelf, and glittering titles ſhun.</l>
               <l>For though the beams of greatneſs may us warm,</l>
               <l>Yet greateſt men have greateſt power to harm.</l>
               <l>The naked ſail-yard ſears no ſtorms at all,</l>
               <l>And greater ſails more dangerous are then ſmall.</l>
               <l>The floating Cork upon the waves doth ſwim,</l>
               <l>While heavy Lead doth ſink the Net therein.</l>
               <l>Of theſe things had ſome friend admoniſht me,</l>
               <l>Perhaps I had been ſtill at <hi>Rome</hi> with thee.</l>
               <l>While as a gentle wind did drive me on,</l>
               <l>My boat through quiet ſtreams did run along.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:30"/>
               <l>He that by chance doth fall upon the plain,</l>
               <l>He falleth ſo that he may riſe again.</l>
               <l>But when <hi>Elpenor</hi> fron a high houſe fell,</l>
               <l>His ghoſt went down to <hi>Pluto</hi> King of Hell.</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Daedalus</hi> his wings did him ſuſtain,</l>
               <l>Yet falling <hi>Icarus</hi> gave the Sea his name.</l>
               <l>Becauſe that he flew high, the other low,</l>
               <l>While both of them their wings abroad did throw.</l>
               <l>The man that unto ſolitude is bent,</l>
               <l>Doth live moſt happy if he be content.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eumenes</hi> of his Son was not deprived,</l>
               <l>Until that he <hi>Achilles</hi> Horſes guided.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phaethon</hi> had not dyed in the flame,</l>
               <l>If that his Father could his will reſtrain.</l>
               <l>Then fear thou ſtill to take the higher way,</l>
               <l>And in thy courſe draw in thy ſails I pray.</l>
               <l>Thou worthy art to live moſt fortunate,</l>
               <l>And to enjoy a candid happy fate.</l>
               <l>Thy gentle love deſerves this praiſe of mine,</l>
               <l>Since thou didſt cleave to me in every time.</l>
               <l>I ſaw how that thy grief for me was ſhown,</l>
               <l>Even in thy looks moſt like unto my own.</l>
               <l>I ſaw thy tears which on my face did fall,</l>
               <l>And with my tears I drunk thy words withal.</l>
               <l>Now to thy abſent friend thou yield'ſt relief,</l>
               <l>Thereby to lighten this my heavy grief.</l>
               <l>Live thou unenvy'd, honour crown thy end,</l>
               <l>For thou art worthy of a noble friend.</l>
               <l>And love thy <hi>Ovid's</hi> name, which cannot be,</l>
               <l>Baniſht, though <hi>Scythia</hi> now containeth me.</l>
               <l>For me a land near to the Bear doth hold,</l>
               <l>Whereas the earth is frozen up with cold.</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Boſphorus</hi> and <hi>Tanais</hi> do remain,</l>
               <l>And places which have ſcarcely any name.</l>
               <l>Unhabitable cold doth dwell beyond,</l>
               <l>For I am near unto the fartheſt land.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:31"/>
               <l>My Country and my wife are abſent far,</l>
               <l>And with them two, all things that deareſt are.</l>
               <l>Yet though with them I cannot preſent be,</l>
               <l>Within my fancy I their ſhape do ſee.</l>
               <l>My houſe, the City ſtand before my eies,</l>
               <l>And all my actions in their place do riſe.</l>
               <l>My wif es dear Image doth it ſelf preſent</l>
               <l>Which doth increaſe and lighten diſcontent.</l>
               <l>Her abſence grieveth me, but then again,</l>
               <l>My comfort is ſhe conſtant doth remain.</l>
               <l>And you my friends do cleave unto my breaſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe names I wiſh by me might be expreſt.</l>
               <l>But wary fear doth my deſire reſtrain,</l>
               <l>And you I think do even wiſh the ſame,</l>
               <l>For though that heretofore you pleaſed were,</l>
               <l>When as your names did in my Verſe appear:</l>
               <l>Yet now Ile talk with you within my breſt,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall your fears by my Verſe be increaſt.</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall my Verſe diſcloſe a ſecret friend,</l>
               <l>Love ſecretly, and love me to the end:</l>
               <l>And know though we by abſence are dis joyn'd,</l>
               <l>Yet you are alwaies preſent in my mind.</l>
               <l>Then ſtrive to caſe thoſe griefs which I ſuſtain,</l>
               <l>And lend your hand to help me up again.</l>
               <l>So may your fortune proſperous remain,</l>
               <l>And never have juſt cauſe to ask the ſame.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>By a feigned name he doth commend</l>
                  <l>One <hi>Carus</hi> that had been his Friend:</l>
                  <l>And then doth mitigate his fault,</l>
                  <l>Since error him to ruine brought.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>MYuſe of friendſhip with thee was but ſmall.</l>
               <l>And if thou wilt thou may'ſt ſay none at all:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:31"/>
               <l>But that thy love moſt faithful I did find,</l>
               <l>When as my ſhip ſail'd with a gentle wind,</l>
               <l>When once I fell, then all did ſhun my wrack,</l>
               <l>And all my friends on me did turn their back.</l>
               <l>Yet thou, when I was ſtrucken with <hi>Joves</hi> flame,</l>
               <l>Didſt viſit me, and to my houſe then came:</l>
               <l>And in thy freſh acquaintance thou didſt ſhow</l>
               <l>More love, than all my ancient friends would do,</l>
               <l>I ſaw thy amazed count'nance at that time,</l>
               <l>Thy face bedew'd with tears, more pale than mine.</l>
               <l>And ſeeing tears fall at each word, my ears</l>
               <l>Did drink thy words, my mouth did drink thy tears:</l>
               <l>Thou didſt imbrace my neck, and then betwixt</l>
               <l>Some loving kiſſes with thy ſighs were mixt.</l>
               <l>Now abſent thou defendeſt me again,</l>
               <l>Thou know'ſt that <hi>Carus</hi> is a feigned name:</l>
               <l>And many tokens of thy love appear,</l>
               <l>Which I in memory will ever bare.</l>
               <l>The gods ſtill make thee able to defend</l>
               <l>Thy friends unto a far more happy end.</l>
               <l>To know how I do live if thou require,</l>
               <l>As it is likely that thou doſt deſire:</l>
               <l>I have ſome hope, which do not take from me,</l>
               <l>That thoſe offended powers will pleaſed be.</l>
               <l>Which being vain or if it may befal,</l>
               <l>Do thou allow my hope though it be ſmall.</l>
               <l>Beſtow thy eloquence upon that theam,</l>
               <l>To ſhew it may fall out as I do mean.</l>
               <l>The greateſt men are placable in wrath,</l>
               <l>A generous mind a gentle anger hath.</l>
               <l>When Beaſts unto a Lion proſtrate lye,</l>
               <l>He ends the combate with his enemy.</l>
               <l>But Wolves and Bears their yielding foes do kill,</l>
               <l>And the inferiour beaſts are cruel ſtill.</l>
               <l>Who like <hi>Achilles?</hi> yet even he appears,</l>
               <l>To be much mov'd with <hi>Dardanus</hi> ſad tears.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:32"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Emathion</hi>'s clemency is beſt declar'd,</l>
               <l>Even by thoſe funeral rites which he prepar'd.</l>
               <l>And that I may not mans calm'd anger ſhow,</l>
               <l>Even <hi>Juno's</hi> Son in law was once her foe.</l>
               <l>Laſtly, I needs muſt hope, ſince at this time,</l>
               <l>I am not puniſht for a hainous crime.</l>
               <l>I did not plot againſt great <hi>Caeſar's</hi> life,</l>
               <l>To ruine him by ſowing civil ſtrife.</l>
               <l>I never yet did rail againſt the time,</l>
               <l>Or ſpake againſt him in my cups of wine.</l>
               <l>But am puniſht for beholding of a fault,</l>
               <l>Which I through ignorance beheld, unſought.</l>
               <l>Yet all my fault, I cannot well defend,</l>
               <l>Though in part thereof I did not ill intend.</l>
               <l>So that I hope that he will pleaſed be,</l>
               <l>To grant in eaſier baniſhment to me.</l>
               <l>I wiſh the morning ſtar that brings the day,</l>
               <l>Would bring this news and quickly poſt away.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>His friends fidelity he doth praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And to excuſe himſelf aſſaies.</l>
                  <l>Deſiring if he have any grace</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Rome,</hi> to uſe it in his caſe.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>OUr league of friendſhip thou wilt not conceal:</l>
               <l>Or if thou wouldſt, it would it ſelf reveal.</l>
               <l>For while we might, none was more dear to me,</l>
               <l>And I do know I was belov'd of thee.</l>
               <l>And this our love was to the people known,</l>
               <l>So that our Love more than our ſelves was known.</l>
               <l>The candor of thy mind is eaſily ſeen,</l>
               <l>Of him who for thy friend thou doſt eſteem.</l>
               <l>Thou nothing from my knowledge didſt conceal,</l>
               <l>And I my ſecrets did to thee reveal.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:32"/>
               <l>For all my heart and ſecrets thou didſt know,</l>
               <l>Excepting that which wrought my overthrow.</l>
               <l>Which hadſt thou known, thou wouldſt have councell'd me</l>
               <l>So well, that I ſhould never baniſht be.</l>
               <l>But 'twas my fate drew on my puniſhment,</l>
               <l>And croſſed me in any good intent.</l>
               <l>Yet whether that I might this evil ſhun,</l>
               <l>Our reaſon cannot fortune overcome:</l>
               <l>Yet thou to me my old acquaintance art,</l>
               <l>And of my love thou holdſt the greateſt part.</l>
               <l>Be mindful then, and if thou gracious be</l>
               <l>At Court, then try what thou canſt do for me.</l>
               <l>That <hi>Caeſar</hi> being unto mildneſs bent,</l>
               <l>May change the place of my ſad baniſhment.</l>
               <l>Even as I did no wickedneſs deviſe,</l>
               <l>Since that my fault from errour did ariſe.</l>
               <l>It would be tedious not ſafe to unfold,</l>
               <l>By what chance theſe eyes did that act behold.</l>
               <l>Such ſhameful deeds as do the ear affright,</l>
               <l>Should be concealed in eternal night.</l>
               <l>I muſt confeſs therefore my former fault,</l>
               <l>Yet no reward by my offence I ſought.</l>
               <l>And for my fault I may my folly blame,</l>
               <l>If to my fault thou wilt give a true name.</l>
               <l>If this be falſe then further baniſh me.</l>
               <l>Theſe places like unto <hi>Romes</hi> Suburbs be.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>The Letter here he doth command,</l>
                  <l>To flye unto <hi>Perhilla</hi>'s hand</l>
                  <l>And ſheweth that the Muſes give,</l>
                  <l>Immortal ſame which ſtill ſhall live.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>GO thou my Letter being writ ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>And to ſalute <hi>Perhilla</hi> make thou haſte.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:33"/>
               <l>To ſit hard by her mother ſhe ſtill uſes,</l>
               <l>Or elſe to be amongſt her Books and Muſes:</l>
               <l>What ere ſhe does, when ſhe knows thou art come,</l>
               <l>She'l ask thee how I do that am undone;</l>
               <l>Tell her I live, but wiſh I did not ſo,</l>
               <l>Since length of time can never caſe my woe.</l>
               <l>Yet to my Muſe I now returned am,</l>
               <l>Making my words to Verſe to flow again:</l>
               <l>And ask her why ſhe doth her wind apply</l>
               <l>To common ſtudies, not ſweet Poeſy?</l>
               <l>Since Nature firſt did make thee chaſte and fair,</l>
               <l>Giving thee wit, with other things moſt rare.</l>
               <l>I firſt to thee the Muſes ſpring did ſhow,</l>
               <l>Leſt that ſweet water ſhould at waſte ſtill flow.</l>
               <l>For in thy Virgin years thy wit I ſpy'd,</l>
               <l>And was as 'twere thy father and thy guide.</l>
               <l>Then if thoſe fires ſtill in thy breaſt do dwell,</l>
               <l>There's none but <hi>Lesbia</hi> that can thee excell:</l>
               <l>But I do fear that ſince I am orethrown,</l>
               <l>That now thy breaſt is dull and heavy grown:</l>
               <l>For while we might we both did read our lines,</l>
               <l>I was thy Judge and Maſter oftentimes.</l>
               <l>And to thy Verſes I an car would lend,</l>
               <l>And make thee bluſh, when thou didſt make an end.</l>
               <l>Yet now perhaps it may be thou doſt ſhun</l>
               <l>All books, becauſe my ruine thence did come:</l>
               <l>Fear not <hi>Perhilla,</hi> but all fear remove,</l>
               <l>So that thy writings do not teach to love:</l>
               <l>Then, learned Maid, no cauſe of ſloath ſtill frame,</l>
               <l>But to thy ſacred art return again.</l>
               <l>That comely face will ſoon be ſpoild with years,</l>
               <l>While aged wrinekles in thy brow appears.</l>
               <l>Old age will lay hold on thy outward grace,</l>
               <l>Which cometh on ſtill with a ſilent pace.</l>
               <l>To have been fair it will a grief then be,</l>
               <l>And thou wilt think thy glaſs doth flatter thee.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:33"/>
               <l>Thy wealth is ſmal, though thou deſerveſt more,</l>
               <l>But yet ſuppoſe thou hadſt of wealth great ſcore:</l>
               <l>Yet fortune when ſhe liſts doth give and take,</l>
               <l>And of rich <hi>Croeſus</hi> ſhe can <hi>Irus</hi> make.</l>
               <l>All things are ſubject to mortality,</l>
               <l>Except the mind and ingenuity.</l>
               <l>For though I want my Country, Friends, and home,</l>
               <l>And all things took from me that could be gone.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill my Muſes do with me remain,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Caeſar</hi> cannot take away my vein.</l>
               <l>Who though he ſhould me of my life deprive,</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall my Fame when I am dead ſurvive.</l>
               <l>While <hi>Rome</hi> on ſeven hills doth ſtand in ſight,</l>
               <l>My works ſhall ſtill be read with much delight.</l>
               <l>Then of thy ſtudy make this happy uſe,</l>
               <l>To ſhun the power of death even by thy Muſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>His Country he deſires to ſee,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Caeſar</hi> would ſo pleaſed be.</l>
                  <l>Then mournfully he doth complain,</l>
                  <l>And ſhews what grief he doth ſuſtain.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>I Wiſh I could <hi>Triptolemus</hi> Wain aſcend,</l>
               <l>Who firſt did ſeed unto the earth commend:</l>
               <l>Or guide <hi>Medea's</hi> Dragons through the aire,</l>
               <l>With which ſhe once from <hi>Gorinth</hi> did repair:</l>
               <l>I wiſh that I had <hi>Perſeus</hi> wings to fly</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Daedalus</hi> his wings to cut the Sky.,</l>
               <l>That while the aire did yield unto my flight,</l>
               <l>I might in joy again my Countries ſight,</l>
               <l>And ſee my poor forſaken houſe again,</l>
               <l>My wife, and thoſe few friends that do remain.</l>
               <l>But why doſt thou ſo fooliſhly require,</l>
               <l>When thou can'ſt ne'r attain to thy deſire?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:34"/>
               <l>In ſtead of wiſhes unto <hi>Caſar</hi> ſend,</l>
               <l>And ſtrive to pleaſe him whom thou didſt offend.</l>
               <l>If he repeal thy baniſhment, his word,</l>
               <l>Can give thee wings to flye like to a bird.</l>
               <l>Perhaps when once his wrath doth milder grow,</l>
               <l>He to my ſure will then ſome favour ſhew:</l>
               <l>And I beſeech him now in the mean time,</l>
               <l>Some eaſier place of exile to aſſign.</l>
               <l>This air and climate both contrary be,</l>
               <l>Continual ſickneſs ſeizeth here on me.</l>
               <l>Either my ſick mind makes my body ill,</l>
               <l>Or elſe the air doth ſome diſeaſe inſtill.</l>
               <l>Since I to <hi>Pontus</hi> came, each night I dream,</l>
               <l>I do diſtaſte my meat, my limbs grow lean,</l>
               <l>Like that pale colour which in leaves is ſeen,</l>
               <l>When they by Autumns froſt have nipped been.</l>
               <l>So do I look being pin'd away with grief,</l>
               <l>Having no friend to yeild me ſome relief.</l>
               <l>For I am ſick in body and In mind,</l>
               <l>In both of which I equal pain do find.</l>
               <l>Methinks my fortune ſtands before my eyes,</l>
               <l>In a ſad ſhape repleat with miſeries.</l>
               <l>When I behold the people and the place,</l>
               <l>Comparing paſt time with my preſent caſe,</l>
               <l>Then I am willing to reſign my breath,</l>
               <l>Wiſhing I had been puniſhed with death:</l>
               <l>But yet ſince that he was more milder bent;</l>
               <l>Let him now grant me milder baniſhment.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi> briefly doth explain,</l>
                  <l>How <hi>Tomos</hi> firſt did get that name.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>ARe here ſome Cities (who can it believe)</l>
               <l>That from the <hi>Grecks</hi> did firſt their name receive?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:34"/>
               <l>While husbandmen even from <hi>Miletus</hi> came,</l>
               <l>And 'mongſt the <hi>Getes</hi> did <hi>Graecian</hi> houſes frame.</l>
               <l>Yet this ſame place doth anciently retain,</l>
               <l>Still from <hi>Abſyrtus</hi> murder, this ſame name:</l>
               <l>For in that ſhip which <hi>Pallas</hi> name did bear,</l>
               <l>And in thoſe unknown Seas her courſe did ſtear.</l>
               <l>While fierce <hi>Medea</hi> from her father fled,</l>
               <l>Unto theſe ſhores her fatal ſails ſhe ſpread:</l>
               <l>Which from a hill one veiwing on the land,</l>
               <l>Cries out, <hi>Medea</hi>'s ſails do hither ſtand.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Myniae</hi> trembled, and without delay,</l>
               <l>Unty their ropes, and all their anchors weigh:</l>
               <l>While that <hi>Medea</hi> ſtruck her guilty breaſt,</l>
               <l>With that ſame hand which had in bloud been dreſt.</l>
               <l>And though her former courage did remain,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill her bloud in paleneſs went and came,</l>
               <l>But when ſhe ſaw the ſails, we are betray'd</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe, my fathers courſe muſt be delay'd,</l>
               <l>By ſome new Art: while thus ſhe doth deviſe,</l>
               <l>By fatal chance, her brother ſhe eſpies.</l>
               <l>And having ſpide him, now quoth ſhe 'tis done,</l>
               <l>For from his death my ſafety now ſhall come.</l>
               <l>And with a ſword ſhe ran him through the ſide,</l>
               <l>Who little thought by her hand to have dy'd.</l>
               <l>Then tear's his Limbs in peeces, and on the ground,</l>
               <l>She ſcatters them that ſo they may be found</l>
               <l>In many places: and that her father may</l>
               <l>Not paſs by it, ſhe places in the way</l>
               <l>His bleeding Head, and both his pale cold hands,</l>
               <l>Which ſet upon a rock before him ſtands.</l>
               <l>And while that horrid ſight did ſtop her father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>He ſtay'd his courſe thoſe ſcattered limbs to gather,</l>
               <l>Whence <hi>Tomos</hi> got that name, becauſe that here,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Medea</hi> firſt her brothers limbs did tear.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="elegy">
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:35"/>
               <head>ELEGIE X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi> lively doth deſcribe</l>
                  <l>The Country where he doth abide:</l>
                  <l>Which in this ſhort map you may view,</l>
                  <l>Which he in baniſhment then drew.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>IF any yet do think of <hi>Naſo</hi>'s name,</l>
               <l>Which yet within the City doth remain:</l>
               <l>Know that I live within a barbarous Land,</l>
               <l>Which neer unto the Northern pole doth ſtand.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sauromates</hi> and <hi>Getes</hi> do hemm me in,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ruder names my Verſe do not beſeem.</l>
               <l>While the aire is warm, we then defended are,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Iſther,</hi> whoſe fair ſtream keeps back the war.</l>
               <l>But when that <hi>Boreas</hi> once doth fly abroad,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Countries he with heavy ſnow doth load.</l>
               <l>Nor doth the ſnow diſſolve by Sun or Rain,</l>
               <l>But the North-wind doth make it ſtill remain:</l>
               <l>New ſnow doth fall on that which fell before,</l>
               <l>While that the earth is doubly covered o're.</l>
               <l>Such is the North winds force when it doth blow,</l>
               <l>That Towers and Houſes it doth overthrow.</l>
               <l>The people wear ſhort mantles 'gainſt the cold,</l>
               <l>So that their faces you can ſcarce behold;</l>
               <l>From their Icy hair a ruffling ſound is heard,</l>
               <l>A hoary froſt doth ſhine upon their beard.</l>
               <l>The frozen wine doth keep the Veſſels ſhape,</l>
               <l>And in ſtead of draughts, they peeces of it take.</l>
               <l>Of Rivers frozen, what ſhould I here tell?</l>
               <l>Or yet of water digged from the Well:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Iſther,</hi> which with <hi>Nile</hi> may equall be,</l>
               <l>Whoſe many mouth do fall into the Sea,</l>
               <l>His blue waves hidden o're with ice doth keep,</l>
               <l>And ſo unſeen into the Sea doth creep.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:35"/>
               <l>Where ſhips did ſail, their feet they now do ſet,</l>
               <l>And on the ice the Horſes hoof doth beat.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sarmatian</hi> Oxen draw their waggons over</l>
               <l>New Bridges, which the running waters cover.</l>
               <l>'Tis ſtrange, yet lying brings me no reward,</l>
               <l>And therefore my report you may regard.</l>
               <l>We have ſeen when as the ice the Sea did cover,</l>
               <l>While that a ſhell of ice a did glaze it over:</l>
               <l>And on the frozen ſea have often gone,</l>
               <l>While with a dry foot we could walk thereon.</l>
               <l>And had <hi>Leander</hi> ſuch a ſhore deſcri'd,</l>
               <l>Then in that narrow ſea he had not dy'd.</l>
               <l>The crooked Dolphins, cannot then repair</l>
               <l>Unto the upper waves to take the air,</l>
               <l>And though that <hi>Boreas</hi> bluſtering wings were heard,</l>
               <l>Yet no waves in the frozen ſea appear'd.</l>
               <l>The ſhips were frozen up that there did ride,</l>
               <l>Nor could the Oars the ſtifned waves divide.</l>
               <l>We have ſeen the fiſh within the ice lie bound,</l>
               <l>While that in ſome of them ſome life was found.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Boreas</hi> therefore with too powerful force,</l>
               <l>Do freez the ſea or ſtop the rivers
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourſe:</l>
               <l>When <hi>Iſther</hi> by dry winds is once congeal'd,</l>
               <l>The barbarous foe no longer is conceal'd.</l>
               <l>Who skilful in their horſeman-ſhip and bow,</l>
               <l>Do waſte the Country whereſoere they go.</l>
               <l>While ſome do fly, and none defend the fields</l>
               <l>Their unkept wealth ſome little pillage yields.</l>
               <l>Their riches is their cattle and their wains,</l>
               <l>And that which their poor Cottages contains:</l>
               <l>And ſome that by the foe are captive took,</l>
               <l>Do leave their Country with a back caſt look,</l>
               <l>Some by the barbed arrows here do die,</l>
               <l>That with their poiſoned heads do ſwiftly fly.</l>
               <l>That which they cannot take, they ſpoil the ſame,</l>
               <l>And make their harmleſs Cottages to flame.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:36"/>
               <l>When they have peace they ſtand in fear of war,</l>
               <l>So that the fields by no man ploughed are.</l>
               <l>The grape is not hid in the leavy ſhade,</l>
               <l>Not are the veſſels fil'd with wine new made.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acontius</hi> could not here an Apple finde,</l>
               <l>To write unto his ſweet-heart in the rinde:</l>
               <l>Here the naked fields have neither leaf nor tree,</l>
               <l>For it's a place mark'd out for miſery.</l>
               <l>And though the world hath ſuch a large extent,</l>
               <l>This land is found out for my puniſhment.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Sweet <hi>Ovid</hi> is enforc'd to write,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt one who raild at him in ſpight:</l>
                  <l>Whom mildly here he doth reprove,</l>
                  <l>And unto pitty doth him move.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THou that my ſad misfortune doſt contemn,</l>
               <l>And cruelly doſt alwaies me condemn,</l>
               <l>Wert nurſed on the rocks by ſome wild beaſt,</l>
               <l>And I may ſay, thou haſt a flinty breaſt.</l>
               <l>O whither can thy wrath extended be?</l>
               <l>Or what is wanting to my miſery?</l>
               <l>The barbarous ſhores of <hi>Pontus</hi> me enfold,</l>
               <l>And here the Northen Bear I do behold.</l>
               <l>The peoples ſpeech I underſtand not here,</l>
               <l>And every place is ful of careful fear.</l>
               <l>For as the Hart purſu'd by Bears doth ſhake,</l>
               <l>Or as a Lamb hem'd in by wolves doth quake?</l>
               <l>So when theſe nations do me round incloſe,</l>
               <l>I am afraid being compaſs'd in with foes.</l>
               <l>Suppoſe it were no puniſhment to me,</l>
               <l>Of wife and children thus depriv'd to be:</l>
               <l>Though nothing troubled me but <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s wrath,</l>
               <l>Sufficient puniſhment his anger hath.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:36"/>
               <l>Yet there are ſome who handle my green wounds,</l>
               <l>And to ſpeak 'gainſt me have let looſe their tongues.</l>
               <l>In eaſie matters every one can ſpeak,</l>
               <l>And little ſtrength a bruiſed thing can break.</l>
               <l>It ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ws ſome ſtrength to throw down walls that ſtand,</l>
               <l>When falling Towers yield to the weakeſt hand.</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou perſecute my empty ſhade?</l>
               <l>Or why doſt thou my grave with ſtones invade?</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Hector</hi> in the wars did ſhew his force,</l>
               <l>It was not <hi>Hector</hi> that behind a horſe</l>
               <l>Was drawn about? nor am I now the ſame,</l>
               <l>And nothing but my ſhadow doth remain:</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou rail on me with words ſo foul?</l>
               <l>I pray thee do not ſeek to vex my ſoul.</l>
               <l>Suppoſe my faults were true, my chiefeſt fault,</l>
               <l>Was not by wickedneſs but errour wrought?</l>
               <l>Then glut thy anger with my puniſhment,</l>
               <l>For I am ſent to grievous baniſhment.</l>
               <l>A murtherer would lament my unhappy fate,</l>
               <l>Thou think'ſt me not enough unfortunate.</l>
               <l>More cruel than <hi>Buſiris,</hi> or that man,</l>
               <l>Who firſt to make a brazen Bull began:</l>
               <l>And on the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Tyrant it beſtow'd,</l>
               <l>While thus in words his Art to him he ſhew'd.</l>
               <l>This work O King! may far more uſeful be,</l>
               <l>Than the outward ſhape doth ſeem to promiſe thee.</l>
               <l>For look, the Bulls ſide may be open'd ſo,</l>
               <l>That whom thou meanſt to kill, thou needs but throw</l>
               <l>Into his belly, and being inclos'd therein,</l>
               <l>Put fire beneath, and then he will begin</l>
               <l>To roar, and make a groaning noiſe as though</l>
               <l>The brazen Bull it ſelf began to Lowe:</l>
               <l>Therefore to recompence my gift again,</l>
               <l>Let my reward be equal to my pain.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phalaris</hi> reply'd, ſince that thou didſt invent,</l>
               <l>This cruel torment for a puniſhment:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:37"/>
               <l>Thou firſt ſhalt feel it, and ſo being thrown</l>
               <l>Into the Bull, he there began to groan.</l>
               <l>But from <hi>Sicilia</hi> I return again,</l>
               <l>Of thee that rail'ſt on me I muſt complain:</l>
               <l>If thou deſireſt to quench thy thirſt with bloud,</l>
               <l>And that to hear my grief would do the good:</l>
               <l>I have ſuffer'd ſo much both by ſea and land,</l>
               <l>That thou wouldſt grieve the ſame to underſtand.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> was not in ſo great diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Neptunes</hi> anger, is than <hi>Joves</hi> far leſs.</l>
               <l>Then do not thou rip up my fau'ts again,</l>
               <l>And from my bleeding wound thy hands refrain,</l>
               <l>Let time my former fault in darkneſs cover,</l>
               <l>That this ſame wound may once be skinned over.</l>
               <l>Sith Fortune throws down whom ſhe doth advance,</l>
               <l>Be thon afraid of her uncertain chance.</l>
               <l>And ſince thou haſt a great deſire to pry,</l>
               <l>And wouldſt be glad to know my miſery:</l>
               <l>My fortune is of miſery moſt full,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Caeſars</hi> wrath all ill with it doth pull.</l>
               <l>And if thou think'ſt I do the ſame augment,</l>
               <l>I wiſh that thou might'ſt feel my puniſhment.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Though it be Spring-time every where,</l>
                  <l>No Spring in <hi>Tomos</hi> doth appear:</l>
                  <l>Which makes him pray here to be ſent,</l>
                  <l>Unto ſome milder baniſhment.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>NOw <hi>Zephyrus</hi> warms the air, the year is run,</l>
               <l>And the long ſeeming winter now it done:</l>
               <l>The Ram which bore fair <hi>Hellen</hi> once away,</l>
               <l>Hath made the dark night equal to the day.</l>
               <l>Now boyes and girls do the ſweet Violets get,</l>
               <l>Which in the Country often grow unſet.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:37"/>
               <l>Fair colour'd flowers in the Meadows ſpring,</l>
               <l>And now the birds their untaught notes do ſing.</l>
               <l>The Swallow now doth build her little neſt,</l>
               <l>Under ſome beam, wherein her eggs may reſt.</l>
               <l>The ſeed which long ſince in the ground was laid,</l>
               <l>Is now ſhot forth into a tender blade.</l>
               <l>And now young buds upon the Vine appear,</l>
               <l>Although the <hi>Getick</hi> ſhore no tree doth bear;</l>
               <l>'Tis there vacation, and the wars at Court</l>
               <l>Do now give place to plaies and other ſport:</l>
               <l>Now they do Tilt, and feats of arms aſſay,</l>
               <l>Now with the ball, and with the top they play,</l>
               <l>Young men annointed now with oyle, begin</l>
               <l>To bathe their limbs within the virgin ſpring:</l>
               <l>The ſcene doth flouriſh, and new ſtrains are found,</l>
               <l>Which make the three Theaters to reſound.</l>
               <l>O four times happy ſure, and more is he,</l>
               <l>That to enjoy the City now is free.</l>
               <l>But here I ſee the ſnow melt with the Sun,</l>
               <l>The undigg'd waters now begin to run.</l>
               <l>The Sea is not frozen, nor doth the ſwaine</l>
               <l>Over the <hi>Iſther</hi> drive his creaking wain.</l>
               <l>Yet when that any ſhips doth hither ſail,</l>
               <l>And Anchor at our ſhore, then without ſail</l>
               <l>I run to the Maſter, and after ſalutation</l>
               <l>I ask him whence he comes, and of what Nation.</l>
               <l>And 'tis a wonder if he be not one</l>
               <l>That from ſome neighbour country then doth come.</l>
               <l>From <hi>Italy</hi> few ſhips do ever ſtand,</l>
               <l>To come unto this haven-wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing land.</l>
               <l>Whether his language Greek or Latin be,</l>
               <l>The latter is moſt welcome unto me.</l>
               <l>If any from <hi>Propontis</hi> here arrive,</l>
               <l>While a north-wind his ſpreading ſails doth drive:</l>
               <l>He may enforme me of the common fame,</l>
               <l>And orderly he may relate the ſame.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:38"/>
               <l>For of Great <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Triumph I do hear,</l>
               <l>And of thoſe vows to <hi>Jove</hi> performed were.</l>
               <l>And how rebelling <hi>Germany</hi> in the end,</l>
               <l>Beneath our Captains feat her head did bend.</l>
               <l>He that ſhall tell me theſe things here expreſt,</l>
               <l>I will invite him home to be my gueſt.</l>
               <l>Alas! does <hi>Ovid's</hi> houſe alone now ſtand?</l>
               <l>Being ſeated here within the <hi>Styrian</hi> land:</l>
               <l>May <hi>Caeſar</hi> make this houſe of mine to be,</l>
               <l>Only an Inne of puniſhment to me.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Againſt his Birth-day he doth complain,</l>
                  <l>Which was now return'd in vain.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>BEhold my Birth-day, (for why was I borne?)</l>
               <l>Doth vainly unto me again teturne,</l>
               <l>Hard-hearted day, why doſt thou ſtill extend</l>
               <l>My years, to which thou ſhouldſt have put an end?</l>
               <l>If thou hadſt any care of me or ſhame,</l>
               <l>Thou wouldſt not thus have followed me in vain.</l>
               <l>But in that place have given me my death,</l>
               <l>Where in my childe-hood firſt I drew my breath.</l>
               <l>And with my friends that now at <hi>Rome</hi> do dwell,</l>
               <l>Thou mightſt at once have took thy laſt farewel.</l>
               <l>What's <hi>Pontus</hi> unto thee, or art thou ſent,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Caeſars</hi> wrath with me to baniſhment?</l>
               <l>Doſt thou expect thy wonted honour here?</l>
               <l>While I a white robe on my ſhoulders wear.</l>
               <l>Or that fair Garlands ſhould environ round,</l>
               <l>The ſmoaking Altar with ſweet incenſe crown'd?</l>
               <l>Offering ſuch gifts as may befit the day,</l>
               <l>While for thy proſperous return I pray.</l>
               <l>But now I do not live in ſuch a time,</l>
               <l>That when thou com'ſt I ſhould to mirth incline<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:38"/>
               <l>A funeral Altar doth become me now,</l>
               <l>That may be ſtuck round with the Cypreſs bough.</l>
               <l>Now incenſe to the Gods were caſt away,</l>
               <l>While in my depth of grief I cannot pray.</l>
               <l>Yet one requeſt upon this day I'le name</l>
               <l>That to this place thou ne're return again.</l>
               <l>Whilst in the fartheſt <hi>Pontick</hi> ſhore I live,</l>
               <l>Which falſely ſome the name of <hi>Euxine</hi> give.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Here he writes unto his Friend,</l>
                  <l>That he would his books defend.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THou chief of Learned men, what maketh thee;</l>
               <l>A friend unto my idle vein to be?</l>
               <l>When I was ſafe then thou my lines didſt praiſe,</l>
               <l>And being abſent thou my fame doſt raiſe.</l>
               <l>And all my verſes thou doſt entertain.</l>
               <l>Except the <hi>Art of Love</hi> which I did frame.</l>
               <l>Since then thou loveſt the new Poets ſtrain,</l>
               <l>Within the City ſtill keep up my Name.</l>
               <l>For I, and not my books, am baniſht thence,</l>
               <l>Which they could not deſerve by my offence.</l>
               <l>The Father oft is baniſhed we ſee,</l>
               <l>While as his Children in the City be:</l>
               <l>My verſes now are like to <hi>Pallas,</hi> borne</l>
               <l>Without a Mother; and being ſo forlorne,</l>
               <l>I ſend them unto thee, for they bereft</l>
               <l>Of Father, now unto thy charge are left.</l>
               <l>Three ſons of mine by me deſtroyed were,</l>
               <l>But of the reſt ſee that thou have a care.</l>
               <l>And fifteen books of changed ſhapes there lyes,</l>
               <l>Being raviſht from their Maſters obſequies.</l>
               <l>That work I had unto perfection brought,</l>
               <l>If that I had not my own mine wrought.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:39"/>
               <l>Which uncorrected now the people have,</l>
               <l>If any thing of mine the people crave.</l>
               <l>Let this among my other books now ſtand,</l>
               <l>Being ſent unto thee from a foraign Land.</l>
               <l>Which whoſo reads, let him but weigh again,</l>
               <l>The time and place, wherein I did it frame:</l>
               <l>He will pardon me, when he ſhall underſtand,</l>
               <l>That I was baniſht in a barbarous Land.</l>
               <l>And will admire that in my adverſe time,</l>
               <l>With a ſad hand I could draw forth a line:</l>
               <l>Miſ-fortunes have depriv'd me of my ſtrain,</l>
               <l>Although before I ne're had a rich vein.</l>
               <l>Yet whatſoe're it was, even now it lies,</l>
               <l>Dried up for want of any exerciſe.</l>
               <l>Here are no books to feed me with delight.</l>
               <l>But in ſtead of books the bows do me affright.</l>
               <l>Here's none to whom I may my lines rehearſe,</l>
               <l>That can both hear and underſtand my verſe.</l>
               <l>I have no place where I may walk alone.</l>
               <l>But with the <hi>Getes</hi> ſhut up in walls of ſtone.</l>
               <l>Somtimes I ask for ſuch a places name,</l>
               <l>But there is none can anſwer me again.</l>
               <l>And when I fain would ſpeak, I muſt confeſs,</l>
               <l>I want fit words my mind for to expreſs.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Seythian</hi> language doth my ear affright.</l>
               <l>So that the <hi>Getick</hi> tongue I ſure could write,</l>
               <l>I fear leſt you within this book ſhould ſee,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Pontick</hi> words with Latin mingled be.</l>
               <l>Yet read it, and thereto a pardon give,</l>
               <l>When thou conſidereſt in what ſtate I live.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:59618:39"/>
            <div n="1" type="elegy">
               <head>LIB. 4. ELEGIE I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>To excuſe his Books he doth begin,</l>
                  <l>And ſhews how his Muſe did comfort him.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>IF any faults are in theſe books of mine,</l>
               <l>Have them excuſed Reader by their time.</l>
               <l>I ſought no fame, but only ſome relief,</l>
               <l>That ſo my mind might not think on her grief.</l>
               <l>Even as the ditcher bound with fetters ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Will lighten heavy labour with a ſong,</l>
               <l>And he will ſing that with a bended ſide,</l>
               <l>Doth draw the ſlow boat up againſt the Tide.</l>
               <l>And he that at the Oar doth tug with pain,</l>
               <l>Doth ſing while he puts back his Oar again.</l>
               <l>The weary ſhepherd ſitting on a hill,</l>
               <l>Doth pleaſe his ſheep with piping on his quill,</l>
               <l>And every Maid within the Country bred,</l>
               <l>Will ſing while ſhe is drawing forth her thread.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achilles</hi> being ſad for <hi>Briſeis</hi> loſs,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Haemonian</hi> Harp did ſoften that ſame croſs.</l>
               <l>While <hi>Orpheus</hi> for his wife much grief did ſhew,</l>
               <l>With his ſweet tunes the woods and ſtones he drew,</l>
               <l>So did my muſe delight me as I went,</l>
               <l>And bore me company in my baniſhment.</l>
               <l>She fear'd no treachery, not the ſouldiers hand,</l>
               <l>Nor yet the wind, or ſea, or barbarous land.</l>
               <l>She knew what errour firſt my ruin brought,</l>
               <l>And that there was no wickedneſs in my thought.</l>
               <l>And ſince from her my fault did firſt proceed,</l>
               <l>She is made guilty with me of that deed.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill the fear of harm me ſo affrights,</l>
               <l>I ſcarce dare touch the Muſes holy rites.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:40"/>
               <l>But now a ſudden fury doth me move.</l>
               <l>And being hurt by verſe, yet verſe I love.</l>
               <l>Even as <hi>Uliſſes</hi> took delight to taſte,</l>
               <l>The Lote-tree, which did hurt him at the laſt.</l>
               <l>The Lover feels his loſs, yet does delight</l>
               <l>In it, and ſeeks to feed his appetite.</l>
               <l>So books delight me, which did me confound,</l>
               <l>Loving the Dart which gave me this ſame wound.</l>
               <l>Perhaps this ſtudy may a fury ſeem,</l>
               <l>And yet to many it hath uſe full been.</l>
               <l>It makes the mind that it cannot retain,</l>
               <l>Her grief in ſight, but doth forget the ſame.</l>
               <l>As ſhe ne're ſelt the wound which <hi>Bacchus</hi> gave,</l>
               <l>But wildly on the <hi>Idean</hi> hills did rave.</l>
               <l>So when a ſacred fire my breaſt doth warme,</l>
               <l>My higher fancy doth all ſorrow ſcorne,</l>
               <l>It feels no baniſhment, or <hi>Pontick</hi> ſhore,</l>
               <l>Nor thinks the Gods are angry any more.</l>
               <l>And as if I ſhould drink dull <hi>Lethes</hi> water,</l>
               <l>I have no ſenſe of any ſorrow after.</l>
               <l>Needs muſt thoſe Goddeſſes then honour'd be,</l>
               <l>Who from their <hi>Helicon</hi> did come with me.</l>
               <l>And for to follow me, they ſtill did pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Either by foot, by ſhipping, or by ſeas.</l>
               <l>And may they gracious unto me abide,</l>
               <l>Since that the Gods are all on <hi>Craeſar's</hi> ſide:</l>
               <l>While thoſe griefs which they heap on me are more,</l>
               <l>Then fiſh in ſeas, or ſands upon the ſhore.</l>
               <l>The flowers in ſpring-time thou maieſt ſooner tell,</l>
               <l>Or Autumns apples, or the ſnow that fell,</l>
               <l>Then all my griefs, being toſſed too and fro,</l>
               <l>While I unto the <hi>Euxine</hi> ſhore do go.</l>
               <l>Where come, I found no change of miſery,</l>
               <l>As if ill-fortune ſtill did follow me.</l>
               <l>My thred of life in one courſe here doth run,</l>
               <l>Of black and diſmal wooll this thread is ſpun.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:40"/>
               <l>Though I omit my dangers and my grief,</l>
               <l>I've ſeen ſuch miſeries as are paſt belief.</l>
               <l>Amongſt the barbarous <hi>Getes</hi> how can he live,</l>
               <l>To whom the people once ſuch praiſe did give?</l>
               <l>How grievous is it to be lockt within</l>
               <l>A walled Town, and yet ſcarce ſafe therein?</l>
               <l>For in my Youth all war I did deteſt,</l>
               <l>And never handled weapons but in jeſt.</l>
               <l>Now in my hands a ſword and ſhield I bear,</l>
               <l>And on my gray hairs I a Helmet wear.</l>
               <l>For when the watchman ſtanding in his place;</l>
               <l>Doth give ſome ſign, then all do arme apace.</l>
               <l>The enemy with his poyſoned ſhafts and bow,</l>
               <l>On their proud Steeds abou the walls do go:</l>
               <l>And as the Wolf doth bare a ſheep away,</l>
               <l>Into the woods, which from the fold did ſtray.</l>
               <l>So thoſe that once are ſtrayed beyond the Gate,</l>
               <l>The foe comes on them, and doth take them ſtraight.</l>
               <l>Then like a captive they his neck do chain,</l>
               <l>Or elſe with poyſon'd Arrows he is ſlain.</l>
               <l>In this place I a Dweller am become,</l>
               <l>Alaſs my time of life too ſlow doth run.</l>
               <l>Yet to my verſe I do return again,</l>
               <l>My friendly Muſe doth me in grief ſuſtain.</l>
               <l>Yet there is none to whom I may recite</l>
               <l>My verſe, or hear the Latin which I write.</l>
               <l>But to my ſelf I do both write and read,</l>
               <l>And then to Judge my ſelf I do proceed.</l>
               <l>Oft I have ſaid, why do I take this vein?</l>
               <l>Or ſhall the <hi>Getes</hi> delight in <hi>Ovids</hi> name?</l>
               <l>Oft while I write, my eyes to weeping ſer,</l>
               <l>And every letter with my tears is wet.</l>
               <l>And then my heart renews her grief again.</l>
               <l>While on my boſome ſhowers of tears do rain,</l>
               <l>When as my former ſtate comes in my thought,</l>
               <l>Thinking to what my fortune hath me brought.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:41"/>
               <l>Oft my mad hand, even angry with my veine,</l>
               <l>Hath caſt my verſes into the quick flame.</l>
               <l>Then ſince of many, theſe few do remain,</l>
               <l>Who e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re thou art, with pardon read the ſame,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Rome</hi> do thou take in good part each line,</l>
               <l>Though each verſe be no better than my time,</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>He grieves that the could not preſent be,</l>
                  <l>At the triumph of conquer'd <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </l>
               </argument>
               <l>NOw haughty <hi>Germany</hi> (as the world hath done)</l>
               <l>May kneel to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> being overcome.</l>
               <l>Now the high palaces are with garlands dight,</l>
               <l>And ſmoaking incenſe turns the day to night.</l>
               <l>Now the white ſacrifice by the Axe is ſlain,</l>
               <l>And with his purple bloud the earth doth ſtain.</l>
               <l>And both the conquering <hi>Caeſars</hi> do prepare,</l>
               <l>To give the Gods thoſe gifts which promis'd were.</l>
               <l>And all the young men born under his name,</l>
               <l>Do pray that ſtill his progeny may raign:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Livia</hi> ſince the Gods her ſon did ſave,</l>
               <l>Preſents thoſe gifts which they deſerve to have.</l>
               <l>The Matrons and thoſe free from bad deſire,</l>
               <l>Who living Virgins, keep the veſtal fire:</l>
               <l>The people and the Senate too ate glad,</l>
               <l>And Gentry, 'mongſt whom once a name I had,</l>
               <l>Theſe publick joyes tome here are unknown,</l>
               <l>And but a weak report doth hither come.</l>
               <l>But on theſe triumphs may the people look,</l>
               <l>And read what towns were by ſuch Captains took,</l>
               <l>While as the captive Kings to encreaſe the ſhow,</l>
               <l>Before the plumed horſes chained go.</l>
               <l>With countenances to their fortune chain'd,</l>
               <l>Owe terrible, now from themſelves eſtrang'd</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:41"/>
               <l>While ſome deſire their cauſe and names to know,</l>
               <l>One knowing little thus deſcribes the ſhow.</l>
               <l>He that in yonder purple robe doth ſhine.</l>
               <l>Was Captain of the war, and next to him</l>
               <l>He whoſe ſad eyes fixt on the ground appear,</l>
               <l>Bore not that look, when he his arms did bear.</l>
               <l>That cruel man whoſe eyes ſtill burning are,</l>
               <l>By counſel did incite them unto war.</l>
               <l>This fellow did falſe ambuſhments provide.</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſhaggy hair his ugly face doth hide.</l>
               <l>This fellow kill'd the Captives which he took,</l>
               <l>A though the Gods ſuch offerings did not brook.</l>
               <l>Theſe Mountains, Rivers, Caſtleſ, which you ſee,</l>
               <l>Were fill'd with bloud of men which ſlaughtered be,</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Druſus</hi> did his honour firſt obtain,</l>
               <l>Being worthy of that houſe from whence he came.</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Rhene</hi> with bloud of men was colour'd over,</l>
               <l>While no green reeds his winding banks did cover.</l>
               <l>Behold how <hi>Germany</hi> with her long hair ſpread,</l>
               <l>Sits at his feet who hath her conquered:</l>
               <l>And to the <hi>Roman</hi> axe her neck doth yield,</l>
               <l>Her hands being chain'd which once did bear a ſhield.</l>
               <l>And above theſe grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> thou art carryed,</l>
               <l>Through all the people in thy conquering chariot.</l>
               <l>Thy ſubjects by loud ſhouts their love do ſhew.</l>
               <l>While all the way with ſweeteſt flowers they ſtrew.</l>
               <l>Thy temples crowned with <hi>Phoehean</hi> Bayes,</l>
               <l>The ſouldiers ſingeth <hi>Io</hi> to thy praiſe.</l>
               <l>While thy four Chariot-horſes by the way,</l>
               <l>Heated with noiſe do often flop and ſtay.</l>
               <l>Then to the Tower and Temples favouring thee,</l>
               <l>Thou goeſt, where gifts to <hi>Jove</hi> ſhall offered be.</l>
               <l>Theſe things I can within my mind review,</l>
               <l>For it hath power an abſent place to ſhew.</l>
               <l>Through ſpacious lands it can moſt freely ſtray,</l>
               <l>And unto Heaven find the ready way.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:42"/>
               <l>By holp whereof the City I do ſee,</l>
               <l>That of this Rood I may partaker be.</l>
               <l>It ſhews the Ivory Chariots which do ſhine,</l>
               <l>So I ſhall be at home even for a time:</l>
               <l>The happy people ſhall behold this ſight,</l>
               <l>And for to ſee their Captain take delight.</l>
               <l>But I mud ſee it by imagination,</l>
               <l>My cars ſhall taſte the fruit of the relation,</l>
               <l>For being baniſht to a Foraign Land,</l>
               <l>To tell me of it here is none at hand.</l>
               <l>Yet he that this late triumph tells to me,</l>
               <l>When e're I hear him I ſhall joyful be.</l>
               <l>And on that day no ſorrow I will ſhow,</l>
               <l>For publick joy exceeds a private woe.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi> ſeemeth to ſpeak here,</l>
                  <l>To the conſtellations of the Bear.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>YOu great and leſſer Beaſts, whereof the one,</l>
               <l>Guides <hi>Graecian</hi> ſhips, the other
<hi>Sydonian:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which from your poles view all things which you pleaſe,</l>
               <l>And never ſet beneath the Weſtern Seas;</l>
               <l>And while that you encompaſs in the skie,</l>
               <l>Your circle from the earth is ſeen on high.</l>
               <l>Look on theſe walls, o're which as they report,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Remus</hi> leapt over in his merry ſport.</l>
               <l>And look with ſhining beams upon my Wife,</l>
               <l>And tell me if ſhe lead a conſtant life.</l>
               <l>Alas! why doubt I in a matter clear?</l>
               <l>Why do I waver between hope and fear?</l>
               <l>Believe as thou deſireſt, that all is well,</l>
               <l>Perſwade thy ſelf ſhe doth in faith excel.</l>
               <l>And what the fixed ſtar's cannot unfold,</l>
               <l>Tell to thy ſelf, and be thou thus reſolv'd:</l>
               <l>That as thou thinkeſt on her? ſo ſhe again</l>
               <l>Doth think on thee, and with her keeps thy name.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:42"/>
               <l>And in her mind thy Countenance doth review,</l>
               <l>And while ſhe lives that ſhe her love will ſhew.</l>
               <l>When thy griev'd mind doth on thy ſorrow light,</l>
               <l>Doth gentle ſleep forſake thy boſome quite?</l>
               <l>Doth thy cold bed renew thy cares afreſh,</l>
               <l>And make thee think on me in my diſtreſs?</l>
               <l>Does night ſeem long, while ſorrows inward burn?</l>
               <l>Do thy ſides ake while thou doſt often turn?</l>
               <l>Yet I believe that now thou doſt no leſs,</l>
               <l>And that thy ſorrow doth thy love expreſs.</l>
               <l>Thou griev'ſt no leſs, than did that <hi>Theban</hi> Wife,</l>
               <l>To ſee brave <hi>Hectors</hi> body void of life,</l>
               <l>Drawn by <hi>Theſſalian</hi> horſes; yet I cannot tell,</l>
               <l>What paſſion in thy mind I wiſh to dwell.</l>
               <l>If thou art ſad, then I am griev'd for thee,</l>
               <l>That of thy ſorrow I the cauſe ſhould be.</l>
               <l>Yet gentle wife do thou lament thy loſſes,</l>
               <l>And uſe the time to think upon thy croſſes.</l>
               <l>Weep for my fall, to weep is ſome relief,</l>
               <l>For chat doth caſe and carry out our grief.</l>
               <l>And would thou couldſt lament my death, not life,</l>
               <l>That ſo by death I might have left my Wife.</l>
               <l>Then in my Country I had died, and dead,</l>
               <l>Thy tears upon my Corps had then been ſhed.</l>
               <l>And thou hadſt clos'd my eyes up with thy hand,</l>
               <l>While looking unto Heaven they did ſtand.</l>
               <l>In an ancient Tomb my aſhes had been ſpread,</l>
               <l>And had been buried where I firſt was bred:</l>
               <l>Laſtly, I then had died without blame,</l>
               <l>But now my baniſhment is to me a ſhame.</l>
               <l>Yet wretched am I if thou bluſheſt then,</l>
               <l>When thou art call'd wife to a baniſht man.</l>
               <l>Wretched am I if thou that name decline,</l>
               <l>Wretched am I, if thou ſham'ſt to be mine.</l>
               <l>Where is that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e wherein thou took'ſt a pride,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Ovids</hi> Name, and to be <hi>Ovids</hi> bride?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:43"/>
               <l>Where is that time wherein theſe words you ſpake,</l>
               <l>That you in being mine did pleaſure take:</l>
               <l>Like a good wife in me you did delight,</l>
               <l>And love encreas'd my value in your ſight.</l>
               <l>And unto you ſo precious was I then,</l>
               <l>That you preferred me before all men.</l>
               <l>Then think it no diſgrace that thou art nam'd</l>
               <l>My wife, for which thou maiſt be griev'd, not ſham'd,</l>
               <l>When raſh <hi>Capaneus</hi> the wart did fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Evadne</hi> bluſht not at his fault at all,</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Jupiter</hi> did fire with fire ſuppreſs,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Phaeton</hi> was beloved ne're the leſs.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Semele</hi> did not loſe old <hi>Cadmus</hi> love,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe periſh'd by her ſure to <hi>Jove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then ſince that I am ſtrucken with <hi>Joves</hi> flame,</l>
               <l>Let not a crimſon bluſh thy fair check ſtain.</l>
               <l>But with freſh courage rather mc defend,</l>
               <l>That for a good wife I may thee commend.</l>
               <l>Shew now thy vertue in adverſity,</l>
               <l>The way to glory through hard waies doth lie.</l>
               <l>Who would talk of <hi>Hector</hi> had <hi>Troy</hi> happy been?</l>
               <l>For vertue in adverſity is ſeen.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Typhis</hi> Are fails when no waves are ſeen,</l>
               <l>In health <hi>Apollo</hi>'s are hath no eſteem.</l>
               <l>That vertus which before time lay conceal'd,</l>
               <l>In trouble doth appear, and is reveal'd.</l>
               <l>My fortune gives thee ſcope to raiſe thy fame,</l>
               <l>And by thy vertue to advance thy name.</l>
               <l>Then uſe the time, for theſe unhappy daies.</l>
               <l>Do open a fair way for to get praiſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>We writes to his friend in his diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe name by ſigns he doth expreſs.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>O Friend, though thou a Gentleman art born,</l>
               <l>Yet thou by vertue doſt thy birth adorn.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:43"/>
               <l>Thy Fathers courteſie ſhineth in thy mind,</l>
               <l>And yet this courteſie is with courage joyn'd.</l>
               <l>In thee thy Fathers Eloquence doth dwell,</l>
               <l>Whom none could in the <hi>Roman</hi> Court excel.</l>
               <l>Then ſince by ſignes I am enforc'd to name thee,</l>
               <l>I hope for praiſing you, you will hot blame me:</l>
               <l>'Tis not my fault, your gifts do it proclaim,</l>
               <l>Be what you ſeem, and I deſerve no blame.</l>
               <l>Beſides, my love in verſe expreſt, I truſt,</l>
               <l>Shall not harme thee, ſince <hi>Caeſar</hi> is moſt juſt:</l>
               <l>Our Countries Father, and ſo mild, that he</l>
               <l>Suffers his name within my verſe to be.</l>
               <l>Nor can he now forbid it if he would,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> it publick, and a common good.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſometimes lets the Poets praiſe</l>
               <l>His acts, that ſo their wits his deeds may raiſe.</l>
               <l>Thy caſe by two examples good doth ſeem,</l>
               <l>The one believ'd a God, the other ſeen.</l>
               <l>Or elſe I'le take the fault, and to it ſtand,</l>
               <l>To ſay my Letter was not in thy hand.</l>
               <l>Nor thus by writing have I newly err'd,</l>
               <l>With whom by words I often have conferr'd.</l>
               <l>Then friend, leſt thou be blam'd, thou need'ſt not fear;</l>
               <l>For it is I that muſt the envy bear.</l>
               <l>For if you'l not diſſemble a known truth,</l>
               <l>I lov'd your Father even from my youth.</l>
               <l>And you know how he did approve my wit,</l>
               <l>More than in my own judgement I thought fit,</l>
               <l>And oftentimes he would ſpeak of my verſe,</l>
               <l>And grace them while he did the ſame rehearſe.</l>
               <l>Nor do I give theſe fair words unto thee</l>
               <l>But to thy Father, who firſt loved me.</l>
               <l>Nor do I flatter, ſince my lives acts paſt,</l>
               <l>I can defend, except it be the laſt,</l>
               <l>And yet my fault no wicked crime can be,</l>
               <l>If that my griefs be not unknown to thee,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:44"/>
               <l>It was an errour brought me to this ſtate,</l>
               <l>Then ſuffer me now to forget my fare.</l>
               <l>Break not my wounds which yet ſcarce doſed are,</l>
               <l>Since reſt it ſelf can hardly help my care.</l>
               <l>And though to ſuffer juſtly lam thought,</l>
               <l>There was no wicked purpoſe in my fault:</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Caeſar</hi> knowing, ſuffer'd me to live,</l>
               <l>Nor to another my goods did be give.</l>
               <l>And this ſame baniſhment perhaps ſhall ceaſe,</l>
               <l>When length of time his anger ſhall appeaſe.</l>
               <l>And now I pray he would me hence remove,</l>
               <l>(If this requeſt would not immodeſt prove.)</l>
               <l>To ſome more quiet baniſhment, where I</l>
               <l>Might live far from the cruel enemy.</l>
               <l>Ana ſuch is <hi>Caeſars</hi> clemency that he,</l>
               <l>Would grant it, if ſome askt this boon for me.</l>
               <l>The ſhores of th' <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea do me contain,</l>
               <l>Which heretofore the <hi>Axine</hi> they did name.</l>
               <l>The ſeas are toſſed with a bluſtring wind.</l>
               <l>Nor can ſtrange ſhips any ſafe harbour find,</l>
               <l>And round about bloud-eating men do live,</l>
               <l>Thus ſea and land do equal terrour give.</l>
               <l>Not far off, ſtands that curſed Altar, where</l>
               <l>All ſtrangers to <hi>Diana</hi> offered were.</l>
               <l>Theſe bloudy kingdoms once King <hi>Thoas</hi> had,</l>
               <l>Not envi'd nor deſir'd, they were ſo bad.</l>
               <l>Here the fair <hi>Epigenia</hi> did deviſe,</l>
               <l>To pleaſe her Goddeſs with this ſacrifice.</l>
               <l>Whither as ſoon as mad <hi>Oreſtes</hi> came,</l>
               <l>Tormented with his own diſtracted brain,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phoceus</hi> with him, his companion,</l>
               <l>Who two in body, were in mind but one.</l>
               <l>To this ſad Altar they were bound, which ſtood</l>
               <l>Before a pair of gates imbru'd with bloud.</l>
               <l>Yet in themſelves no fear of death they had,</l>
               <l>But one friend for the others death was ſad.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:44"/>
               <l>The Prieſt with Faulthion drawn ſtood ready there,</l>
               <l>With a courſe fillet bound about his hair.</l>
               <l>But when ſhe knew her Brothers voice, ſhe came</l>
               <l>And did embrace him that ſhould have been ſlain.</l>
               <l>And being glad ſhe left the place, and then</l>
               <l>She chang'd the rites, which <hi>Dian</hi> did contemn.</l>
               <l>Unto this fartheſt region I am come,</l>
               <l>Which even Gods and men do likewiſe ſhun.</l>
               <l>Theſe barbarous rites near my country are maintain'd,</l>
               <l>If a barbarous country may be <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Land?</l>
               <l>May thoſe winds bear me back, which took <hi>Oreſtes</hi> hence,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Caeſar</hi> is appeas'd for my offence.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>His grief to his friend he doth reveal,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe name he on purpoſe doth conceal.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>O Chiefeſt friend 'mongſt thoſe were lov'd of me,</l>
               <l>The only ſanctuary to my miſery,</l>
               <l>By whoſe ſweet ſpeech my ſoul reviv'd again.</l>
               <l>As oyle pour'd in, revives the watching flame.</l>
               <l>Who didſt not fear a faithful port to open,</l>
               <l>And refuge to my ſhip with Thunder broken.</l>
               <l>With whoſe revenues I ſupply'd ſhould be,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Caeſar</hi> had took my own goods from me.</l>
               <l>While violence of the time doth carry me,</l>
               <l>Thy name's almoſt ſlipt out of memory?</l>
               <l>Yet thou doſt know'r, and touched with the flame,</l>
               <l>Of praiſe doſt wiſh thou mightſt thy ſelf proclaim.</l>
               <l>If thou wouldſt ſuffer it, I thy name would give,</l>
               <l>And make them that they ſhould thy fame believe.</l>
               <l>I fear my grateful verſe ſhould hurtful be,</l>
               <l>Or unſeaſonable honour ſhould but hinder thee,</l>
               <l>Since this is ſafe, rejoyce within thy mind,</l>
               <l>That I remember thee that thou wert kind.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:45"/>
               <l>And as thou doſt, to help with Oares ſtrive,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Caeſar</hi> pleas'd, ſome gentler wind arrive.</l>
               <l>And ſtill bear up my head which none can ſave,</l>
               <l>But he that plung'd me in the <hi>Stygian</hi> wave,</l>
               <l>And which is rare, be conſtant to the end,</l>
               <l>In every office of a ſteafaſt friend.</l>
               <l>So may thy fortune happily proceed,</l>
               <l>That thou no help, but others thine may need.</l>
               <l>May ſo thy Wife in goodneſs equal thee,</l>
               <l>And in thy bed may diſcord ſeldome be.</l>
               <l>May thy kindreds love be unto thee no other,</l>
               <l>Than that was ſhew'd to <hi>Caſtor</hi> by his Brother.</l>
               <l>May ſo thy ſon be like thee, and in's prime,</l>
               <l>By his carriage may they know him to be thine.</l>
               <l>May thy Daughter make thee a Father-law to be,</l>
               <l>And give the Name of Grand-father to thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Though time all things doth aſſwage,</l>
                  <l>Yet his ſorrow more doth rage.</l>
                  <l>So that being tyr'd at length,</l>
                  <l>To bear his grief he had no ſtrength.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>IN time the Oxe endures the labouring plough,</l>
               <l>And to the crocked yok: his neck doth bow:</l>
               <l>In time the Horſe do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h to the reins ſubmit,</l>
               <l>And gently takes into his mouth the bit.</l>
               <l>In time the <hi>Affrick</hi> Lyons older grow,</l>
               <l>Nor do they ſtill their former fierceneſs ſhow.</l>
               <l>Time makes the grape to ſwell until the skin</l>
               <l>Can ſcarce contain the wine that is within.</l>
               <l>Time brings the ſeed unto an ear at laſt,</l>
               <l>And maketh Apples to be ſweet in taſte.</l>
               <l>Time weares the plough-ſhare that doth cut the clay,</l>
               <l>The Adamant and Flint it wears away.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:45"/>
               <l>This by degrees fierce anger doth appeaſe,</l>
               <l>It leſſens ſorrow, and ſad hearts doth eaſe.</l>
               <l>Thus length of time can every thing impair,</l>
               <l>Except it be the burthen of my care.</l>
               <l>Since I was baniſht corn hath twice been threſht,</l>
               <l>The Grapes have twice with naked feet been preſt.</l>
               <l>Yet in this time no patience can I gain,</l>
               <l>My mind moſt freſhly doth her grief retain.</l>
               <l>Even as old Oxen often ſhun the yoak,</l>
               <l>And the horſe will not be bridled that was broke.</l>
               <l>My preſent grief is worſe than that before,</l>
               <l>Which by delay encreaſes more and more.</l>
               <l>Preſent griefs better known thin paſt griefs are,</l>
               <l>And being better known they bring more care.</l>
               <l>Beſides, 'tis ſomething, when we bring freſh ſtrength,</l>
               <l>And are not tyr'd before with griefs ſad length,</l>
               <l>The new wraſtler on the yellow ſand is ſtronger,</l>
               <l>Thin he whoſe arms are tyr'd with ſtriving longer:</l>
               <l>The unwounded Fencer, better is than he,</l>
               <l>Within whoſe bloud the weapons dyed be.</l>
               <l>A new built ſhip reſiſts the winds fell power,</l>
               <l>When an old one's broken with the ſmalleſt ſhower.</l>
               <l>And we more patiently before did bear,</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſorrows which by time encreaſed are:</l>
               <l>Believe it, I grow faint, and I am ſure,</l>
               <l>My body will not long theſe griefs endure.</l>
               <l>My ſtrength nor colour doth not now abide,</l>
               <l>And my lean skin my bones can ſcarcely hide.</l>
               <l>My body and my mind too is not well,</l>
               <l>Which on the thought of grief doth alway dwell:</l>
               <l>The City and my friends both abſent are,</l>
               <l>And Wife, than whom there's none to me ſo dear:</l>
               <l>But the <hi>Scythians</hi> and a rout of <hi>Getes</hi> here be,</l>
               <l>But abſent things and preſent trouble me:</l>
               <l>One hope there is which yields me ſome relief,</l>
               <l>That death will give an end vnto my grief.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="elegy">
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:46"/>
               <head>ELEGIE VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>He doth here excuſe his friend,</l>
                  <l>That no letters to him did ſend.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>AFter cold winter twice the Sun hath come,</l>
               <l>And through the Fiſhes twice his journey run:</l>
               <l>Why was not thy right hand ready for to ſhew</l>
               <l>Thy love by writing verſes, though a few?</l>
               <l>When open any letters ſeal,</l>
               <l>Why did I hope it would thy Name reveal?</l>
               <l>I hope many a Letter hath been writ by thee,</l>
               <l>Though none of them were yet deliver'd me,</l>
               <l>I ſooner will believe <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s head,</l>
               <l>With ſnaky heirs was round encompaſſed.</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Scylla,</hi> or <hi>Chymera's</hi> monſtrous frame,</l>
               <l>Lyon and Serpent parted with a flame.</l>
               <l>Or that the <hi>Minotaure</hi> hath ever been,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Cerberus</hi> with his tripple Dogs face ſeen.</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Sphynx,</hi> or <hi>Harpies,</hi> Gyants that had feer,</l>
               <l>Like Serpents, <hi>Gyges,</hi> or the <hi>Centaures</hi> fleer.</l>
               <l>I will believe theſe things may ſooner be,</l>
               <l>Than that thou art chang'd and haſt forgotten me.</l>
               <l>For many Mountains now 'twixt thee and I,</l>
               <l>And many Rivers, Fields, and Seas, do lye.</l>
               <l>And many things thy Letters may prevent,</l>
               <l>From coming to us, which from thee were ſent.</l>
               <l>Overcome theſe lets by writing oft to us,</l>
               <l>That I may not alwaies excuſe thee thus.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi> grieves that he is ſent,</l>
                  <l>In his old age to baniſhment.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>MY temples like the ſwans ſoft feathers are,</l>
               <l>And white old age doth cover my black hair.</l>
               <l>Now idle age and weak years coming be,</l>
               <l>And now to bear my ſelf doth trouble me.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:46"/>
               <l>Now all my former labours I ſhould end,</l>
               <l>And without fear my life in quiet ſpend:</l>
               <l>And now my mind ſhould take her reſt at leiſure,</l>
               <l>And in my ſtudy I ſhould live at pleaſure.</l>
               <l>To my houſe and Gods, ſome honour I ſhould grant,</l>
               <l>And my Fathers Lands, which now their Maſter want.</l>
               <l>That in my Nephews or wives boſome I,</l>
               <l>Within my Country might grow old and die.</l>
               <l>Thus formerly I hop'd my age ſhould end:</l>
               <l>And thus I had deſerv'd theſe years to ſpend,</l>
               <l>The Gods were not pleas'd, ſince I being toſt,</l>
               <l>By tempeſts, am in <hi>Sarmatia</hi> ſet at laſt.</l>
               <l>The bruiſed ſhips are drawn into the Dock,</l>
               <l>Leaſt in the Middle ſtream they ſhould be broke.</l>
               <l>Leaſt the horſe ſhould ſhame his gotten vict'ry paſt,</l>
               <l>In the meadow he is put to graze at laſt:</l>
               <l>The Souldier that's unfit his arms to bear,</l>
               <l>Hangs up his Armour which he once did wear.</l>
               <l>So ſince with age my ſtrength is now decreaſed,</l>
               <l>It is time I ſhould from labour be releaſed.</l>
               <l>It is no time in forain lands to ſtay,</l>
               <l>Nor at a <hi>Getick</hi> ſpring my thirſt to allay.</l>
               <l>But in my Garden now to take delight,</l>
               <l>And then again to enjoy the Cities ſight.</l>
               <l>And thus my mind not knowing future ill,</l>
               <l>I wiſht I might in age live quiet ſtill,</l>
               <l>The fates withſtood, and give me a happy time</l>
               <l>At firſt, but loaded theſe laſt days of mine:</l>
               <l>And fifty years being ended without ſtain,</l>
               <l>In the worſt of my life I bear the blame.</l>
               <l>Being neare unto the marke at which I aim'd,</l>
               <l>The remainder of my life ſad ruin gain'd.</l>
               <l>The Chariot of my life was overthrown,</l>
               <l>When it unto the goale was almoſt come.</l>
               <l>And 'gainſt me have enforc'd him to be wrath,</l>
               <l>Than whom the world not one more element hath.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:47"/>
               <l>Though my offence ore-came his clemency,</l>
               <l>To grant me life he never did deny.</l>
               <l>But near the North-pole I my life muſt lead,</l>
               <l>In the land which by the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea doth ſpread.</l>
               <l>Had the <hi>Delphian</hi> Oracle told theſe things to me,</l>
               <l>That place had ſeem'd then moſt vain to be.</l>
               <l>There's nothing though the <hi>Adamant</hi> it contain,</l>
               <l>That can be ſtronger than <hi>Joves</hi> ſudden flame.</l>
               <l>There's nothing is ſo high or plac'd above</l>
               <l>Danger, but that it is ſet under <hi>Jove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though part of my grief did come by my own fault,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Caeſars</hi> wrath my utter ruin wrought.</l>
               <l>But be you now admoniſh'd by my fate,</l>
               <l>To pleaſe that man who equals gods in ſtate.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Here he doth admoniſh one,</l>
                  <l>That he proceed not to do him Wrong.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>SInce thou art content I will conceal thy name,</l>
               <l>And drench thy deeds in <hi>Lethean</hi> waves again.</l>
               <l>And thy late tears our mercy ſhall o're-come,</l>
               <l>So thou repent of that which thou haſt done.</l>
               <l>But if hatred of us ſtill thy boſome warmes,</l>
               <l>My unhappy grief muſt take up forced arms.</l>
               <l>Though I am baniſht to the fartheſt lands,</l>
               <l>My anger may from thence reach out her hands,</l>
               <l>All right of laws great <hi>Caeſar</hi> did me grant,</l>
               <l>My puniſhment is, my Country for to want.</l>
               <l>And if he live, we may hope our return,</l>
               <l>The Oake looks green which lightning once did burn.</l>
               <l>If I had no power to revenge, at length,</l>
               <l>The Muſes then would lend me help and ſtrength:</l>
               <l>Though in the <hi>Scythian</hi> coaſts I here do lie,</l>
               <l>Whereas the ſtarry ſignes are ever dry:</l>
               <l>Yet through large ſpacious lands my praiſe ſhall go,</l>
               <l>And all the world my ſad complaint ſhall know.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:47"/>
               <l>What we ſpeak in the Weſt, unto the Eaſt ſhall fly,</l>
               <l>And the Eaſt ſhall hear my Weſtern harmony.</l>
               <l>Beyond both lands and Seas they ſhall hear me,</l>
               <l>In a loud voice ſhall my lamenting be.</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall the preſent age thee only blame,</l>
               <l>But of poſterity thou ſhalt be the ſhame.</l>
               <l>I am now diſpoſ'd to fight, though I have not blown</l>
               <l>The trumpet, and I with no cauſe were known.</l>
               <l>Though the Circk ceaſe, the Bull doth caſt aloof</l>
               <l>The ſand, and beats the earth with his hard hoof:</l>
               <l>And now my Muſe ſound the retreat again,</l>
               <l>While that he may diſſemble his own name.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>In this ſweet Elegie at laſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi> ſhews his life that's paſt.</l>
                  <l>Deſcribes his birth, and doth rehearſe,</l>
                  <l>How he took delight in verſe.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>POſterity receive me with delight,</l>
               <l>For it is I that once of Love did write.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sulmo</hi> my country is where cold ſprings riſe,</l>
               <l>And fifteen miles it from the City lies,</l>
               <l>Here was I born, and as you know right well,</l>
               <l>When both the Conſuls by like fortune fell.</l>
               <l>Beſides, I was heir to my Grand-father by right,</l>
               <l>Not made a gentle man by fortunes might.</l>
               <l>After my Brother I was born at laſt,</l>
               <l>When twelve months from his birth were fully paſt.</l>
               <l>And both of us were born upon one day,</l>
               <l>On which two wafer cakes we us'd to pay.</l>
               <l>Of thoſe five feaſts to <hi>Pallas</hi> memory,</l>
               <l>This is the firſt which bloudy us'd to be.</l>
               <l>Forth-with we being young, by our Fathers care,</l>
               <l>Did go to men in Art that famous were.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:48"/>
               <l>My Brother in ſweet eloquence did delight,</l>
               <l>Being born in wrangling wars of Court to fight.</l>
               <l>But I diviner poeſy did favour,</l>
               <l>And my Muſe did entice me to her labour.</l>
               <l>My Father ſaid, why art thou thus enclin'd?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Homer</hi> himſelf did leave no wealth-behind.</l>
               <l>Mov'd with his words, I left the Muſes well,</l>
               <l>And unto writing proſe I ſtraight-way fell.</l>
               <l>But then my lines would into numbers run,</l>
               <l>And what I writ would ſtraight a verſe become.</l>
               <l>In the mean time, years in ſilence going on,</l>
               <l>I and my brother took the freer gown,</l>
               <l>The purple robes our ſhoulders now did cloathe,</l>
               <l>And in our firſt ſtudies we delighted both.</l>
               <l>At twenty years my brother di'd, and then</l>
               <l>To want part of my ſelf I firſt began.</l>
               <l>The honours due to youth we both did take,</l>
               <l>And of the three men I a part did make,</l>
               <l>Being forc'd into the Senate at the length.</l>
               <l>That burden it was greater than my ſtrength,</l>
               <l>My mind nor body could no pains abide,</l>
               <l>And I did always ſhun ambitious pride.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Aonian</hi> ſiſters bid me ſeek ſafe leiſure,</l>
               <l>Wherein indeed I always took great pleaſure.</l>
               <l>I lov'd and cheriſh'd Poets of that time,</l>
               <l>For I did think the Poets were divine.</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Macer</hi> read to me in verſe, of Birds,</l>
               <l>What hearbs are hurtful, and what hels affords.</l>
               <l>Often <hi>Propertius</hi> did his love recite,</l>
               <l>Joyn'd unto me even by acquaintance right.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ponticus</hi> in Heroicks, <hi>Ballus</hi> in Iambicks rare,</l>
               <l>Theſe to my ſweet companions always were.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Horaces</hi> numbers did my ear delight,</l>
               <l>While he ſmooth verſe unto the Harp doth ſtrike.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virgil</hi> I only ſaw, and covetous fates</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tibullus</hi> from my friendſhip hence tranſlates.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:48"/>
               <l>He was <hi>Gallus</hi> ſucceſſour, <hi>Propertius</hi> followed him,</l>
               <l>In courſe of time I was the fourth came in.</l>
               <l>As I my elders, my youngers me renown,</l>
               <l>And my <hi>Thalia</hi> ſoon abroad was known</l>
               <l>Twice was my beard cut, when I did rehearſe</l>
               <l>Unto the people firſt my youthful verſe.</l>
               <l>One call'd <hi>Corinna</hi> by a feigned name,</l>
               <l>In praiſing her did exerciſe my vein.</l>
               <l>Much did I write, but what I faulty deem'd,</l>
               <l>I gave them to the fire for to amend.</l>
               <l>And when I fled, I burnt ſome things I lov'd,</l>
               <l>For with my verſe and ſtudy I was mov'd.</l>
               <l>A light occaſion would move my ſoft heart,</l>
               <l>Which ſoon would be o'recome by <hi>Cupid</hi>'s Dart.</l>
               <l>Yet with loves fire being quickly ſet on flame,</l>
               <l>There was no ſcandal went under my name.</l>
               <l>To me a boy, an unthtifty wife they aſſign,</l>
               <l>Who was married to me but a little time.</l>
               <l>My next wife though ſhe were without all blame,</l>
               <l>Yet in my bed ſhe did not long remain.</l>
               <l>My laſt abides theſe latter years, and can</l>
               <l>Endure to be wife to a baniſh'd man.</l>
               <l>My ſecond Daughter did two husbands take,</l>
               <l>And twice a grand-father of me did make.</l>
               <l>My Father now his life even finiſht had,</l>
               <l>While nine times four years he to mine did add.</l>
               <l>I wept for him, as he would have done for me,</l>
               <l>And then my Mother dyed preſently.</l>
               <l>Happy and timely to the grave they went,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they di'd before my baniſhment.</l>
               <l>And I am happy, ſince while they did live</l>
               <l>They had no cauſe at all for me to grieve.</l>
               <l>If ought remain unto the dead but names,</l>
               <l>And the thin Ghoſt do ſcape the Funeral flames;</l>
               <l>If you my Parents hear ſome ſad report,</l>
               <l>And that my faults are in the Stygian Court,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:49"/>
               <l>Know then (whom to deceive is not my intent)</l>
               <l>Errour, nor wickedneſs caus'd my baniſhment.</l>
               <l>Thus much to the dead, to you I now return,</l>
               <l>That the actions of my life would fain diſcern,</l>
               <l>Now whiteneſs, when my beſt years ſpended were,</l>
               <l>Came on and mingl'd with my ancient haire.</l>
               <l>The ho ſe-man with <hi>Piſaean</hi> Olive crown'd,</l>
               <l>Hath ſince my birth got ten prizes renown'd.</l>
               <l>When as the Emperors wrath doth me command</l>
               <l>To <hi>Tomos</hi> which by <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea doth ſtand.</l>
               <l>I need not ſhew the cauſe of my ſad fall,</l>
               <l>Which is already too well known to all.</l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſhew the treacherous intent,</l>
               <l>Of friends and ſervants, bad as baniſhment.</l>
               <l>Yet my mind ſcorn'd to yield to grief at length,</l>
               <l>And ſhew'd her ſelf invincible in ſtrength.</l>
               <l>And forgetting of my quiet life, I than</l>
               <l>To take arms in my unwonted hand began.</l>
               <l>In more perils I By ſea and land have been,</l>
               <l>Than ſtars between the ſhining Poles are ſeen.</l>
               <l>At laſt I arrived at the <hi>Getick</hi> coaſt,</l>
               <l>Joyn'd to <hi>Sarmatia,</hi> being with errors toſt.</l>
               <l>Though noiſe of wars do round about me rage,</l>
               <l>Yet by my verſe I did my grief aſſwage.</l>
               <l>Though there be none that can my words receive,</l>
               <l>Yet thus I do the day alone deceive,</l>
               <l>In that I live and labour ſtill between,</l>
               <l>And that the time doth not to me long ſeem.</l>
               <l>Thanks Muſe to thee, for thou doſt yield relief,</l>
               <l>Thou art the eaſe and medicine of my grief.</l>
               <l>Thou art my guide, from <hi>Iſter</hi> me doſt bring,</l>
               <l>And placeſt me in the <hi>Heliconian</hi> ſpring.</l>
               <l>And haſt given me in my life time a great name,</l>
               <l>Which after death is given ſtill by fame.</l>
               <l>Envie which doth at preſent things repine,</l>
               <l>Hath never bitten any work of mine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:49"/>
               <l>Though many Poets in this age forth came,</l>
               <l>Yet fame was never envious to my name.</l>
               <l>I prefer'd many who of me ſtill ſed</l>
               <l>No leſs, and through the world I ſhall be read.</l>
               <l>If Poets any truth do Propheſie,</l>
               <l>I ſhall not all be earth when I do die.</l>
               <l>If favour or my verſe gave me this fame,</l>
               <l>Kind Reader I do thank the for the ſame.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="book">
            <div n="1" type="elegy">
               <head>LIB. 5. ELEGIE I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>He writeth here unto his friend,</l>
                  <l>To whom he doth this book commend.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THis Book which cometh from the <hi>Getick</hi> ſhore,</l>
               <l>Add thou (my friend) unto the other four.</l>
               <l>For this is like unto the Poets times,</l>
               <l>And thou ſhalt find no ſweetneſs in my lines.</l>
               <l>My verſe and fortune full of ſorrow be,</l>
               <l>My matter with my writing doth agree:</l>
               <l>Being happy, in a pleaſant veine I writ,</l>
               <l>But now alaſs I do repent of it.</l>
               <l>But when I fell, my ſad chance I proclaim.</l>
               <l>And I my ſelf the Argument do frame,</l>
               <l>Even as the Swan that on the banck doth lie.</l>
               <l>Bewails her ſelf when ſhe is near to dye.</l>
               <l>So I being caſt on the <hi>Sarmatick</hi> ſhoare,</l>
               <l>My own ſad funeral do here deplore.</l>
               <l>If any do in wanton verſe delight,</l>
               <l>I adviſe him not to read what I do write,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gallus</hi> and ſweet <hi>Propertius</hi> fitter be,</l>
               <l>Whoſe names do flouriſh ſtill in memory.</l>
               <l>And in their number would I might not fall,</l>
               <l>Alas why hath my Muſe even ſpoke at all?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:50"/>
               <l>But now to <hi>Scythia</hi> for a puniſhment,</l>
               <l>He that did write of quivered love is ſent.</l>
               <l>Yet I have bent my friends unto my vein,</l>
               <l>And bid them to be mindful of my Name.</l>
               <l>If ſome would know why I ſo much do ſing</l>
               <l>Of grief, aſcribe it to my ſuffering.</l>
               <l>We do not now compoſe with will and Art,</l>
               <l>Sorrow doth to the matter wit impart.</l>
               <l>How ſmall a part of grief is in my verſe!</l>
               <l>He's happy that his ſufferings can rehearſe.</l>
               <l>As ſhrubs in wood, or ſands which <hi>Tyber</hi> gild,</l>
               <l>Or the ſoft blades of graſs in <hi>Marſes</hi> field,</l>
               <l>So many miſeries do we now endure,</l>
               <l>Of which my Muſes are the only cure.</l>
               <l>If thou ask when <hi>Ovid</hi> ends his weeping lines?</l>
               <l>I anſwer, when I find more happy times.</l>
               <l>She this complaint from a full ſpring affords,</l>
               <l>They are not mine, but my miſ-fortunes words.</l>
               <l>If to me ray Wife and Country thou reſtore,</l>
               <l>I ſhall be merry as I was before.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s wrath to me becomd more milde,</l>
               <l>I'l give thee verſes that with mirth are fill'd.</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall my writing not ſo juſt again.</l>
               <l>Though once it ran out in a wanton veine.</l>
               <l>I'le ſing what ſhall by <hi>Caeſar</hi> be approv'd,</l>
               <l>If that I might be from the <hi>Getes</hi> remov'd.</l>
               <l>Till then ſad matter in my books ſhall be,</l>
               <l>This pipe doth unto funerals agree.</l>
               <l>But thou mayſt ſay, 'twero better for to cover</l>
               <l>Thy griefs, and ſtrive in ſilence them to ſmother.</l>
               <l>Thou wouldſt have torments, yet no groans reſound,</l>
               <l>Thou bidſt him not to weep that bath a wound.</l>
               <l>In that Bull which <hi>Perillus</hi> once did frame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phaleris</hi> ſuffer'd them to roar and complain.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Priam</hi>'s tears, <hi>Achilles</hi> did not blame,</l>
               <l>But thou more cruel wouldſt my tears reſtrain.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:50"/>
               <l>When <hi>Dian Niobe</hi> did childleſs leave,</l>
               <l>She did not bid her that ſhe ſhould not grieve.</l>
               <l>'Tis ſomething by words to eaſe ſorrows vein,</l>
               <l>Which maketh <hi>Progne</hi> always to complain,</l>
               <l>This made <hi>Paeantius</hi> in a cold Cave lye,</l>
               <l>Wearying the <hi>Lemnian</hi> rocks even with his cry.</l>
               <l>Sorrow conceal'd doth choak and inward ſwell,</l>
               <l>Reſtraint to gather ſtrength doth it compel.</l>
               <l>Then pardon me, or leave my works even quite,</l>
               <l>If they harm thee which do me much delight.</l>
               <l>But yet they can be hurtful unto none,</l>
               <l>Which only have their Author overthrown</l>
               <l>I confeſs they are ill, who bids thee take them then?</l>
               <l>Or who forbids thee lay them down again.</l>
               <l>Yet that they may be read at laſt of thee,</l>
               <l>More barbarous than the place they cannot be.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> with her Poets ſhould not me compare.</l>
               <l>Though 'mongſt the <hi>Sauromates</hi> I witty were.</l>
               <l>Laſtly, I ſeek no glory to obtain,</l>
               <l>Nor that which ſpurs up wit, aſpiring fame:</l>
               <l>I would not have my mind to waſt with care,</l>
               <l>Which ſtill breaks in though they forbidden are.</l>
               <l>This makes me write, but if you ask why I ſend</l>
               <l>Theſe books, it is to viſit you my friend.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>He bids his wife not to fear,</l>
                  <l>To entreat <hi>Caeſar</hi> that he would hear</l>
                  <l>His caſe, and after be content,</l>
                  <l>To grant him milder baniſhment.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>WHen a letter comes from <hi>Pontus</hi> art thou pale?</l>
               <l>Why does thy hand in opening it even fail?</l>
               <l>Fear nor, I am well, my body which I long</l>
               <l>Did ne're inure to pains, now groweth ſtrong.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:51"/>
               <l>And being vext, by uſe doth waxe more hard,</l>
               <l>Or that to be ſick, time is now debar'd:</l>
               <l>And yet my mind of ſtrength doth get no more,</l>
               <l>My affections are the ſame they were before.</l>
               <l>Thoſe wounds which I thought time would cloſe again,</l>
               <l>As if they were new made put me to pain:</l>
               <l>Time hath ſome power to heal a little croſs,</l>
               <l>But greater ſorrows do by time grow worſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poeantius</hi> ten whole years that wound did feed,</l>
               <l>Which from the poyſoned ſnake did firſt proceed.</l>
               <l>Let part then of my grief his wrath appeaſe,</l>
               <l>And let him take ſome drops from the full ſeas.</l>
               <l>Though he take off much, yet much remain ſtill ſhall,</l>
               <l>Part of my puniſhment will be like to all.</l>
               <l>As ſhells on ſhoare, or flowers on beds of Roſes,</l>
               <l>Or as the grains which Poppy firſt diſcloſes.</l>
               <l>As beaſts in woods, or fiſh in waters ſwims,</l>
               <l>Or birds do beat the gentle air with wings:</l>
               <l>So many are my griefs, and I as well</l>
               <l>The drops of the <hi>Icarian</hi> Sea may tell.</l>
               <l>Though I hide my dangers both by ſea and Land,</l>
               <l>And how my life was ſought by every hand:</l>
               <l>In the barbarous part of all the world I lie,</l>
               <l>Which is encompaſs'd by the enemy.</l>
               <l>Since my crime is not bloudy, I ſhould be</l>
               <l>Conveyed hence, if thou didſt care for me.</l>
               <l>That God on whom the <hi>Roman</hi> power doth lee,</l>
               <l>Hath been moſt milde unto the enemy.</l>
               <l>Why do'ſt thou doubt? go and intreat for me,</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Caeſar</hi> no man can more gentle be,</l>
               <l>What ſhall I do if thou doſt me forſake?</l>
               <l>And from the broken yoke thy neck doſt take,</l>
               <l>And whence ſhall I ſome comfort now provide?</l>
               <l>Since that my ſhip doth at no anchor ride.</l>
               <l>He ſhall ſee, and to the Altar I will run,</l>
               <l>The Altar, which no hands at all doth ſhun.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:51"/>
               <l>I abſent to the abſent powers will ſpeak,</l>
               <l>If that a man to <hi>Jove</hi> his mind may break.</l>
               <l>Thou Ruler of the Empire in whoſe ſafety,</l>
               <l>The Gods do ſhew their care of <hi>Italy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The glory and example of thy land,</l>
               <l>Great as the world which thou doſt command.</l>
               <l>So dwell on earth, that heaven may thee deſire,</l>
               <l>And ſlowly to the promis'd ſtars aſpire.</l>
               <l>Spare me, and take ſome thunder back again.</l>
               <l>Enough of puniſhment will ſtill remain.</l>
               <l>Thy wrath is milde, thou granteſt me to live,</l>
               <l>And the right of a Citizen to me didſt give.</l>
               <l>Nor was my ſubſtance given away, and than,</l>
               <l>Thy Edicts calls me not a baniſht man.</l>
               <l>All which I fear'd, cauſe I did thee incenſe,</l>
               <l>But thy wrath was more milde than my offence.</l>
               <l>To baniſh me to <hi>Pontus</hi> thou didſt pleaſe,</l>
               <l>While that my Ship did cut the <hi>Scythian</hi> Seas.</l>
               <l>Thus ſent, at the <hi>Euxine</hi> ſhores I landed ſtraight,</l>
               <l>Which under the cold Pole are ſcituate,</l>
               <l>Nor with the cold aire here more vex'd am I,</l>
               <l>Nor hoary froſt which on the clods doth lie:</l>
               <l>Or that they are ignorant of the Latin tongue,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Graecian</hi> ſpeech by <hi>Getick</hi> is o'rcome,</l>
               <l>As that I am encompaſs'd round with war,</l>
               <l>So that within the walls we ſcarce ſafe are:</l>
               <l>Sometimes there's peace, but yet no truſt therein,</l>
               <l>We fear the wars until the wars begin.</l>
               <l>So I remove, may <hi>Charibdis</hi> me devour,</l>
               <l>And ſend me down unto the <hi>Stygian</hi> power.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Aetna</hi>'s ſcorching flame I'le burn with eaſe</l>
               <l>Or be thrown into the <hi>Leucadian</hi> ſeas.</l>
               <l>For to be miſerable I do not refuſe,</l>
               <l>But yet a ſafer miſery I would chuſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="elegy">
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:52"/>
               <head>ELEGIE III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>To <hi>Bacchus</hi> that he would but ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Caeſar</hi> and for him entreat.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>BAcchus,</hi> this day the Poets keep to thee,</l>
               <l>If in the time I not deceived be.</l>
               <l>Tying ſweet garlands round about their head,</l>
               <l>While much in praiſe of wine by them is ſaid.</l>
               <l>Mongſt whom while I was ſuffered by my fate,</l>
               <l>I made up one, whom thou didſt not then hate.</l>
               <l>But now plac'd under the ſtars of the Bear,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sarmatia</hi> holds me to the <hi>Getes</hi> ſo near.</l>
               <l>I that did lead a life from labour free,</l>
               <l>In my ſtudy or in the Muſes company:</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Geticks</hi> weapons laſh on every hand,</l>
               <l>Having ſuffered much before by ſea and land.</l>
               <l>Whether fate or angry Gods did this aſſign,</l>
               <l>Or that the <hi>Parcae</hi> frown'd at my birth time?</l>
               <l>Yet by thy power thou ſhouldſt have helped me,</l>
               <l>One of the adorers of thy live tree.</l>
               <l>Or can no God ever alter that decree,</l>
               <l>Which once the fatal Ladys Propheſie.</l>
               <l>Thou by deſert in Heaven a ſeat doſt hold,</l>
               <l>And mad'ſt thy way through labours manifold?</l>
               <l>Nor did thy Country always thee contain,</l>
               <l>But to the <hi>Geles</hi> and ſnowy <hi>Strymon</hi> came.</l>
               <l>To <hi>Perſis</hi> and to <hi>Ganges</hi> wandring ſtream,</l>
               <l>And all thoſe waters <hi>Indians</hi> drink unclean.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Parcae</hi> that the fatal threads do ſpin,</l>
               <l>To thee twice born, twice this decree did ſing.</l>
               <l>If I by the Example of the Gods may go,</l>
               <l>A hard eſtate of life doth keep me low:</l>
               <l>And in as heavy a manner as he fell,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Jove</hi> for bragging did from <hi>Thebes</hi> expel.</l>
               <l>When thou heardſt thy Poet was thus thunder-ſtruck,</l>
               <l>For thy mothers ſake ſome grief thou mightſt have took.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:52"/>
               <l>And looking on thy Poets might'ſt ſay thus,</l>
               <l>One here is wanting that much honour'd us.</l>
               <l>Help <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and may ſo a double vine,</l>
               <l>Burden the Elme, the grapes being full of wine.</l>
               <l>So may the <hi>Bacchae</hi> with the <hi>Satyres</hi> be,</l>
               <l>Ready to make an amazed cry to thee.</l>
               <l>And may <hi>Lycurgus</hi> bones be hardly preſt,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pentheus</hi> ghoſt from torment never reſt.</l>
               <l>So may thy wives clear crown within the sky</l>
               <l>Shine ever, and excel thoſe ſtars are nigh,</l>
               <l>Come hither and help me in my ſad eſtate,</l>
               <l>Remember I was one of thine of late.</l>
               <l>The gods have one ſociety, ſtrive to encline</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s power by that ſame power of thine.</l>
               <l>And you Poets that my fellow ſtudents be,</l>
               <l>Take wine, and after pray the ſame for me.</l>
               <l>And let ſome of you, when <hi>Ovids</hi> name he hears,</l>
               <l>Set down the cup and mingle it with tears.</l>
               <l>Saying when he doth all the reſt eſpy,</l>
               <l>Where's <hi>Ovid,</hi> once one of our company?</l>
               <l>Do this if my candour did deſerve your love,</l>
               <l>Or if I ne're did any line reprove.</l>
               <l>If while I reverence former men that writ,</l>
               <l>I am held equal not beneath in wit:</l>
               <l>If with <hi>Apollo</hi>'s favour you would frame</l>
               <l>A verſe, then keep among you ſtill my name.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>This Letter here doth well deſcry,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi>'s grief and miſery,</l>
                  <l>And it praiſeth much a friend,</l>
                  <l>That was conſtant to the end.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>I <hi>Ouids</hi> Letter, from the <hi>Euxine</hi> Land</l>
               <l>Am come, being tyred both by ſea and land:</l>
               <l>Who weeping ſaid, go thou and viſit <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy ſtate is better than my fatal doom.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:53"/>
               <l>Weeping he writ me, nor at his mouth would wet</l>
               <l>The ſeal, which to his moiſt cheeks he did ſet.</l>
               <l>If any one my cauſe of grief would know,</l>
               <l>He wiſhes I the ſumm to him ſhould ſhow:</l>
               <l>He ſees no leaves in woods, in fields no graſs,</l>
               <l>Nor how the water in full ſtreams doth paſs.</l>
               <l>He may ask why <hi>Priam</hi> griev'd for <hi>Hectors</hi> ſake,</l>
               <l>Why <hi>Philoctetes</hi> groan'd, ſtung by a Snake.</l>
               <l>Would the Gods would put him into ſuch a ſtate,</l>
               <l>That he ſhould have no cauſe to wail his fate:</l>
               <l>Yet as he ought he endures his miſerys,</l>
               <l>Nor like a wild horſe from his bridle flys:</l>
               <l>He hopes that <hi>Caeſars</hi> wrath will not ſtill laſt,</l>
               <l>Knowing no wickedneſs in his faults that's paſt.</l>
               <l>He calls to mind great <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s clemency,</l>
               <l>Which by himſelf he doth exemplifie.</l>
               <l>For that he keeps his wealth, and ſtill doth live,</l>
               <l>And is a Citizen, all this be doth give.</l>
               <l>Yet thee (if thou believ'ſt me) he doth beare,</l>
               <l>Always in mind, and above all things dear,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Patroclus</hi> and <hi>Pylades</hi> thou ſhalt be,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Theſeus</hi> and <hi>Euryalus</hi> he calls thee:</l>
               <l>Nor doth he wiſh his Country more to ſee,</l>
               <l>And thoſe things which with it now abſent be,</l>
               <l>Than to ſee thy face, than hony ſweeter ſtill:</l>
               <l>With which the <hi>Attick</hi> Bee the Hive doth fill.</l>
               <l>Oft being ſad, the time to mind he doth call,</l>
               <l>And grives that death did not prevent his fall:</l>
               <l>When ſome my ſudden miſery did ſhun,</l>
               <l>Nor to the threſhold of my houſe would come:</l>
               <l>He remembers thou moſt faithful didſt remain,</l>
               <l>If any two or three a few do name.</l>
               <l>And though amazed he did then perceive,</l>
               <l>That thou as much as he himſelf didſt grieve.</l>
               <l>Thy words and ſighs he uſually declares,</l>
               <l>And how his boſome was wet with thy tears.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:53"/>
               <l>Of which he ſays he will be mindful ever,</l>
               <l>Whether he ſee day, or the earth him cover.</l>
               <l>He would ſwear ever by his head and thine,</l>
               <l>Which as his own he eſteemed ac that time.</l>
               <l>He ſhall return thy love full thanks again,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall thy Oxen plough the ſhoare in vain.</l>
               <l>Defend a baniſh'd man, I ask what he</l>
               <l>Himſelf doth not ask, that hath well known thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Hit Wives birth he doth celebrate,</l>
                  <l>And prays ſhe may be fortunate.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>MY Wives birth-day due honour doth expect,</l>
               <l>My hands do not thoſe holy rites neglect.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> in the fartheſt part of all</l>
               <l>The world, did keep a ſolemn feſtival.</l>
               <l>Let now my tongue forget paſt griefs again,</l>
               <l>Which I fear hath forgot good words to frame.</l>
               <l>That garment which I once a year do take,</l>
               <l>I'le near being white, and unlike to my fate.</l>
               <l>And a green Altar ſhall of turf be made,</l>
               <l>And a garland round about the Altar laid.</l>
               <l>Boy give me incenſe making a fat flame,</l>
               <l>And wine that in the fire may hiſs again.</l>
               <l>Birth-day, I wiſh that thou may ſtill come here</l>
               <l>Proſperous, and unlike to mine appear.</l>
               <l>If any ill-fate hover o're my wife,</l>
               <l>Let me endure it in my wretched life.</l>
               <l>And let my ſhip bruis'd with a grievous ſtorme,</l>
               <l>Saile on her way through ſafe ſeas without harm.</l>
               <l>In her houſe and country let her take delight,</l>
               <l>'Tis enough that theſe are taken from my ſight.</l>
               <l>Though in her husband ſhe unhappy be,</l>
               <l>Lee her other part of life from clouds be free.</l>
               <l>May ſhe live and love her abſent husband now.</l>
               <l>And ſpend thoſe latter years which faces allow.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:54"/>
               <l>And mine too, but I fear my fare would give</l>
               <l>Some infection to thoſe years which ſhe doth live.</l>
               <l>Nothing is certain, for who'd thing that I,</l>
               <l>Should mongſt the <hi>Getes</hi> keep this ſolemnity?</l>
               <l>Look how the wind towards <hi>Italy</hi> now drives</l>
               <l>The ſmoak, that from the incenſe doth ariſe.</l>
               <l>There is ſenſe in the clouds, which fire doth ſhow,</l>
               <l>But what it doth portend I do not not know.</l>
               <l>When thoſe brothers once did ſacrificing ſtand,</l>
               <l>Who after were ſlain by each others hand;</l>
               <l>In two parts the black flame did upward go,</l>
               <l>As if it were by them commanded ſo.</l>
               <l>I remember once I ſaid it could not be,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Chalimachus</hi> was not believ'd of me:</l>
               <l>Now I believe, ſince thou wiſe ſmoak do'ſt bend</l>
               <l>For the North, and towards <hi>Italy</hi> do'ſt aſcend.</l>
               <l>This is the Day, which if it had not been,</l>
               <l>No feaſt-day had of wretched me been ſeen:</l>
               <l>This day brought vertues that moſt equal were,</l>
               <l>To thoſe ſame men whoſe fames did ſhine moſt clear.</l>
               <l>Chaſtity and conſtancy with her were born,</l>
               <l>But no joyes began upon that day forlorn.</l>
               <l>But labour, cares, and ſad adverſity,</l>
               <l>And like a widdow all alone to lie.</l>
               <l>Yet goodneſs by adverſity is try'd,</l>
               <l>And prais'd that doth in hardeſt times abide.</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> ſeen no troubles in his days,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Penelope</hi> had been happy without praiſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Evadne</hi> had lain in the earth unknown,</l>
               <l>If her husband conquerour from <hi>Thebes</hi> had come.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pelias</hi> Daughters one is prais'd by fame,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe married an unhappy man.</l>
               <l>Had another firſt gone on the <hi>Trojan</hi> ſhore,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Laodamia</hi> we ſhould hear no more:</l>
               <l>And that affection had been ſtill unknown,</l>
               <l>If that a fair wind in my ſails had blown</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:54"/>
               <l>You Gods, and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> which to you ſhall go</l>
               <l>When he hath liv'd out <hi>Neſtors</hi> years below.</l>
               <l>Spare not me, who due puniſhment receive,</l>
               <l>But her that doth unworthily now grieve.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Here he doth entreat his friend,</l>
                  <l>Not to leave him in the end.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THou that wert once the hope of my affairs,</l>
               <l>A refuge and a haven to my cares.</l>
               <l>Doſt thou forget thy friend in miſery?</l>
               <l>That pious office doſt thou now lay by?</l>
               <l>My burden thou ſhould'ſt not have undergone,</l>
               <l>If in this time thou would'ſt have laid it down.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Palinurus</hi> thou in the ſea doſt leave my barke,</l>
               <l>Fly not, but be thou faithful in thy Art.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Autamedon</hi> in the battel never fled,</l>
               <l>Nor left <hi>Achilles</hi> horſe unmanaged.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Podalius</hi> whom he took to cure, would ſtill</l>
               <l>Give him that help he promis'd by his skill.</l>
               <l>Better not take, than to thruſt forth a gueſt,</l>
               <l>Let my hand on thy Altar firmly reſt:</l>
               <l>To maintain me at firſt thou did'ſt intend,</l>
               <l>Me and thy judgement do thou now defend.</l>
               <l>If that there be no new offence of mine,</l>
               <l>To make thee change thy faith for any crime,</l>
               <l>My breath which I in <hi>Scythia</hi> fetch ſo ſlow,</l>
               <l>I wiſh may firſt out of my body go,</l>
               <l>E're any fault of mine thy breaſt do move,</l>
               <l>Or that I ſeem leſs worthy of thy love.</l>
               <l>We are not ſo by unjuſt fates oppreſt,</l>
               <l>That length of miſery ſhould diſturb my breaſt.</l>
               <l>Suppoſe it were, how often did <hi>Oreſtes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Speak froward words againſt his <hi>Pylades.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nay it is true that he did ſtrike his friend,</l>
               <l>Yet in friendſhip he continued to the end.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:55"/>
               <l>In this the wretched with the rich are even,</l>
               <l>That unto both much flattery is given.</l>
               <l>We give the way unto the blind, and thoſe</l>
               <l>Who are fear'd, becauſe they wear the purple cloathes.</l>
               <l>You ſhould ſpare my fortune though you ſpare not me,</l>
               <l>There is no place now angry for to be.</l>
               <l>Chuſe the leaſt ſorrow which I do ſuſtain,</l>
               <l>'Tis more than that whereof thou doſt complain.</l>
               <l>As ditches hidden are with many a reed,</l>
               <l>Or as the Bees, which do on <hi>Hybla</hi> feed,</l>
               <l>Or like thoſe grains which by the Ants are found,</l>
               <l>And in a ſmall path carried under ground.</l>
               <l>Even ſuch a troop of ſorrows compaſs me,</l>
               <l>Believe me, my complaint might greater be.</l>
               <l>He that is not content herewith, may pour</l>
               <l>Water to the Sea, or ſands unto the ſhore.</l>
               <l>Therefore thy unſeaſonable rage appeaſe,</l>
               <l>Nor leave my ſails in the midſt of the Seas.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>His miſeries he here repeats.</l>
                  <l>With the manners and habit of the <hi>Getes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </argument>
               <l>THis letter which thou readſt, from thence did come</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Iſter</hi> into the green ſea doth run.</l>
               <l>If thou enjoy'ſt thy life and ſweeteſt health,</l>
               <l>I ſhall be fortunate in that my ſelf:</l>
               <l>Doubtleſs dear friend thou askeſt how I do?</l>
               <l>Which though I ſilent were, yet thou maieſt know</l>
               <l>I am wretched, this my ſumme of grief doth give,</l>
               <l>Who e're offendeth <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſo ſhall live.</l>
               <l>If thou wouldſt know the people of this region,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Tomos,</hi> and their manners and condition.</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Getes</hi> and <hi>Graecians</hi> here do ſpread it o're,</l>
               <l>This land of rugged <hi>Getes</hi> containeth more.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sarmatians</hi> and the <hi>Getes</hi> continually,</l>
               <l>In troopes upon their Horſes do paſs by.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:55"/>
               <l>'Mongſt which theres none but bears his bow in ſhew,</l>
               <l>And Arrows which with vipers bloud look blew.</l>
               <l>A wilde voice, fierce look, deaths trueſt ſhape they have,</l>
               <l>And then their hair and beard they never ſhave.</l>
               <l>They are ready with a knife to give a wound,</l>
               <l>Which ever ſalvage by his ſide hath bound:</l>
               <l>With theſe he lives, who of you will mindful be,</l>
               <l>Thy Poet (Friend) doth theſe both hear and ſee.</l>
               <l>And may he live, and in this place ne're die,</l>
               <l>That my ghoſt from this hated place may fly.</l>
               <l>Thou writ'ſt my verſe in Theaters is ſung,</l>
               <l>And that a loud applauſe to them is rung.</l>
               <l>Thou know'ſt I have done nothing in ſtage-ways,</l>
               <l>Nor is my muſe ambitious of applauſe.</l>
               <l>Yet I like it that my memory they retain,</l>
               <l>And of a baniſh'd man keep up the name:</l>
               <l>Though when I think what hurt once from them came,</l>
               <l>I curſe my Muſes, and my verſe again.</l>
               <l>And having curs'd, I cannot them forſake,</l>
               <l>Thoſe weapons bloudied m my wounds I take<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>The ſhip torn with <hi>Euboian</hi> waves, yet after</l>
               <l>Dares freely ſail in the <hi>Capharian</hi> water.</l>
               <l>Yet I labour not for praiſe, nor take I care,</l>
               <l>To get a name, which better unknown were.</l>
               <l>With ſtudy I delight my mind, and try,</l>
               <l>To delude my ſorrows and my cares thereby.</l>
               <l>What ſhould I do on this ſame deſart ſhore?</l>
               <l>What other help for grief can I implore?</l>
               <l>The place it ſelf is unpleaſant unto me,</l>
               <l>And nothing in the world can ſadder be.</l>
               <l>The men are ſcarcely worthy of that name,</l>
               <l>More cruelty than wolves they do retain.</l>
               <l>They fear no laws, the right doth yield to wrong,</l>
               <l>The Laws are by the warlike ſword o're-come.</l>
               <l>To keep off cold, they skins and mantles weare,</l>
               <l>And their grim faces are hid with long haire.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:56"/>
               <l>In ſome of them ſome little Greek is ſound,</l>
               <l>Which is made barbarous by the <hi>Getick</hi> ſound.</l>
               <l>Amongſt theſe people there is ſcarce one man,</l>
               <l>That render common words in Latin can.</l>
               <l>I a <hi>Roman</hi> Poet (pardon me I pray,</l>
               <l>You Muſe) ſpeak in the <hi>Sarmatick</hi> way.</l>
               <l>I am aſham'd, yet through diſ-uſe I find</l>
               <l>That latine words come ſlowly to my mind.</l>
               <l>And many barbarous words this book deface,</l>
               <l>Which is no fault of mine, but of the place.</l>
               <l>Yet that I may the latin tongue not loſe,</l>
               <l>And that I may ſtill keep my voice in uſe,</l>
               <l>Thoſe un-uſed words unto my ſelf I ſpeak,</l>
               <l>And to ſtudious colours I retreat:</l>
               <l>Thus I draw on the time, and my ſelf bring,</l>
               <l>From the contemplation of my ſuſtering.</l>
               <l>By verſe I ſeek to forget my miſeries,</l>
               <l>If I get this by ſtudy, it doth ſuffice.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>To inveigh agaiſt one he doth begin,</l>
                  <l>Who had railed firſt at him.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THough I am fallen, yet I'm above thee,</l>
               <l>Than which there's nothing can inferiour be.</l>
               <l>What makes thee, wicked man, to ſtomach me?</l>
               <l>Inſulting in that which may hap to thee.</l>
               <l>Cannot my miſeries make thee ſoft and milde?</l>
               <l>For which the beaſts would weep though they are wilde.</l>
               <l>Fear'ſt thou not fortune on a globe that ſtands,</l>
               <l>Nor yet that hated Goddeſſes commands?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rhamnuſia</hi> will on thee revenged be,</l>
               <l>Becauſe thou tread'ſt upon my miſery.</l>
               <l>I have ſeen a ſhipwrack and men caſt away,</l>
               <l>Yet that the water was juſt ne're did ſay.</l>
               <l>Who once deni'd the poor ſome broken meat,</l>
               <l>Is glad himſelf of begged bread to eat.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:56"/>
               <l>Fortune doth rove with an unconſtant pace,</l>
               <l>And ne're remaineth certain in one place,</l>
               <l>Now ſhe is merry, then ſullen by and by,</l>
               <l>And conſtant only in inconſtancy,</l>
               <l>We flouriſht once, but ſoon that flower did fade,</l>
               <l>And this our ſudden blaze of ſtraw was made.</l>
               <l>Yet leſt thou cruelly rejoyce in vain,</l>
               <l>I have ſome hope to pleaſe the Gods again.</l>
               <l>My fault is not wicked, though it merit blame;</l>
               <l>And envy is wanting to encreaſe my ſhame.</l>
               <l>Beſides, from ſun-riſing till he down doth go,</l>
               <l>The world a milder man can never ſhow.</l>
               <l>And though he cannot be o'recome by ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Intreaty makes his heart grow ſoft at length.</l>
               <l>And like the Gods to whom he ſhall go at laſt,</l>
               <l>Will pardon me, and give more than I ask.</l>
               <l>It you count the fair and ſoule days in a year,</l>
               <l>You ſhall find the day hath oftner been clear,</l>
               <l>Then leaſt thou joy in my ruine any more,</l>
               <l>Think <hi>Caeſar</hi> may me once again reſtore.</l>
               <l>Think that the Prince appeas'd, it may come to paſs,</l>
               <l>That in the City thou mai'ſt ſee my face.</l>
               <l>And ſee thee baniſht for a worſe fault than this,</l>
               <l>Which is the next unto my former wiſh.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>He ſhews why his friend be dare not name,</l>
                  <l>Or mention him for fear of blame.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>IF thou would'ſt let thy name be in my verſe,</l>
               <l>How often then ſhould I thy name rehearſe?</l>
               <l>For thou the ſubject of my ſong ſhould'ſt be,</l>
               <l>And each leaf of my book ſhould mention thee.</l>
               <l>My love to thee through the City ſhould be ſpread,</l>
               <l>If baniſht, I am in the City read.</l>
               <l>The preſent age, and latter ſhould know thee,</l>
               <l>If that my writings tear antiquity,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:57"/>
               <l>And the learned Reader praiſe to thee ſhould give,</l>
               <l>And be honour'd while that I thy Poet live:</l>
               <l>'Tis <hi>Caeſer</hi>'s gift that we do breathe this air:</l>
               <l>After the Gods, thanks unto the due are.</l>
               <l>He gave me life, and thou do'ſt it maintain,</l>
               <l>That ſo I may enjoy that gift again.</l>
               <l>Some were diſmay'd my ruine for to ſee,</l>
               <l>And ſome diſmayed were for company.</l>
               <l>And behold my ſhip-wrack from ſome hill on land,</l>
               <l>And to me ſwimming would not reach their hand.</l>
               <l>Thou cald'ſt me halfe dead from the <hi>Stygian</hi> water,</l>
               <l>And mad'ſt me to remember this hereafter.</l>
               <l>May the Gods and <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſtill be friends to thee,</l>
               <l>My prayer cannot any larger be.</l>
               <l>Theſe things in my witty books I would have brought</l>
               <l>To light, if thou the ſame had'ſt fitting thought.</l>
               <l>Now though commanded for to hold her peace,</l>
               <l>My Muſe from naming thee can hardly ceaſe.</l>
               <l>As the couples cannot hold the ſtriving hound,</l>
               <l>When he the footing of the Dear hath found.</l>
               <l>As the fierce horſe with heels and head doth bear,</l>
               <l>On the Liſt-gates till they be open ſet.</l>
               <l>So my <hi>Thalia</hi> ſhut in and enclos'd,</l>
               <l>To name thee though forbidden is diſpos'd,</l>
               <l>Yet leſt a friends love hurt thee any way,</l>
               <l>Fear not, I will thy own commands obey.</l>
               <l>Becauſe thou think'ſt that I do think on thee,</l>
               <l>Since thou forbid'ſt not, I will thankful be.</l>
               <l>And while this life preſerving light I view,</l>
               <l>My ſoul ſhall always ſerve and honour you.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>He complains that he three years had ſpent</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Pontus</hi> in ſad baniſhment.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>SInce we came to <hi>Pontus Iſter</hi> twice was froze,</l>
               <l>And thrice the <hi>Euxine</hi> ſea even hardned grows.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:57"/>
               <l>But yet as many years they ſeem to me,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Troy</hi> was under the <hi>Greek</hi> enemy.</l>
               <l>Time ſeems to ſtand, ſo ſlowly it goes on,</l>
               <l>The year moſt ſlackly doth his journey run.</l>
               <l>Nor doth the Solſtice from night take away,</l>
               <l>Nor the winter never ſhortneth the day.</l>
               <l>With us the natures of things changed are,</l>
               <l>Which lengthens all things equal to my care.</l>
               <l>Or doth the time his wonted courſe go on,</l>
               <l>And only ſeem long unto me alone?</l>
               <l>While the <hi>Euxine</hi> ſhore ſo call'd by a falſe name,</l>
               <l>But more truely <hi>Scythia,</hi> doth me contain.</l>
               <l>Fierce wars the Nations round about doth threaten,</l>
               <l>Who think their living is by ſtealth well gotten.</l>
               <l>Nothing without is ſafe, the hill is fortifi'd</l>
               <l>With walls, and the nature of the place beſide.</l>
               <l>The foe like a ſhoal of birds comes in,</l>
               <l>And drives away the booty e're he's ſeen.</l>
               <l>Sometimes their darts in the ſtreets we gather up,</l>
               <l>Which do fly o're the walls the gates being ſhut.</l>
               <l>If any one to plough the earth is bold.</l>
               <l>One hand the plough, the other armes doth hold.</l>
               <l>The Shepheatd with an helmet, pipes on's read,</l>
               <l>And ſtead of Wolves, the ſheep the wars do dread.</l>
               <l>The Caſtle ſcarce defends us, wherein we fear,</l>
               <l>Cauſe the <hi>Salvages</hi> with the <hi>Graecians</hi> mixed are.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Barbarian</hi> here with us doth dwell moſt free,</l>
               <l>And the moſt houſes by him poſſeſſed be.</l>
               <l>Whom though you fear not, their looks hateful are,</l>
               <l>Their bodys covered with skins and long hair:</l>
               <l>Thoſe which from <hi>Greece</hi> are thought to be deriv'd,</l>
               <l>Their bodys with the <hi>Perſian</hi> flop doth hide.</l>
               <l>They uſe the commerce of a neighbour tongue,</l>
               <l>By geſture each thing is to mo made known.</l>
               <l>For I am underſtood by none of them,</l>
               <l>And the dull <hi>Getes</hi> the Latine words contemn.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:58"/>
               <l>They ſpeak ill of me while that I am preſent,</l>
               <l>And do object to me my baniſhment.</l>
               <l>And they do chink ill of me oftentimes,</l>
               <l>When while they ſpeak I anſwer them by ſignes.</l>
               <l>And injuſtice is more cruel than the ſword,</l>
               <l>Some in the Court with wounds are often goar'd.</l>
               <l>Hard <hi>Lacheſis</hi> thou gav'ſt too long a thred</l>
               <l>Of life to me, under an ill ſtar bred.</l>
               <l>Thu my Countries ſight, and friends I now do want,</l>
               <l>And thus in <hi>Scythia</hi> do make my complaint.</l>
               <l>Both grievous are, I have deſerv'd from <hi>Rome</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To be baniſht, not to ſuch a place to come.</l>
               <l>What ſpeak I madly? I deſerv'd to die,</l>
               <l>When I offended <hi>Caeſars</hi> Majeſty.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>To his wiſe 'cauſe ſome did her defame,</l>
                  <l>And call her wife to a baniſh'd man.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THy Letter which thou ſendſt me doth complain,</l>
               <l>That ſome one call'd thee wiſe to a baniſht man.</l>
               <l>I griev'd not that my life is ill ſpoke by,</l>
               <l>Who now have us'd to ſuffer valiantly:</l>
               <l>But that I am a cauſe of ſhame to thee,</l>
               <l>And I think thou bluſheſt at my miſery.</l>
               <l>Endure, thou haſt ſuffered more even for my ſake,</l>
               <l>When the Princes wrath me from thee firſt did take.</l>
               <l>He's deceiv'd who calleth me a baniſh'd man,</l>
               <l>My fault a gentler puniſhment did attain.</l>
               <l>Our ſhip though broke is not o'rewhelm'd or drown'd,</l>
               <l>It bears up ſtill, though it no Port hath found.</l>
               <l>My life, my wealth, my right he doth not take,</l>
               <l>Which I deſerv'd to loſe for my faults ſake.</l>
               <l>To offend him was a puniſhment far more,</l>
               <l>I wiſh my funeral hour had gone before.</l>
               <l>But becauſe no wickedneſs was in my fault,</l>
               <l>To baniſh me he only fitteſt, thought.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:58"/>
               <l>As to thoſe whoſe numbers cannot reckon'd be,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Majeſty was milde to me.</l>
               <l>Therefore my verſes by right as they may,</l>
               <l>O <hi>Caeſar,</hi> do ſing forth thy praiſe alway.</l>
               <l>I beſeech the Gods to ſhut up Heavens Gate,</l>
               <l>And let thee be a God on earth in ſtate.</l>
               <l>But thou that call'ſt me thus a baniſht man,</l>
               <l>Encreaſe not my ſorrow with a feigned name.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>To his friend who wiſh'd him to delight</l>
                  <l>Himſelf, while he did verſes write.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>THou writ'ſt that I ſhould paſs the time away</l>
               <l>With ſtudy, leſt my mind with ruſt decay.</l>
               <l>'Tis hard (my friend) verſe is a merry taske,</l>
               <l>And it a quiet mind doth always aske.</l>
               <l>Our fate is droven by an adverſe wind,</l>
               <l>No chance more ſad than mine can be aſſign'd.</l>
               <l>Thou wouldſt have <hi>Priam</hi> at his ſons death jeſt,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Niobe</hi> dance as it were at a feaſt.</l>
               <l>Ought I to ſtudy or elſe to lament?</l>
               <l>That alone unto the fartheſt <hi>Getes</hi> am ſent.</l>
               <l>Give me a breaſt with ſo much ſtrength ſuſtain'd,</l>
               <l>Such as <hi>Anytus</hi> had, as it is fam'd.</l>
               <l>So great a weight would ſink his wit at length,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joves</hi> anger is above all human ſtrength.</l>
               <l>That old man which <hi>Apollo</hi> wiſe did call,</l>
               <l>In ſuch a caſe would not have wit at all.</l>
               <l>Though I forget my Country and my ſelf,</l>
               <l>And have no ſenſe at all of my loſt wealth:</l>
               <l>To do my office fear doth me forbid,</l>
               <l>Being compaſs'd in with foes on every ſide.</l>
               <l>Beſides, my vein grows dull being ruſted o're,</l>
               <l>And now it is far leſſer than before.</l>
               <l>The field if that it be not daily till'd,</l>
               <l>Will nothing elſe but thornes, and knot-graſs yield.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:59"/>
               <l>The Horſe having long ſtood ſtill will badly run,</l>
               <l>And be laſt of thoſe that from the Liſts do come.</l>
               <l>The boat that hath long out of water been,</l>
               <l>Grows rotten, and the chinks thereof are ſeen.</l>
               <l>Then hope not I that had an humble vein,</l>
               <l>Can e're return like to my ſelf again.</l>
               <l>My wit by my long ſuffering is decay'd,</l>
               <l>And part of my former vigour now doth fade.</l>
               <l>Sometimes my Tables in my hand I take,</l>
               <l>And I my words to run in feet would make.</l>
               <l>I can write no verſes but ſuch as you ſee,</l>
               <l>Fitting the place and their Authours miſery.</l>
               <l>And laſtly, glory gives ſtrength to a ſtrain,</l>
               <l>And love of praiſe, doth make a fruitful vein.</l>
               <l>I was allur'd with hope of fame before,</l>
               <l>While as a proſperous wind my ſails out bore:</l>
               <l>But now in glory I take not delight,</l>
               <l>I had rather be unknown if that I might.</l>
               <l>Becauſe that ſome my verſe at firſt did like,</l>
               <l>Would'ſt thou have me therefore proceed to write?</l>
               <l>May I ſpeak it with your leave you ſiſters nine,</l>
               <l>You chiefly caus'd this baniſhment of mine.</l>
               <l>As the maker of the Bull in it did ſmart,</l>
               <l>So I am alſo puniſh'd by my Art.</l>
               <l>And now with verſe I ought for to have done,</l>
               <l>And being ſhipwrack'd I the ſea ſhould ſhun,</l>
               <l>Suppoſe that ſtudy I ſhould again aſſay,</l>
               <l>This place is unfit for verſes any way.</l>
               <l>Here are no books, nor none to lend an ear,</l>
               <l>Nor none can underſtand me if they hear.</l>
               <l>All places here both rude and wilde are found,</l>
               <l>And filled with the fearful <hi>Getick</hi> ſound.</l>
               <l>I have forgot in Latine for to ſpeak,</l>
               <l>And I have learnt the language of the <hi>Gete.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet to ſpeak truth, I cannot ſo reſtrain,</l>
               <l>My Muſe but ſometime ſhe a verſe will frame.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:59"/>
               <l>I write, and then I burn thoſe books again,</l>
               <l>And thus my ſtudy endeth in a flame.</l>
               <l>I cannot make a verſe, nor do deſire,</l>
               <l>Which makes me put my labour in the fire.</l>
               <l>No part of my invention to you came,</l>
               <l>But that which was ſtole or ſnatch'd from the flame.</l>
               <l>And would that Art too had been burnt for me,</l>
               <l>Which brought the Authour unto miſery!</l>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>Here he doth accuſe his friend,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he did no letters ſend.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>FRom the <hi>Gettick</hi> Land thy <hi>Ovid</hi> ſends thee heath,</l>
               <l>If one can ſend what he doth want himſelf.</l>
               <l>For my mind from my body infected is,</l>
               <l>Leſt my part of me ſhould torment miſs.</l>
               <l>A pain in my ſide me many days doth hold,</l>
               <l>Which I had gotten by the winters cold.</l>
               <l>If thou art well, then we in part are well,</l>
               <l>For thou didſt under-prop me when I fell.</l>
               <l>Thou gav'ſt me many pledges of thy heart,</l>
               <l>And did'ſt defend me ſtill in every part.</l>
               <l>'Tis thy fault that Letters thou doſt ſeldome ſend,</l>
               <l>Thou performed'ſt deeds, deny'ſt words to thy friend.</l>
               <l>Pray mend this fault, which if you ſhall correct,</l>
               <l>In thee alone there will be no defect.</l>
               <l>I would accuſe thee more, but it may be,</l>
               <l>Thy Letter being ſent came not to me.</l>
               <l>May this complaint of mine ſeem raſh and hot,</l>
               <l>May I falſely think that thou haſt me forgot.</l>
               <l>Which as I pray for I am ſure to find,</l>
               <l>For I can ne're believe thou haſt chang'd thy mind.</l>
               <l>Gray worm-wood ſhall in the cold ſea be ſcant,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Sycilian Hybla,</hi> ſhall ſweet hony want.</l>
               <l>E're thou in remembring of thy friend grow ſlack,</l>
               <l>The threds ſure of my fate are not ſo black.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:60"/>
               <l>And that thou may'ſt avoid ſo foule a crime,</l>
               <l>What thou art not, beware thou do not ſeem.</l>
               <l>And as we were wont to paſs the time away,</l>
               <l>With ſome diſcourſe, till we had ſpent the day,</l>
               <l>Let Letters carry and fetch back our words,</l>
               <l>While hands and paper tongues to us affords.</l>
               <l>But leſt I ſeem too diſtruſtful for to be,</l>
               <l>And that theſe few lines may admoniſh thee.</l>
               <l>Take my Farewel, which word doth Letters end,</l>
               <l>And may fortune better fates unto the ſend.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="elegy">
               <head>ELEGIE XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid</hi> ſhews his wife that ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Shall by his books immortal be.</l>
               </argument>
               <l>WHat a memorial my books give to thee?</l>
               <l>Thou Wife more dearer than my ſelf mai'ſt ſee.</l>
               <l>Though fortune from their Authour do detract,</l>
               <l>Yet by my wit thy fame ſhall be exact.</l>
               <l>While I am read, thy fame ſhall too be read,</l>
               <l>Which cannot in the funeral fire lie dead:</l>
               <l>And though thou ſeem'ſt unhappy by my fate,</l>
               <l>Yet ſome ſhall wiſh to be in thy eſtate:</l>
               <l>Who 'cauſe thou bearſt part of my miſery,</l>
               <l>May call thee happy, and may envie thee.</l>
               <l>By giving riches thou no more hadſt got,</l>
               <l>Since the rich-mans ghoſt from hence doth carry nought,</l>
               <l>But I have given thee fame that ſtill ſhall laſt,</l>
               <l>The greateſt gift that I could give thou haſt.</l>
               <l>And 'cauſe thou doſt defend me in my trouble,</l>
               <l>This maketh honour come upon the double.</l>
               <l>For that my voice doth ever mention thee,</l>
               <l>Thy husbands love may ſtill thy glory be.</l>
               <l>And leſt ſome call thee raſh, abide to the end,</l>
               <l>Both me and thy faith ſee that thou defend:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:59618:60"/>
               <l>For while we ſtood, thou only didſt maintain,</l>
               <l>Thy goodneſs free from any fault or blame.</l>
               <l>Which is not ruin'd by this fault of mine.</l>
               <l>Thy vertue now may make thy works to ſhine.</l>
               <l>'Tis eaſie to be good, when we remove</l>
               <l>All occaſions that may make wives not to love.</l>
               <l>But in thunder if the ſhower ſhe do not ſhun,</l>
               <l>Such affection doth true marriage-love become,</l>
               <l>Rare is that love which fortune doth not guide,</l>
               <l>But when ſhe flies away doth firm abide.</l>
               <l>If vertue a reward to any be,</l>
               <l>Shewing moſt courage in adverſity,</l>
               <l>Thy vertue in no age ſhall be conceal'd,</l>
               <l>But through the world admired and reveal'd.</l>
               <l>Thou ſeeſt <hi>Penelope</hi> doth ſtill retain,</l>
               <l>For conſtancy an unextinguiſh'd name.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Admetus</hi> and brave <hi>Hectors</hi> wife are ſung,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hiphias</hi> wife that into fire did run.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Phylacean</hi> wife by fame new life hath found,</l>
               <l>Whoſe husband firſt ſet foot on <hi>Trojan</hi> ground.</l>
               <l>I do not need thy death, ſhew love to me.</l>
               <l>And thence thou ſhalt get fame moſt eaſily.</l>
               <l>Nor think I exhort thee, cauſe that thou doſt fail,</l>
               <l>Though the ſhip go with oares, we put on ſail.</l>
               <l>He that exhorts, doth praiſe what thou doſt do.</l>
               <l>And by exhorting doth his liking ſhow.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
